okay next we are talk we will be talking
about hamiltonian path problem we want
to prove that hamiltonian path problem
is mp complete
so for the same
[Music]
style actually
we
want to reduce here okay we want to
reduce three set two hamiltonian path
problem okay
and in order to prove that firstly we
want to
we want to say that hamiltonian path
problem is
itself is in np okay and i don't want to
repeat that because we already talked
about this
uh
for
you know previously we have hamiltonian
first problem as the example by np
uh problems in mp so continuous problem
is in mpo or you can think of
uh polynomial time verifier is easier to
implement so that would be
that won't be a problem
then given
a three-set
instance which is a boolean formula in
3cmf
we want to convert it the formula to a
graph a directed graph actually a
directed graph and specify as a node as
and a node t
so that the formula is satisfiable if
and only if
that's directed graph with the specified
snt
has a com uh
as a hamiltonian path from s to t okay
so how do we do that
it's also quite easy
if we are given
a boolean formula three in string c and
f that'll be like this way
and
uh remember that i'm not sure uh
this
is uh
corrected
okay uh
don't be confused because there is a
there is an arrow here you see that a1
b1 c1 a1b
a2 b2 c2 and a
k b k c k okay
these abc is just bring variables or
literals and
don't be confused with
cj here
and the c1 through ck here
this c1 and
is not this c1 okay
these nodes here
mean the c here means clause
okay not the c in the formula they are
just you know
name clash that's
name conflict
okay so that's an arrow
so you you can just think of like
a1 b1 d1 a2 b2 d2 ak bk dk okay
so let's see here and here is not the c
there they are just called means crosses
okay
that's the most important thing for this
graph because
some of you may just
feel it's very strange that why we do c
not a or b no because those c is not the
c in the clause
the c
on the graph is close means close okay
okay
then
we have a putting formula in 3cf and
then you go through the formula once
and you know that
you have in this example you have k
clauses right k clauses
and you will know that how many
variables you have
because
it may be you know x1 x2 x1 bar x2 x1
bar x2 x3
etc then probably you will have like
let's say l close uh
l variables and k clauses
right availables k clauses
after collecting
these uh this information after
collecting this information
firstly
we construct
a diamond shape
graph
for
each boolean
variables
not literal variables
for
that example i have like you have x1
here
x1 bar here x1 and x1 bar
are the same variable okay same variable
so you just need
a structure for one x one
that's it okay so the diamond
shaped uh graph is like you have uh
you have uh this node
as the
start node or begin
node and an end node
then
you have directed pass this way and
these two node and go back here
and you have
many nodes in between and then you have
the directory pass go
right and go
left
so finally you have
this diamond shaped structure and how
many nodes you need to have
between you know the left and right
depends on how many uh calls you have
and will and actually depends on
how many times
this variable is used
in the clause
as uh
you know so as long as you have enough
notes in between then that will be okay
and what is enough we will
later you will know uh how many okay
because during the construction you know
at some upper bound of the node you
should have that
or not up about lower bound the node you
should have as long as you have enough
node then there will be no problem
anyway a diamond shape
okay
and
since we know that there are l green
variables we have arrow diamond shapes
right then we connect them together
like this one
and we specify
s
and t
okay
so that'll be
an easy implementation implementation
for the whole thing right
so
we haven't we haven't finished our
conversion okay we haven't finished our
conversion
let's examine this structure first
okay we specify s here
and t here let me ask you a question
is there on this graph
alone
is there
a hamiltonian path
from s2t
yes
there actually there are
many hamiltonian paths
right
for example you can
go this way
and all the way here then you go this
way
and go this way
and
go here and all the way here
right and repeat this the whole thing
you get a hamiltonian pass to t
right
and how many hamiltonian pairs actually
in fact
you
have
exactly
two
julie l
hamiltonian path
right
why because you have x1 x2
xl diamond shape and for each diamond
shape
from the stars note you can select going
left or going right
either way
it's a hamiltonian path right
so you have two choice here two choices
here and you have two choices here so
totally
so many hamiltonian paths
then you know that
okay it's exactly
the number
of
truth assignments
to the l variables right
for each variable you can have left
and right
false and true
so
let's say
if we consider going left as
setting
the boolean variable to
true
and going right
setting the boolean variable to false
then
the structural diamond connected the
diamond structure alone
is capable of expressing
all possible truth assignments for the l
variables
right
understand this
part is very
critical for the proof
as long as you know what i'm saying then
you understand why we
uh understand the next thing we are
going to do
okay
okay so we have created we have created
a structure
and containing two to the arrow
hamiltonian path
but as i said we haven't finished the
proof we still have something to do
so
since we have
k clauses
for each clause
we give it a note
so
c1
close one okay not c one here let's see
right here close one close two close
three to close k
okay
since the whole thing here is the graph
we want to output
and
before connecting
close this node
with the main structure
we won't have hamiltonian path right
at this time
and
then
we look at
what
variable or literal
used
in each clause
let's give it an example for example we
have
x1
x to bar
x4
okay
then
in the structure of x1
we choose
note
without overlapping with others okay two
notes
and
assuming that going left making
the variable true and the going right
making the variable false
add a h
from the left
of the pair to c1
and then going back to the right
node
okay
and then c1 has x2 bar right so we also
have
choose 2 a pair
then since it's x2 bar
from right note going to c1
and
going to left node
so the same thing goes to x4 we choose
two node
and since it's uh
x2 sorry x4 so from
lab to c1 and then goes back to c2
so that will be
uh
the way we connect closest note with the
main structure like
we have in the textbook
so if
cj contains xj we choose
non-overlapping
pair of nodes and from left
to right
if cj contains xj bar
the same thing then
go here and here
okay
so
according to
one variables
either you know itself or negation of
itself
uh be used
in the clauses
you need you will need to have
you know something like this
and then
you know you need
probably need a node to separate each
pair
note separate each pair nodes separate
each pair
and finally here something like this
and
go
back
go there go back or go there go back
something like this
so
if a variable
be used like three times
you will need
three three plus one this one
so many notes to separate the usage and
to avoid confusing then it will be okay
okay
then
how can we be sure that
after doing the connection according to
the usage of the boolean formula
of the
variables or literals
then
it will fulfill our you know conversion
maybe with disability relationship
so it's like
again let's go back to
it's doing this
and
okay something like this
see
let's say
after converting
a three cnf formula into the directive
graph like this
firstly
we want to say that
this formula oh
three sets
this formula belongs to three sets
if and only if
the graph we have here
belongs to
hamiltonian pass
okay
let's go this direction first
so
if the formula
is satisfiable that means
that means
there is
a truth assignment
there is a truth assignment
satisfy the formula
right
then
firstly we start from on the graph we
start from s
according to the truth assignment for
each variable
firstly we ignore
the connection between the main
structure and the clause structure
and you just go through all the node on
the main structure according to
that
according to that
truth assignment that's no problem right
then
we check
for example if c1
in the original formula
is satisfied by
as our example okay by x2 bar
by x2 bar
then x2 bar
must be false right
so
on the diamond structure i on the
diamond shape x2 bar is false that means
you will have a flow
go
right at first and go through this way
right
then x2 c1 is satisfied by the true of
x2 bar
that means you will have a path from the
pair of the rhino
go to c1
so c1 is reached
and then go back to the right note
that's a left node and then go on
with the past
right
so since each clause
is satisfied by at least one literal
then you just need
to deviate the path from the main
structure
to the close and the back to the main
so
if the formula
is satisfiable
the truth assignment satisfies that
formula
can be translated
directly here into
a hamiltonian phase on our whole graph
from s to t that's no problem
well usually uh someone
can get confused with that they say that
okay um for example
when you go here and back here how can
you go again
to see what
well you don't need to
okay there is no uh requirement that
whenever you
have a pass to go to the closed
structure you you need to go no there is
no such requirement we just need to take
the deviation once
for each cause
so there's no problem
another confusion is that
if
if for example if c1
that's our example is like c c 1 is x 1
x 2 x 4 right that's our example
if x y is true x 2 bar
is true
and what happened
well nothing happened you just need to
choose one of them you don't need to go
both
right the confusion raised
because you think you have to go c to 1
twice no you don't need to do that
if there are more than one literal to be
true in a close
you just need to choose one
right you just need to choose one
then
so uh again
we have uh
explained that
then if we don't consider closed nodes
the main structure alone you have to
truly error paths right
after finish the whole graph how many
hamiltonian paths you have actually
that's very interesting because for
mapping with disability we don't care
about how many
just you know at least the one
but if you really want to know how many
of them it depends on
the formula
if
exactly
one liter role of each clause to be true
then you will have exactly
one hamiltonian path
right because
you can only
go through the clause notes
when you reach the
literal to be true for that clause
so exactly one
for example if you have like
two
and two here
then
you will have four hemingtonian path
okay
so think about it and you will know the
whole thing
uh whole concept of the proof here
okay now we know that uh
if
there is a truth assignment for the
formula
to be true then that truth assignment
can be translated
to the graph we generated
uh to a hamiltonian
path
of the graph we translated
uh generated right and
let's say
this direction
somehow we know that
if somehow we know that okay the graph
we generated really has a hamiltonian
path
how can we be sure that
the original formula is satisfiable
well the same reason
since
someone draws a hamiltonian for you
hamiltonian path on the graph for you
and
not only main structure okay and every
closed node has been reached have been
reached
then you just need to translate
uh the path
if it goes left then x1 is false
right
sorry right if it goes left uh left here
x2 is true if right false etc and
finally for example
right then false
and
this truth assignment
can make the original formula true why
because according to the assignment
all clauses
are reached
they are satisfied
so the original formula is true
so the convert uh
the process uh the procedure to convert
a from a cmf formula three cnn formula
to this graph
satisfies
me reducibility and the whole conversion
time is within the polynomial of the
length why because
l variable must be less than you know
the dense right and
k closes everything is
well bounded by the polynomial bound of
the length of the input string
so there's no problem for this
conversion to be in within polynomial
time
so we have a polynomial time reduction
from three set
to hamiltonian path and hypotenuse
itself is in mp
then
we proved
and methane path to be
empty complete
all right
now
see we use threeset to prove other
problem to bmp complete
and we want to show
we don't need to use three set okay we
can use hamiltonian pass
to prove
undirected hamiltonian path
to be mp complete
okay
so what is um directly on the campus
that means
uh
you have a graph undirected graph and
specify snt
and is there a hamiltonian
is there a path from s to g
and also all nodes in that graph
is reached exactly once
okay that's on directly hamiltonian path
so on the right hand maintenance itself
is n is the mp why because you can write
a polynomial verifier
and
someone give you the path you just need
to check if it's all on the graph if yes
and then to check if all the nodes on
the graph is reached exactly once if yes
then
you know
accept it
so that's pretty straightforward
verifier
so it's england p
so that's reduced hamiltonian path to
underwriting hematanian path
and how to reduce
a hymenom pest
to un
direct metallic patch
what is hamiltonian path again
so you will have a direct
directed graph g directly right and
specified
a node s and then the node t
this
is an instance of hamiltonian path
okay
and let let me uh emphasize it again
when we get the problem instance like
this we don't know the answer what means
by we don't know the answer we don't
know if there is
really a hamiltonian path from s2t on
the graph okay we don't know the answer
remember that
don't
think about that we know the answer no
we don't know so the whole process for
conversion we convert the problem
instance to another
to
a problem instance of another problem
the conversion itself
doesn't know the answer
knowing the answer is not a requirement
for the conversion
again that like
like the process we introduced here
or here
we don't need to know the answer to do
the conversion okay remember that we
don't need to know the answer
we can just do the conversion that's why
we need to prove that
if
the original problem is yes
then the converted problem is yes and
vice versa that's why we need to prove
it but for probably instance we don't
know the answer okay that's very
important
okay
so
for
for a hamilton uh hemingtonian problem
instance we have g
nc
right
since we have g
and we know
that we know actually they are specified
in the problem snt
we
expand g
for each node in g for each node in g
except except for s and t okay
we make
note for example u1
in g
sorry we should actually
if we uh
if there is a u1 in g
we make it three notes
u1
let me
write it this way
u1 in
middle
out
so for each node in g other than s and t
we make them
three nodes
all right
so if you have a node u2
we make it
u2 in
u2
like middle and the u2
out so in middle out
so if you have a u3 another node we make
it u3 in
u3 middle and u3 out three
and we have h remember undirected so
underrated h here
here here
and as
we have
one node s out
and t we have one node t in
okay
so for notes
for
the original g
we converted it to underrated graph and
the forward vertex we basically copy s
as s out t as t in and for other all
other nodes we
have three nodes for each node
like what we just introduced okay
so that will be
the vertex of our
underrated graph
and for h
then we just copy
uh
well not all but
basically all ages
what all ages
since the a the h on the directed graph
is directed right
so for example you have
u1 to u
q
so we
connect u1 out
to
u2e
okay
so for every ui
to uj we connect ui out
to
u j in on our underage graph
so if you have a
u3
to u2 so you can make u3 out to u2 in
if you also have a u2 to u3 so you can
we connect u2 out to u3 in
that's it so we basically command
the directed
h
on the original graph
on our undirected graph we
do
from out node of that node to the in
node of the target node
and then
we only copy uh edges from s
auto r from s to other nodes not
edges from other nodes to s we don't
connect those agents why because there
is no point to do that since we are
asking if there is a hamiltonian path
from s to t there is you know
it doesn't make sense to consider
into s right so for the same reason
there is no need to consider
out of t so that's why we have only s
out and the t in
okay
so for example we have uh s2
u1 in
oru maybe from the the original graph we
also have
s out to
u3 in and we have u1 out in u2 out team
something like that
so we can produce according to the
original directive graph we can produce
an underrated graph this way
and then we specify s out
and the t in
so that would be the pro uh problem
instance for the
hamiltonian path
okay
so
if i give you any hamiltonian path
probably instance
you don't need to know the answer you
can convert it into
um undirected hamiltonian paths probably
instance right
that's what i said we don't need to the
conversion
we do the conversion we don't need to
know the answer the conversion is
independent of the answer itself
that's why from chapter five actually
when we talk about
reduction when we talk about mapping
reducibility
we are not solving problems
we don't know the answer to
the problem we are given
we just you know rubber wrong the
problem as an other
that's it
that's
reduction
okay don't forget it okay
okay now here comes the well difficult
part not really difficult but difficult
part
why
such a
conversion gives you
relationship deck this one is
hamiltonian path this one is
if and only if this one is an
hamiltonian pest why
because
if the problem we are given if the
hamiltonian
path proper instance we are given really
has a hemitandian path like this one
so from s
from s
go to some node and some node and
t
and these are the
all the nodes in g
and every node is reached
exactly once
this path
can be
translated
onto the undirected graph
for instance
we construct it as this one
right remember how we produce that graph
from s out
since
there is a path from s to t
on our graph we really have a path
to u1 in right
and since u1
u1
becomes
three
nodes
we have has
we have edge between these two nodes
right
so
of course uh okay i i
maybe maybe this is good
we have passed here
and then u1 to u2 we have passed here
right
and the u2 is the three node we have
paste here
and the u2 goes next we have pass here
see the trick here
since each note
is separate
as three note
and
you always
from s out
you go to some in node
right you go to something note
even you have something like this
something like this or
this this
okay
when you go to
the in node of some original node
next step you cannot
go
here
uh sorry let's finish the this direction
first
so firstly if we really have
a hamiltonian pace on
the original graph
that path
can easily be translated
to the hamiltonian path on our
undirected graph right
there's no problem with that right
because that's how we uh generated our
undirected graph
okay
then
we want to say the opposite that
if on our
graph
there is a
there is a path
like
what we described here okay there is a
path
then why
we can say that there is a path here
because
on our graph
you will start from s out
to some in node so to to the in node of
some nodes okay that's kind of weird
anyway
the next step you cannot go
here
like this one you have to go through its
in node and then our node and connect it
to some in node some other node
why
again because if at this moment
if you step on
the in node
and you go other way
for example go here
then
you will never be able
to go back here
so the in node here will not be step
through then
a hamiltonian path on the undirected
graph cannot be formed
to form a hamiltonian path on the
undirected graph the
middle node the middle node here
must be stacked through
when
the in node
is reached
otherwise the middle note will not be
stepped through will not be reached then
a hamiltonian pass cannot be formed okay
that's the tricky part of how we do it
so actually if you split one origin node
into
four
nodes
it works too into five nodes it works
too
but if you split only to two nodes you
say okay it's in is out
it doesn't work
okay because it is possible
you know something like this can happen
in if you split the note only two in and
out because you can have something like
you will have some
s out goes here then you don't step
through all node and go
otherwise you know you can come here and
go here then you know arbitrary go
somewhere
and in the end that would
that kind of pass cannot be translated
back to
the directed path no
so
you must have at least one middle node
and as long as you have one little node
it works so one to
any number of it doesn't matter
so if on the underrated graph we have
some hemitanium pass here then you know
such an undirected hemitempest
can be translate back to the hemitanian
path from s2t on the original graph with
without any problem
because
in middle out
is
a note
in middle out
is a node
etc right and
why we can do
this because on the original graph there
is a directed pass
so
hamiltonian pairs
the prob uh the problem instance we are
given has a hamiltonian path
the undirected graph we translated
we generated have a hamiltonian pest
and vice versa so that's why we proved
that
we can uh prove we reduce hamiltonian
pass to on direct and hamiltonian path
and then pre proof on
the right-hand tempest is
also ng-complete
okay and the conversion is of course
within polynomial time because we just
expand the graph like you know
about three
uh three
times triple the notes actually triple
the note
minus two actually anyway
oh
yeah actually minus four
so
the
last uh
problem is subset sum
okay
and we want to prove subsystem isn't be
complete we also you know the same
technique we reduce three sets to subset
some
and firstly we want to prove something
sum is in mp and you know i don't want
to repeat that again because subsets of
is also an example we are using as you
know problems in mp so that's it's in np
no problem
now we just need to uh provide the
conversion from subset sum to
so sorry
from a problem instance of three sets
two subsets
okay
then
remember that
what is the instance of three
set that will be a
formula in three cms right and what is a
problem instance for subsystem
we want we we we have a multiset of
integers and
a sum
right that's that's a subsystem okay
so
if
we are given
a boolean formula in three c and f
then
again
you read the whole formula once
and you will know that
in this formula there are arrow boolean
variables
and there are k
clause
right
after you scan the whole thing you know
that you know the information here
then
the conversion
begins with
we prepare a table like
uh figure
7.5 57 here
so firstly we know that there are l
boolean variables
so
we make
two
l
rows
like this
okay no problem right
and k close
we make
two k
rows like this
okay
so with you know uh y l
y one z one y two z two
y l zero that they
those are just nem naming
for convenience
okay because i can explain the whole
thing better with the names here but
that's not necessary
and also g1 h1
through to gkhk that's all still just
uh convenient
the naming makes the explanation
convenient okay
and then for column
we have
l column here
okay and
k column here
so
for given
formula in three c and f we know that
air variables k close so we prepare a
table
with
two l
plus two k
rows and l
plus k
columns
okay
so
now we start to feel the table
okay
so
firstly this part
empty
nothing to feel
okay no problem right
then
for the uh
for
the two l rows part
very easy
one
and a zero zero zero zero zero zero
okay
one
zero zero zero zero zero zero
and the one
one
or zero on the left sorry on the right
and
one one
0 0 here and 2 1 1 here so that's why i
use the two arrow rows l columns
no problem right
then
we
you know
feel uh going through the same feeling
we have this part
so one one
all the left
hand zero one one all the left out right
right uh side zero
and then
finally one one
okay
so for the next
area here is very easy
you look at the formula
okay you look at the formula
for first clause
for example
if
first clause is x1
or x2 bar
or x3
for the boolean variable
we mark y
for the
negation of the boolean variable we mark
z
so
we mark y one z two
y
three
okay
so y one
z2
y3
and all others are zero
or other level okay
and
uh if you have duplicate like what x1 or
x1 or x1
you just need to fill
the one sorry y1
okay
so we just examine each clause so for
this one we mark
y one z two
uh y three and four
uh this example is like
y two so
that must be x2 right
and y3 that must be x3 and we don't know
the third one anyway so for each
clause
for each clause
we mark the corresponding position of
the boolean
well literal
for
x1 we mark for x i
we mark
i
as one
for x one x i bar we mark z i s one
that's it
so we can
fill the
last part
this area this way
no problem right
okay for the last row here there's a
last row here okay
we just feel 1 1 1 1 one and a three
three three
three that's it
okay
now we finish the table
okay after finish table and the question
you ask is that okay subset sum we need
to have a multiset of integers
where is the subset of uh sorry multiset
of integers
actually
we consider
each row
okay
we consider not not include y2 just you
know consider each row
as
one
there's a mole integer or actually you
can do other base doesn't matter
uh
you cannot do binary because we have
three here okay
other than
uh
where the bay a base greater than three
works
okay as long as the base is greater than
three it works
so easy for decimal right
so we consider for example
this one is
one okay
and then we have one zero
right so that's that's ten
and we have one zero zero that's 100
that's it so we consider each row
as an integer that's it so how many
integers we have in s the multiset
we have
two l plus 2k
integers
although those integers are probably
very very large but they are integers
any problem no yeah
then we specify sum
here so that's a very very large integer
you have
l1 and k3 right
so
t and that's our
subset sum problem
instance
okay
so conversion is finished
and the whole conversion
time is apparently polynomial to the
length of the you know
three cnf formula
okay
now the final the last part is that
why the given formula satisfiable
our subject sum
uh
per instance is can be solved
because
you
see
if
if the
formula is satisfiable
we just adjust we just need to
select
the corresponding y and z
according to
the literal
actually according to the truth
assignment for example
if x1 is false
we choose
v1
if x
2 is true
we choose y2
okay
something like that
so
we just
since
the
formula is satisfiable we just choose
we just choose
y or z according to the truth assignment
after choosing these rows
you see y1 and z1 you choose one y2 and
z2 will choose one etc so we will choose
l rows actually arrow integers from our
multiset right
and
add them together
what do you have
apparently you will have one one one one
one
exactly here
and then
one two three
one
not
not two okay
one
two
three
you have a number between one and three
after adding the l
integers
right
then
we just need to choose
rows
from
the k rows actually k integers
to make
the number exactly three
okay
and why is one two three not zero to
three
because that truth assignment satisfy
the formula
that means
for the column here
there will be at least one there
maybe two maybe three but at least one
right
so
after choosing the l integers here and
add them together we will have
this area and then we can choose
appropriate integers from this part to
make them exactly three
so
if the formula is satisfiable the stop
says some problem instance we converted
can really be you know so you can really
selected some of the
uh
some integers from the multiset to make
them add up to
t
the specified sum
okay
so that's one direction the other
direction is that if someone asks you
the subset some permissions like this
and
there is really
some integers
selected from the two l plus two k
integers and add up to be exactly the
sum
why the original
formula is satisfiable
well it's very easy because you see
from this part
you know that select
integers from this part alone
cannot
make three
right cannot make three
why
because at most two for each column
right
so
select from this part alone cannot max3
and
according to this you can conclude that
at least one comes from the upper part
okay comes from the other part
and
since the integer here
you selected add up to
one in this area
each
column is one in this area
and we don't have
things here right
that means
from
the l
integers here
you
the the integer you selected
must be
from y1 and v one you select one integer
y two and the z two you select one y
three and the z three you select one and
et cetera
why because if you don't
you know among these two so that uh
select this one how can you add up one
here
the same thing goes to this one this one
this one and every one
right so we know that if from the subset
sum
we can select some integer and add up to
you know the t here
there must be
uh from each two
rows you select one integer and also
that
and also that
this part of area cannot make three
alone must be there there must be at
least one from the upper area
so these two relation comes together you
know that
since
you have
each pair you select one
those selection can be translated into a
boolean choose assignment
if you select y
that
boolean variable is set to true if we
select uh from z
that boolean variable is set to false
and
setting that variable to true or false
the cause all closed
is satisfied
because there is at least one from this
area to make
this part
okay so
if the sound has a uh you know uh
if the converted
snt is really
in subset sum that means
the original pulling formula is
satisfiable
then our
proof is completed
because we established the mapping
reducibility property and
the whole conversion can be
completed within a polynomial time
okay
so
we have
proved
subset sum
is undecomplete
okay
so that's uh
that's all we have finished the
uh
our course for the whole semester
and
good luck with your
final examination