okay
now we have defined a new kind of
finite automata which is uh capable of
non-deterministic computation and we
call this kind of finite automata
non-deterministic finite automata and we
will call it
nfa later and also
we prove that
nfas and the dfas are equivalent
okay so
we can extend our definition of regular
languages
to the computational
model of an effect that means we
can have the result here that
a language is regular if and only if
some non-deterministic finite automata
recognize it
therefore if we want to prove some
language
is regular now in addition to
deterministic finite automata we can
use non-deterministic final automata
why because if we can successfully
construct
a non-deterministic finite automata to
recognize
the language we want to prove as regular
after we construct that nfa we can use
the construction procedure of
the proof we used in
theorem 1.39
to get the equivalent dfa
so we proved that language is regular
okay now we have this result we can use
it
to complete our proof on
the three regular operations the closure
property
of the three regular operations
so firstly we want to prove
the class of regular languages is closed
under the union operation again
yes which is also the theorem 1.25
so this time we use nfa
to do the proof in order to
use nfa to prove the closure property of
the union
operation the assumption criteria are
the same
so we have two regular languages
let's say it's a1 and
a2 okay
they are a1 and a2
they are regular languages and by
definition
we will have dfas
to recognize a1 and a2 respectively
and of course also nfa now
assume that n1 which is then
nfa recognized a1
and n2 recognizes a2
so we got n1's
machine details and also
the five tuple five components
of eight and two based on
you can consider them as uh source code
of n1 and n2
and based on the let's say source code
downloaded from github
we want to construct and here like we
did
in 1.25
we want to construct a new nfa here to
recognize the union of
a1 and a2 okay
so let's visualize n1 and 2 as the block
diagram as the figure on the left part
let's say n1 has some states
right and we there is a star state and
the sum
accept states and two are the same
and our idea is that we want to build
a new nfa like
this one mainly by
copy copy
and one and copy the whole n2 here
so within the two
block the two blocks they are
n1 and the n2 respectively
then the idea is that we want to add a
new
start state here so we add one state
here
and we have epsilon
epsilon transition to the star states of
n1 and n2
so as long as you are familiar with
the operation of non-determined finite
automata
then you know that let's say
when processing
an input string for n1
so for n1
there will be a processing tree
right for
n1 there will be a process in three like
this
and for the same input string
like let's say n2 will be up
operating like this
right something like this one
then what we want to do is we construct
a new machine
and when start processing
w start from the start state
of n start from the start state of
n then you don't consume
any input you go to
n1 and also n2 so
see that's the beauty of
non-deterministic computation here
so you see when the
process the thread goes to
these state
what and one will get all still the
original input w and
and to the same so you see they are well
they will run in parallel and
if any of the states here
is a start state then n accept w
and vice versa as long as one of
n1 or n2 accept w
then the whole machine whole new machine
accepts w
right so that's why we can use
non-deterministic final automata
to recognize a1 and the a2
i mean the union of a1 and a2
right so either one of either side of
the
new machine accepts the input string
then the whole machine accepts the input
string that's why
the newly constructed nfa
will recognize the union of
a1 and a2
so i think the idea here is not
so complicated it's actually more
straightforward than the dfa one
right then of course drawing the diagram
is easy
but we anyway still need for more
describe the whole
constructions okay so how to do that
it's actually easy because to construct
an
nfa we need to scr uh describe
in detail what are the five five
components
are what what the five components are
and here we also simplified the scenario
here
we assume that the two languages
share the same alphabet
in this case we don't need to
do the alphabet thing because they are
the same okay so that's
uh for the for one of the
five components okay let's take the
second one
is the states of our new machine
so we define the state of the new
machine
remember that we want to copy and one
here
so we want to have all the states and
one half
and we want to copy the n2 here so we
want to have
all the states and two halves
we want the machine to have that then
we add a new
states here state here so the
states of our new machine will have q0
and all states from
n1 and all states from n2
so we do a union of the three sets here
okay so uh
please note that here actually here we
have a
very important assumption
but the assumption is too easy if
the assumption is actually trivial for
mathematicians
so they don't uh write it
explicitly what assumption is that we
assume that q1
and q2
are disjoint that means the intersection
of q1 and q2
is nothing there is no
states shared by q1 and q2
see that's a problem that's that's a
problem about
the convention or definition of
mathematics because we use sets
to describe q1 q2 and whatever we want
to do
for the new machine instead let's say
if q1 you have
1 q 2 as its states
and the q 2 you have q 2 q
3 q 4 s it
states and the union what is that
that will be q1 q2
q3 and q4 right
but it is not what we want
because for example in here q2 in here
and q2 in here are different states
actually so we don't want these results
we want five states and the separated
into machines right
so we basically assume that there's
nothing
duplicated for q1 and q2
and the question you will ask is that
okay so
what if in in a way real situation
there are duplicate members for q1 and
q2 and we want to do the proof
and do the construction of the new
machine what should we do
that's pretty easy because remember that
in modern
programming languages there are
mechanisms for this one of them is
namespace
okay so you can easily
rename all the states here
as q1 underscore
q1 q1 underscore
q2 and all states for q2
you rename them as q2 underscore
q2 q2 underscore q3
and so on and when you do a union of the
two sets there will be no problem at
all right just like you download some
source code from
github or you copy it copy them from
your
i don't know classmates and you want to
put the source code together to make it
work
sometimes there will be variable name
problem
and in a way you can you know according
to different source files
you do the namespace the concept not
the programming language mechanism
itself but
you can do some pretty easy
find and replace find and re
replace to rename all the variables
uniquely for each file then there will
be no problems to put them together
although it is you know quite detailed
but
you have to know that there are
assumptions
here in the proof then
you will be i think you can understand
it better to why we write
the proof this way and it is a
important detail for non-mathematicians
we will also have this in later proofs
so i describe it
i try to describe it more clearly here
okay so we have all the states we want
here
then q0 here
is our new start state so we specify
that
for this for
another component
then since q1 and the q2
are disjoint they have no
duplicate members f1 f2
of course no duplicate member for them
because
f1 is a subset of q1 and f2 is a subset
of q2 so the accept states
of our new nfa
is q sorry f1
and f2 the union of f1 and
f2 okay so all the states of
original n1 and n2 are accepts
accept states of our new machine now we
have
four four components
the final one the essential
the uh the final essential one is our
transition function
for the new machine
and how do we write the transition
function remember that
at this stage there is
no transition at all okay
so we need to copy all
transitions in one
two here and all transitions
in n2 to here and add
this one epsilon transition ends this
one epsilon transition
okay so to copy the
transitions defined by n1
we just need to copy
n1's transition
so if the states here is
in original states of
n1 we just call delta 1 right
we copy all the transitions of n1
similarly we do that for n2
okay now for these two
block n1 and n2
we actually copy the whole machine
now we want to do
these these new states
q0 added by our construction
so if q here
is q 0
we add epsilon transition
to q1 and q2
okay to q1
what is q1 the star state of n1
and what is q2 the star state of
n2 as n2 yes
and for all symbols
remember that a symbol is
in
this alphabet which is the original
alphabet
and also possibly the empty string
so for o a in empty string
it goes to q1 and q2 and
otherwise nowhere
okay nowhere so there is no uh
arrow out of q0 if
some symbol is consumed
okay
so now you can see that for any queue
in the state and any symbol
in the alphabet of this one
our transition function is
well defined
so
the nfa is constructed and
it it is pretty straightforward to see
that and we already
described the reason why the newly
constructed
nfa can recognize the union
of a1 and a2 right because
you can think of that there is an input
stream for
the nfa after
as soon as after the machine
is booted then one thread
directly start from n1
star state and also at the same time
in parallel there is a thread here from
the start state of n2 and they both
process the input string the same input
string
right and for the property of
non-deterministic computation
as long as one one of
n1 of one of or one of
n2 except the string the whole machine
accept the string that is why
the machine accepts the union of
a1 and a2 okay
so if there is no other
problem here we need to make also two
nodes here
one unlike
unlike the proof the construction
we used for theorem 125
that is we use dfa to
prove the same thing the union uh the
closure property of the union operation
on regular language
unlike that this proof
cannot be extend
to intersection
okay as you see in that proof
it's pretty easy to transform the proof
to prove the colossal property of the
intersection
operation but here we cannot do that
because the whole machine here
are separated parts
and there is no as i described
previously
there is no communication between
threads or
processes so we cannot
do something like okay
n1 accepts the string and
and to accept the string we cannot do
that
with the framework with the
computational model
of nfa that's impossible so
at least for this construction here
we cannot extend to prove
we cannot extend this proof here to
prove
the closure property of the intersection
operation
the second note here is that
like that in the previous proof
with dfa this proof cannot
extend to proof
the closure property of the union
operation
of infinite regular languages
why because you see the construction
of our new nfa we need to
have so many states
right for n1
we know that it is
a finite number and for n2
it is a finite number so
the cardinality of our states
the number of our states is 1 which is
q0
and the plus a finite number plus
a finite number right so of course
the whole number will be finite and
the constructing machine is the finite
finite
automata but
if you want to
say that you have infinite regular
languages
then you will need to union a lot of
actually infinite
states right so in this way
we have no way to bound
the quantity here
we have no way to bound the quantity
here
so we cannot extend we cannot extend
the construction to prove
union the cultural property of union
operation
on infinite regular languages
that's the same as the previous
construction with dfa
okay so compare this
to proof i think it will be easier
to get yourself familiar with
the property of interface
and also dfa actually
okay so
that's a recap of you know what we
have already seen now
we can do the
next regular operation
which is concatenation here
previously we don't we don't know how to
proceed with the computation model of
dfa
right now we have a new weapon which
is an fa we can try to do that with an
fa
and you may ask uh okay what's the
difference
what's the difference between using nfa
and
using dfa if you remember that
with dfa we don't know how to split the
string
so we try the first part and the second
part
we feed the first part to the first
machine and the second part of the
second machine we don't know how to
split it
but with nfa we can what we can do we
can do this one
see if there is a input string here
we can try if the first
machine can accept this part
because we can just put w into
first machine right after putting into
the first machine
and it you know process one symbol by
one symbol by one symbol
and some states may
some some of the process may stay on the
on one of the accept states then at that
time
at that time this part
of the string can be accepted by
the first machine then we try to feed
the rest of the string into the second
machine
right but the beauty of
non-deterministic computation
is here that the original process
can still go on so
we have a new process doing this
attempt and the original process can go
on
and find an other
part of the input stream
which can be accepted by the first
machine and we try
the rest
and the feed them to feed these
symbols to the second machine
and that's a new process the original
process can still
goes on and we find this one
and every time when a part of the input
string can be accepted
by the first machine we focus new
process
and fits the rest of the input string
into the second machine and by repeating
the whole
process and the focusing all necessary
all necessary processes
we can try all possible
let's say split point
right for example if you have a
string like this and you've you just
need to feed the first one first machine
and
you found that okay uh one sorry zero
one one
is accept can be accepted by the first
machine then you focus process
you feed the rest of the string
two and two but you
still the original process still goes on
for example you find that oh
0 1 1 0 1 1
is is also accepted by the first machine
then you feed this one
to the second machine with a new fork
new
process and also you
continue the original process and you
may find that
okay this will be
another split point and you test it
with n2 so
by doing this way with the capability of
non-deterministic computation for the
operation of concatenation we can try
all possible three points right
is that interesting so how to do the
construction
it's very straightforward actually as
long as you understand the
previous proof of the union operation
we are doing the same thing basically
so now assume that
a1 and a2 are regular languages and
n1 and n2 are
layer recognizers so
n1 is here and n2 is here what we want
to construct
is a new machine and and
we copy all
and one here and the whole end to here
then what we want to do is in the new
machine
in a new machine the original
the original accept states of m1
is no longer accept states will be
are no longer accept states but the
original
accept states of n2 are still already
accepted of our new machine
okay that's the
some slight changes and
we add as i emphasize that
we add new
epsilon transition that from the
original
accept states of n1 we
have abstrom transition to
the accepts the star state of n2
and that's it that's our construction
okay
so n1 star states is the star state of
our new machine
so by doing this construction
you can easily see what i just described
in the previous slide that
if you have input string here
you put into our new machine right
so whenever the
input goes to for example
one of the process goes to here
then if this part
of the input string is putting
onto the original n1
it accepts right
and under our newly constructed machine
you can see that
everything is usual for the part of n1
but we have a new
epson transition into the start state of
n2 right so we will
test this part of input
on n2
so if n2 accepts then
it is a string by combinating
the string one of the string accepted by
n1
and one of the string accepted by n2
right but of course
this transition is a new
is a new process so original process
still goes on
right so perhaps here
we the the one of the uh plus
one of the computational branch reaches
here
again what a new process
is created and start from n2
star state so we will try this part on
n2 and
we know that this power can be accepted
by a one right
so repeating all the process here we
actually can
test all possible split points and
as long as one of them works
then we know a string
is a concatenation is one of the company
combination
of a1 and a2
right so
how to formally describe the
construction of this machine
again we want to construct this machine
here
we need to describe the five components
and of course for simplicity and without
loss of generality
we assume that they use the same
alphabet
if different alphabets are
are used then we will have a have many
entries in our transition functions but
uh it's not difficult to write them all
but
there will be now necessary details to
the proof of of this theorem because we
want to do
we want to introduce the concept of how
to construct a
machine to recognize concentration and
that's
detailed that part of detail is not
helpful
okay so firstly the state of the
construction uh the
machine will be the union of q1 and q2
and we we don't need extra state right
it's very easy and also remember that
q1 and q2 are assumed
to be disjoint the intersection of them
is mt set okay so we put them together
without causing any mass
then q1 which is the start state of the
original
n1 is our new start state
of the machine
and f2 which are
f2 which is the set of the accept states
of
n2 is our accept state
so finally we need to
deal with transition function here
so for any
q in our queue
let's see if q in q1
and not one of the accept states
we copy all of them
okay if q
is in f1 see
in the first line we didn't consider q
in f1 now we consider queuing f1
so qf1 and the symbol
is not epsilon we
also copy everything
and finally if killing f1
and epsilon for the symbol
we still copy everything but
we add one more transition
to the star state of n2
okay so this this part will be
many students forget
this part why we write the whole thing
this way
because by copy
the whole machine you need to keep
everything here and we only
add a new chance
epsilon transition and why we don't do
that
uh in other places because it is
quite possible that uh okay sorry i
should
say that some of uh previously someone
said that why do we just write something
like this
then you probably changed
your part you may probably change the
transition function of n1
right because it is possible that
originally there is an epsom
transition here then if you write it
this way
this transition will be you know deleted
actually and only f-zone two here
that'll be wrong because you change the
machine then
the machine is no longer n1 and
you know it will no longer recognize
a1 so you need to keep everything
identical to its original state so
copy everything and only add something
you want to add
okay then for n2
we just need to copy everything we don't
have
a lot of extra work to do
then it's done
so that will be the proof
to the theorem that the class of regular
languages
is closed under the concatenation
operation
okay
so finally we want to prove
the class of regular languages is closed
under the star
operation okay
and remember that what is the star
operation
the star operation is like you have a
language
right as we described previously
you have a language and
the star operation means you
artificially
add epsilon
let's say if the language
a here has no empty string
then after doing the star version
somehow there is an empty string there
if a here has an empty string
then there will be no problem right
anyway you add empty string here and
union with a itself and the union
a let's use this symbol here which is
concatenation
a and also a
concatenation oh sorry okay nation twice
and infinitely
so some uh we usually
denote the set here
as a 0 power and
a 1 a squared
a cubic
and so on so which is
i from 0 to infinity
a i so that would be star operation
and you see that star operation
you can actually consider star operation
consists of union right
union so we have union here
union here union here union here and a
lot of union
and it also consists of
concatenation concatenation here
and four or
at accessor so since we are we already
know how to construct
c concatenation here and
union here we just need to do
the same thing and the
machine is concatenate
with itself and doing union with itself
okay so what does that mean
that means
we have a regular language a1
and the corresponding recognizer and nfa
is n1 here then the five components of
n1 is these five components
then we want to construct a and
new nfan recognizing a one star
okay so firstly
we want to remember that a1 star what is
that
that would be a new artificial added
string here
so in order to do that we add
a new state here
and add a new state here and also the
new state
is will be the will be one of the
accept states in our newly constructed
machine
so we added this string here
then we copy the whole
n1 here okay copy the whole n1 here
so let's say at this moment
if we don't do any other extra stuff
then what will be the new machine here
recognized it will recognize
a one itself right
with this one
right because this one will be
recognized by
here and the absorb here that means
when the machine is booted there will be
two processes one
goes on and one
so it will recognize originally what
a one is and the list states will make
this string one of the recognized
language
okay so if you have no problem
then see that we need to
concatenate the machine itself back to
the star uh content this machine to
itself
so we just need to add
epson transition back to its
star state right
when we do this what will
uh happen it's like the conconnation
operation proof
so you see that when you have a input
string
whenever on
the n1 part the process goes to one of
the accepts
accept states then there will be a new
process focused here
start from the original star state
right so repeat the whole thing
it might if finally
this string is accepted by the machine
then every time every time
one of the acceptance is stepped on
means it is a split point
so for this particular example
string w is actually in
a 1 4 right
because this part in a1 this part in
a1 this part in a1 and
this part in a1 and
it is also possible that
you have like a way to separate the
string
so w may also be in a 1
2 something like like that but you can
easily know that anyway
as long as the input string
is accepted by our new machine
the input string is either absolute if
input string is epsilon then it will be
accepted right
if input string is either if the new
machine here accepts the string the
input string will either be epsilon
or it can be separate
into several segments and
each of them is in
a1 so that's
why we also write the
definition of
star operation oh sorry
like here
see so that's actually the definition we
have in section 1.1.5
okay so if you have no problem regarding
the proof idea here the construction the
formal construction
is pretty straightforward like the
previous one we have
we just need to
copy everything
from n1 at one state which is a star
uh accept states also and our start new
start state
and epson to the start state
and the epsilon through a star state
epsilon through star state
that's it so our
new machine has the original q1 of n1
with one extra state the one extra state
is the star state and the accept states
is the original
accept states with one more
newly added q0 okay
then we copy every transition like
in the previous proof that for all
original states uh
which is not uh and accept states we
copy them
copy all the transition function and for
states of the accept states and apps
non-app song transition we copy
everything
and for this situation we still copy
and add one
back to its star state
okay and for the newly
sorry for the original star state
accept state no star state yes
for the newly added star state here
we add epsilon transition
the original start state
okay so that would be this transition
so here is the original
dates back to the start star state and
here is our new star states
epsilon to the start state that's it
and from the new state everything else
noun empty symbols
goes nowhere okay
so that will be the proof formal
description
of the proof
to the class of regular languages is
closed under the star operation
okay