okay
once more we know that
context-free language
context languages are not all possible
languages given in alphabet we are going
to discuss the closure properties of
context-free languages we will try to
know some
operations under which
the context of languages is closed
okay
and the first operation of
is substitution we we are going to
introduce a new operation here which is
called uh substitution
a substitution uh
actually a substitution is a
generalization of the homomorphism we
defined in the study of regular
languages so you can go back to chapter
1 to see the definition of of hormone
vision so that you will know
why it is a generalization
so uh simply put
a substitution
is defined on
an alphabet
and map to a set of a string
a set of strings or sorry a set of
strings
so
for example if you have alphabet
0 and 1
and you want to map
to
another strings on another alphabet like
a b
c something like that
one possible substitution e may be
s of zero
map2 for example a a
b c a a
b b c something like that
or you map one two
let's say
a star b
c c
b something like that okay so
uh it is a regular expression so that
means you actually map two infinite
strings like
b c c b
a b c c b
a
square b c c b et cetera right
so as long as you define a map
of
each symbol
of an alphabet to
some strings
a set of strings then we call that
a substitution
okay
then
as long as you define a substitution you
can
extend this substitution
into
see we define on alphabet which is each
symbol
and we can be this substitution can be
extended into
strings and languages okay
so for strings that will be
given n
given
a substitution as
we define we extend the definition to
the domain of strings
with
empty string mapped to empty string
and each
strings
each string
the last one
map2
see that's the original substitution
here
and then
that's a recursive definition go back to
here
okay so we already explain explain such
extension in
actually the extended transition for dfi
nfa or
the extension in homomorphism right so
it's the same thing
and when we extend the
definition given substitution
to
languages
so
the
domain becomes a set of strings
and that's even easier
we just
get everything
in the string
sorry in every string in the language
and
map to
listing
and what is this
this goes back to
the extension here
okay
so
okay uh understand it as
you just get every string
from the language
then
you look up
what
uh
what sets of the strings can this string
map too
and then you just collect every possible
strings into a language then we call it
the substitution extension of the
original one okay
so here
we want to
prove that
if you have a language
l
which is a context free language over
some alphabet
sigma
and
if you have a substitution s
defined on sigma
such that
each
symbol in the alphabet sigma
the language
you mapped to
don't forget that
a set of strings
is a language
okay a set of a language is just a set
of strings
so
if each
for each other for each symbol in the
alphabet
the substitution map to some
context free language
then we can prove that
the whole language l beer
the substitution
with the extension like this
is also
a cfl
okay that's what we want to prove here
so how to prove that we can just
construct the
grammar for the mapped language okay
so
let's say
since l
since l is
a context-free language
there must be some context context-free
grammar generating that language right
so
let g
be the context-free grammar for l here
so a contextual grammar is a full tuple
you have variable alphabets rows and
stars variable one of the variable right
and
since for each symbol in the
alphabet
for each symbol in the alphabet
the mapped
language for each symbol is also
a countless free language right
so let's say there will be grammars for
each of them for each language so let's
say the grammar for symbol a
is this one
okay so if you think of a concrete
example like your alphabet is 0 1
then
in the proof here
in a proof here you have
l which is on sigma star a subset of
sigma star right
so you have a l and the g is the context
free for that l
then
you have a substitution
s and s of 0
is the language
you mapped
symbol 0 2 and s of 1
is the language
you s map 1 the symbol one two right
and
since
s of zero is a context free language we
know that there is a context free
grammar g zero
generated generating s of zero and we
also have another contextual grammar g1
generating s of one okay
so ga here
is
j here represents so many
different
grammars okay for each symbol in
alphabet
for each symbol here for each symbol in
alphabet so
let's construct it
let's construct a new grammar g prime
here for s of l
okay
and let's say since g prime is a
contextual grammar we need to explain
the four
components
variable
terminals
rules and star variable okay
so what is the b prime here
v prime is the union of v
and
all the a's
okay
so you have uh
you just need to do a union of
all variables of the original
grammar for l and o
variable for vas
or variables
okay so that's our v prime v prime
then
sigma prime which is the terminals for
the mapped language
that will be the union of
all sigma a's
okay or sigma x
and here is the ace with b
so that's slightly different
why because
you map
string in l into strings
on
the union of sigma s
okay
so that's our sigma prime
then
what is the start variable here actually
the start variable here is the original
star variable of l okay we have we don't
have that here but yes
s prime is actually s
then what are our rules
okay
the rules consist of
firstly
all rules in each
grammar for each symbol
okay all rules
in each ra that's grammars for
the language mapped by each symbol
via the substitution
and then
we copy the rules in r which is the
rules for
l
rules for the grammar generating l
but we replace
all terminal each terminal we replace
each terminal
with
sa
okay we replace each terminal with sa
let's
go for an example here
let's see
you have a
language l
let's say uh
let's say this example okay
so
and what is a grammar the grammar is as
epsilon right and also as 0 as
1 that's it
so this grammar can generate this
language let's say the language here is
this one and
the grammar here is
a variable only s and
terminal 01
and the rules is the two rules here
let's say two rows here
and s is our
star variable
so let's say we have a substitution for
zero and the map to
s of zero and the grammar is g zero and
one g one okay
so
we copy all the rules are zero
and the union
are one
and union what
the two rules but we change them
first rule
we just copy it because epsilon is
actual and the second rule which change
change
we change that
change zero to
s zero
and
s is s and s one okay
so that's it that's our
r prime
so
the construction is done like this
okay
so actually if you want to cut finish
the proof we need to
prove that
every string
in
fg prime if and only if every string in
s of l
okay we need to do the proof
to finish it but we omit the this part
and we just talk about
informally why it works you can think of
that
for l
since the grammar g
generated arrow that means
l of g
is l right
so for every string for every string in
l
you have a pass three from s which is
the start variable
you have a pass three right
for
some string in l
right
and then
for each symbol
will be mapped to a set of string
because for each symbol for example uh
this 0 is 1
and the 0 will be matched to match to a
set of string s of 0 right
and of course
this
set of strings is also a contextual
language so everything in here
can be generated here
as a right
so for the construction here we replace
zero here as s0
right at one here as s1
something like that
then
we will start here
to have a pass three according to
g zero
and
possibly generate all
strings of s of zero here and also s of
one here and here
so
that will be
exactly
s
of l
and the whole thing here
is a pass three
is a pass three start from s
start from s and according to
g prime here
okay so that is why
if you have
a substitution and
you have a contextual language and the
substitution for
each symbol
map to some
context free language
then the whole
arrow
will be mapped to some context free
language
okay so that's we call
close your property for the operation of
substitution
and remember that
if you don't have this criteria that
s of a
is a complex free language if you don't
have criteria
like this then
this theorem doesn't hold why because
you can think of a very easy
uh counter example if you
don't have a criteria like this
for example if we have a alphabet
zero one
okay
then
we have a language
just
just 0
and which is a string and only of length
1 and only 0 okay
then we said that we have a
substitution
s0 map to a n b n c n
and
greater or equal to 0 and s 1
map to
only
empty string okay
so is this a substitution yes it is but
it doesn't
have the property that
s of a is a context free language right
this is not we have proof that we have
proven
that language is not a context free
language so for language here
if l is this one
s of l what is that that would be
exactly
this language right
and
you can easily
know that this language is not
a context free language
so you we
have to have
criteria here even
l is a context free language
is this a context free language yes it
is
right because you have you can write a
grammar like s becomes 0 that's it
then
substitution
also need to have this property so we
have the closure property
okay
so that's for substitution and
substitution is a generalization of
homomorphism
why
because
substitute substitution is a symbol
mapping to a set of string
and the homomorphism is a simple map to
a string
and a set of string
you know uh if a symbol can only map to
one string that would be a special case
map into a set of strings right so
that's a generalization of
so let's see other closure properties we
want to check here
that
a and b
be context-free languages and r
b
regular language
okay
so firstly we want to prove that
substitution
has the closure property and we already
did okay so
and don't remember don't forget that
for
the substitution each
each language must be also cfl so we do
so then
it works
for closure property okay
then
we need to
we need to prove the
context of the class of context free
language
the context with languages is closed
under the
union operation
okay
so how to prove it
since a is a context free language
you have a grammar a
right then
you will have the va
sigma a
rule a and
star variable a
okay
and also for g sorry also for
grammar for language b right a b
[Music]
sigma b
r b
s b let's say
then
what is a
the union of a and b
we can easily construct a new grammar
and we do
all
variable union as our variable
and of course sigma union as our
alphabet
and then
we have all rules
add together
with
new rules or new rules
we need
a new variable okay so we need a new
variable
which is our
start variable for the grammar we are
going to construct and then
we union
r here what is r
r is
r contains two rules first rule is our s
may become
s a
second rule is s may become as b
then we finish the proof
right
why because you see
all strings
in language a
can be generated
from our star variable the first step of
derivation becomes s a
right then
it will become all
strings in a
and we can also go
this direction right uh this way
and it will go
you will derive all possible strings in
b
see
that's why
the new grammar g here the language of
the new grammar g here is a
and b
union
right actually we've seen this
right so
for uh
easier
we can write it this way
right so that'll be union of two regular
uh contextual languages
so as you can see
all context-free languages
can be
we can do the union
for finite context language via this
construction of
grammar
and you cannot do infinite because
you see when you do
the union of variables a union of
alphabet
if you have infinite context with
languages this number cannot be bounded
as a finite number it possibly goes
infinite so it doesn't work for infinite
country languages okay
then
the next operation is concatenation
so that's
very easy as we described previously
we have
ga and gb
right so we just need to we also uh do
the union of variables
alphabets rules and
stuff like that
and
we add
one
symbol sorry one variable
in
va and vb so that's our
uh
that's variable for our new grammar
and we copy the we we do the union on
alphabet then we just need to add
one new rule
as may become s a
s b
okay just one
and of course you need to
keep o rule a and row b
then s is our new star variable okay so
let's
do this
okay so that's our lingual sigma
grammar
then why it it can generate the
concentration of a and b
because you see
so start from our start variable here
the first derivation the first step of
derivation
is exactly s a as b
right
then s a may become all possible strings
in a
and s b becomes all possible strings in
b then
all this
is exactly the combination of a and b
okay
then if you have no problem
with union and concatenation
it's very easy to do the start start
operation
we don't even
need to add
new
level we just need to
add two
new rules
first rule is
sa
may become
empty string
right
because remember that for star operation
we have an artificial added empty string
into the language no matter the original
language has empty string or not
so we add this rule for that
then we just need to
add another rule to do the repeat
because a star
is what a 0 that is
this one
union
a right union a square
cubic
etc
so
we just need to add
this rule
then that's it right
because we can use this rule indefinite
times
so we can create square
cubic etc
right if you don't understand here you
can think that firstly
sn may directly become epsom right
that's here
and the sa can
become all strings
in a
that's here
right if you don't use this rule then
the original language can be generated
then you if you use this rule once
as a
as a and then you don't you don't want
to use this rule anymore you will get a
square
right sorry
then if you use this rule
twice like
first time
second time then you get
three cubic right
so
you can use the this row indefinite
times to create all possibility here
that's why
the class of
context free languages is closed under
the operation of star star operation
then next
the reversal
we've defined reversal in
chapter one so we don't do we don't want
to do that again okay so for reversal
in context free language is easier to
well
similarly
easy to prove because you just need to
rewrite all all the rules
that say you have a grammar
for the language a
and you have variable a
you have sigma a you have
row a and
star variable a right
then
for all the rules here you have the
ahead and may become a body right you
just need to rewrite all the rule the
body to the reversal then you will get
that
for expo for an e easy example like 0 1
and 1
and
[Music]
ok
then
the rule is like
sigma
zero s one right
then we just need to reverse
these and this
so since empty string there's no
difference here and
one as
visual
right then you will get
the reversal of the language
okay so that will be
assume a is here and the ar
is here
so you just need to rewrite
or you're not you just need to reverse
the body of each rule you will get
the reversal of that language okay so
the class of context-free language is
closed under the operation of reversal
okay
soho for homomorphism
well we don't really need to prove it
because i just described that
homomorphism is a special case of
substitution
and
if you have a for homomorphism
which is that
for every
symbol in the given alphabet for example
zero
the homomorphism map zero into a
string right for example this string a a
or one two
a b b c
something like that
and since it mapped to only one string
if you consider one string as a
set of string
then
this language
is
is a context free context free language
actually it's a regular language right
because every language has finite number
of strings
actually it's a regular language so it
is definitely context free language so
it is also context-free language
and then the homomorphism
actually
satisfies the definition
for
the our crucial property of substitution
so homomorphism
i should say so the class of
context-free languages is closed
under the operation of homomorphism
okay
and if you want to directly proof it it
you can also
uh
use that actually i'll use the
homomorphism here
okay so assume that a is a context free
language
then
there will be rules right
rules
then you just need to rewrite
within the rules you rewrite the
terminal part
and replace them with the string mapped
two
okay so
for exactly this example how do i do
that
again let's use the
language here
then we have two rules right
and epsilon is is okay there is no
terminals actually and for this rule
we replace zero as a a
and one as abbc so
we rewrite
a rule as
a s a b b c that's it
see for the for the rules for the bodies
of the rules you just need to rewrite
all the terminals
as the string that's
mapped to by the homomorphism then you
can get
h of a
and of course
since h of a can be described by the
changed by the modified rules like this
it is a context-free
language
okay so a class of context with
languages is closed under the operation
of homomorphism
okay
then for inverse homomorphism uh if you
are interested in
uh how to prove
the closure property you can look up uh
in on the internet we will
omit that proof here because we don't
have further use for inverse
homomorphism in our
uh
in our course this semester
and
the proof idea for inverse hormone is
basically
the ideas we introduce in the proof for
regular languages but since for inverse
homomorphism we we are using pda if you
remember
that
in regular language we use
dfa so that's pretty easy you just need
to construct a new
machine for that
but for context free language
we use pda here and you you need more
constructions and that's too much for
for here so i will i mean that if you
are interested it's pretty easy to find
a
proof on the web okay
so
next one is intersection
okay
but intersection you we will know that
um
that let's say
if a and b
are
regular context-free languages
actually
the intersection of two
context-free language
may not
maybe
and may not be countess three languages
okay
so firstly it may be
for example if you have the same context
free language the intersection of the
same language and if a is context three
then a the intersection of a and a is of
course context-free right there's no
need to discuss that
and
it is possible that two-context-free
language the
intersection of two context free
language is not context free let's give
uh let's have an example here okay
so if you remember we uh
last time we are pro uh we were proving
that there is inherently ambiguous
context-free languages right
so that that language is a
i
b j
c k and what
i equal to j or
j
equal to
k
and if you remember
uh we firstly proved that this language
is a context free language by
constructing the grammar right
so for the first part here
we have a become bc a may become bc b
may become let's say epsilon
a b
b
and c may become
epsilon
c a
right
and then
d
e f
for the second part
and e may become
let's say
epsilon
a
e
and f may become
epsilon
b f c
right
and we say that uh we can do the union
here so add one more variable
become a or d and 2 rule
that's union right
and
if you think about it
the left part
will generate
right
and the
right hand side will generate a i b
j
c j
something like that
and consider
the language
of
constructed by doing the
intersection of
the two languages
okay so what do you get you will get a
and b and c n
and
equal to or greater than zero
right
so you see
two
regular languages
that's let's say uh
a
and b
the union of a and b is regular no
problem but for this particular example
a
and b the intersection of a and b is not
context free
so
there is no closure probability
generally for the intersection of two
context-free languages
okay so this one we have proved that
it's not contestant
then
the intersection here is not between two
context-free languages
it is a context free language
and a regular language
okay
so if you have a country language and a
regular language you can do intersection
of them you still get a context free
language okay
then how do we prove that
and we can prove that by contro using
pda and dfa
so the proof idea is that this for a you
have a pda right
and what is a pda
a pda is essentially
an nfa
right
and nfa
then
with
a stack
right that's a pda
and for the uh for regular language r
here
pdf4a
okay for
regular language r here you have a dfa
okay so what is dfa
you know that you have a star uh start
start state and several states
and perhaps some
accept states something like that
right
and you just need to
combine these two machines
to do
intersection and how to do that
the construction is
very similar to the first theorem we
prove
the closure property for
regular language under the operation of
union we combine two dfas right
we do a cartesian product of the states
of two dfas and
we just combine them and look up where
to go
and here we do the same thing
see
for this uh
for this state
for example one
and let's say
uh that we have n
n state here and m state here
okay
so
we
construct a state set of
so many states actually we also do a
cartesian product
then
you will have something like
1 in the original
pda a
and
1 for dfa
okay then one two
two one
and
and then two
one
two and
and n one
sorry
n1
and m right
and for this row
for rows
for rows is like
the dfa
state for columns it's like an fa a tda
state right
then
you just need to merge
the transition function as we have
in the construction
for the
union
of two regular language
okay so for example for pda's
transition function it describes from
some state
and
some symbol
you have the
operation on stack
and since it's a
since it's a non-deterministic
computation you may have several next
steps right
so let's say
q1
qi let's say you may go to q
j
and
nothing or q
k
and uh push
t2
and etc
then
you just need to
look at dfa
dfa will have like transition
uh
p
i a
goes to well
that's definitely goes to
p j
right because dfa you have only one way
to go
so
you when you combine these states as one
state
you just and for symbol a here
you just need to make the state here
q j
p j
epsilon
that is you just need to
do
essentially the original pda
separation
but
you use
your
states
to also keep track
of the operation of that dfa
okay
so we are basically doing the same thing
as we did
for the
proof in
as i said the closure property of
regular languages
under the operation of union
then
you can see that since dfa
has nothing to do with stack
so we don't need to change or we don't
need to modify anything regarding the
stake operation here
we go we just piggyback
the situation the state transition of
dfa
in
uh on the original essential operation
of the dfa
oh sorry pda
then
we define
the accept states
the accept states of our new pda
as
see for example this is
a zoom list is two and four
and
it is uh
one
and
two
let's say it's not a accepted
then
only
four one
two one
four two
two two okay that's a it is uh accept
states then it's three
then four three
two three
so only these states
as accept state
then
when the modified pda acceptor string
you know that that dfa accepts a string
and the original df pda extender string
okay so the modified constructed pda can
recognize the intersection
of
the context language a with the regular
language r
okay
so that's why uh
a class of context-free languages is
closed under the intersection operation
okay and that's als we also explained
why
two context-free languages at the
intersection of two context-free
languages may not
be might not be context three
so
intersection is regarding
context free languages and
regular languages
okay
then since we have this
since we have this
we know that
context three languages
oh sorry regular languages is closed uh
the class of regular languages is closed
under the operation of complete
complement right complement
we know that
so
we can also know that
if you have a regular language r
the complement of r is also regular then
you can do a context free language
the intersection of the context language
with the complement of a regular
languages
of the regular language then you get
the difference
okay so we also know that the difference
of a context-free language and a regular
language is still context-free because
we can construct our comp
complement of r and the the intersection
thing then
it's closed
it is still
a context-free language
okay
then we can also know that
we can also know that
the complement
of context free language
may not be a context free language
okay
why
because we know that a and b
may not be may not be
complex free
right
and we know that
union
has the cultural property
so
if
if let's say if
the complement of
context free language is still a context
sorry
yes
if the complement of a
context free language is still
context-free
then
let's say contextual language a
complement is still context free if
okay if
and
complement
sorry context free language b
complement of b
is still context free
if okay
and
union no problem if they are contestable
language then the union is countess free
right
then if
this the complement of this language
is still context free
then you get
what
a
and b the intersection of nb that's
the morgan's law
right that's de morgan's rule
and so
the complement
of
context free language might not be
context-free
if it is
context free then we should have
the intersection of two context-free
language is still context-free
right
but we know it's not so the complement
there is no crucial property for the
complement operation for context three
languages