okay uh let's continue to finish the
proof of cook level theorem that is we
want to
prove that
satisfied very problem is an mp complete
problem
so last time we have uh
written the
our first boolean formula as phi cell
here
and let me recap some concept
that we want to uh
fill we want to fill the table of
n to the case power y and to the case
power by using
a lot of
boolean variables and for each boolean
variables x i
j s
if this variable
is true that means we want to fill i
j
with
symbol uh symbol s
okay
so if uh x i j s is false then
we don't want to fill
as the symbol s into row i column j
okay
uh
since we define boolean variable this
way we want to make sure the table is a
table that is
every space every locate every location
here
will be filled by one
and only one symbol
so to
accomplish this
we design
phi cell
the boolean formula
and
use uh this part to make sure that
rho
rho i column j
has
more than
one or equal to one symbol and use this
part to make sure it
feel
equal to one or less than one symbol and
by doing end that will be exactly one
symbol
okay
and then this is a
a double for loop to go through every
spaces every uh sorry every space here
so
if uh you have a boolean assignment for
these
uh
boolean variables
to make
to satisfy this
formula
then
no the truth assignment of those boolean
variables can be translated into a table
of
in which
each
blank is filled exactly with one symbol
okay
so apparently you will have a lot of
truth assignment
uh satisfying this
file cell whenever the file cell is
satisfied that means the table um
is filled correctly uh by correctly i
mean validly okay each
blank is filled with one symbol and now
they are and on the other hand if you
have a table filled with one symbol in
each blank then
that table can be
translated into
one
into a
truth assignment satisfying this boolean
formula
okay
then
after uh we have a
boolean formula for cell here now we
want to pay attention to the content of
the table okay so firstly we make sure
the table is valid then we want to
take care of the content
the purpose we
we have
we have this table is that actually we
want this table
to
be filled with
a computation
history
to be filled with
a computational history
of
the turing machine and running on
input stream w
okay
then
uh usually i talk about this after we
finish the
proof but i think i i should say it
first then many of you can
actually
catch the idea of the whole thing
okay
so what uh
some
some of you may ask that uh since there
are so many possibilities of uh
the computation history of n on w
how can we have that in one
table
actually we don't
we don't want this table to contain all
possibilities
at the end
you see uh when n on w
it will be like this right because it's
announced
none determines the turing machine right
so you will have many branches
so we what we really want
is
by
assigning these boolean variables
with different assignments
we want to have
the table as
one
branch
of the computation history that is so
in the end we want this table
to reflect
one
computational branch
that's it
okay
so
after knowing this you will know why we
design the other three boolean formula
then we complete the proof
so we want to
see we want to
we want to have
uh well we want to connect
or we want to establish the connection
between
choose assignment
within truth assignment and
the record of the computation history
so if uh perhaps you can have one set of
truth assignment to reflect
this one
and the other set of truth assignment
to
reflect this one
and yet another choose assignment to
reflect
this one
okay
then that's our purpose basically we
want to
we want this table to so to be so
flexible that it can repl represent all
computational branches of
non w
okay
all computational branches actually more
because you have many invalid content
right
but
we want
all possible
computational branches to be represented
by
the truth assignment
and we use boolean formulas
to talk about
those truth assignments that we want
okay that's the key idea
okay so if i say oh
if your choose assignment
satisfies by sale that means the table
is
okay a table
then
let's design another
boolean formula called
by start
file start is easy
we just end
one one
filled with you know separator
and one two filled with
q0
then one three filled with w1
then one for w2 etc then wn
and blank blank
till the end
okay
so
you can clearly see
if you were building
a variable truth assignment satisfied
satisfies by start
that means
the first row
of the table
is exactly
the start configuration of
n on w
right
now you see uh how we use boolean
formula to
to make the table content as we want
something you know concept like this
okay
then
assuming that
the table is really
a computational history
we just we want a formula to check
if there is any
blank filled with
q
accept
okay
so we just do and big or
we order all
positions with
you accept
we do a big or
that means
if
y accept
is true it's satisfied
some blank of the table
is q
accept
right
but actually according to our assumption
as long as
for example
here you got q accept then every talent
every uh for all rows every position
here is q accept because that's our
assumption in the beginning of the
proof
okay
we assume that the machine
if nobody knows but if the machine
enters q accept
the whole thing stops so your
computation history just you know
duplicates on each row so that would be
the case but doesn't matter as long as
in the table there is a queue accept
then
that formula is true
will be you know satisfied is satisfied
so
now you see the three uh boolean formula
one is the five cell to make sure each
blank is filled with one symbol and then
five star
make sure the first row is the star
configuration of the machine n running
on w
uh input w
then we have a final uh check
fi
accept to check
whether q accept is
appears in the table
or whether the machine actually enters
q accept
but
the missing part here
the missing piece here is that
how do we make sure
each configuration
yield
next configuration so
that the table is really
one of the possible computation branches
the history of the
table
really
represents
the history of one possible
computational branch
so
that's the
job of five move here
if i move here
so for five move here
again we do
a double loop
for every row and then every column
then
we have the
legal window check here and what is the
legal window a legal window is actually
two by three or yeah two by three
actually so two by three
window
and
if the content of the window
is legal
then we then the
formula at least this part of formula
is evaluated through
and how do we know
what kind of content
for the by three window to be legal
that will depend on
the transition
function of the machine
so now you see
five move is really
it's really uh
the one connected to the operation of
the machine
okay you see that even n on w
we don't really need to take uh yeah we
don't really need to check the machine
then we uh and we can actually write up
five cell
file start and
file accept
so the
fine move
reflects the operations of the machine
okay
then
for example if in the machine
there is a
transition
for states q1 if you read a
it becomes q1
stays in the state
q1 and you replace a with b and the left
head
move to right
okay then you imagine that
for the uh for one
configuration
you may have something like
okay
that would be
q1a
okay so
for example
so
for example of this transition
and you really have uh
first the configuration and the second
configuration like this
then
you have type content
with uh a a q1 a something
and then
for the machine to operate
on this transition
legally you will get something like
a becomes b right
and then
your head go
right
so that would be this one
then for this uh possibility
these type
of the six
well uh two by three window
will be the uh is legal according to
this transition okay
and also
you will have
these two by three to be legal
and also
something
these two by three
is legal two
okay
so for another another example if you
have q1b
and
you have two
you have two next move
so this kind of
this kind of transition
will give you
a
legal window like this
okay so q1
you read b right
then q1 becomes q2 and
b becomes c right and this a is should
be this a
okay
so actually you can have larger lego
windows like two by four two by five
but two by three is the minimum we want
to have
and
don't forget that
how do we do the legal window checking
it's not
like you check these three
and check this three no it's not that
like that
we do the legal window checking like
this
check this
two by three right then you do two by
three then you do two by three then you
do two by three and then
after
checking the whole
uh
the whole row actually two whole rows
this way
you can make sure
this configuration really
goes to next configuration
for
the transition defined
of the machine
okay
and after doing that you will know
configuration i goes to configuration i
j uh i plus one
according to the definition of the
machine
then
you do
checking this to roll then these two
roll these two row
and
everything
so that's why
that's why
we write this this way
so for the double loop here
okay
we
write out all possible legal content
within
a window 2x3 window
then
2x3 window is like like we
write
5 star we just end
these six
symbols
okay
so
like this one
we have a legal window make
you know
checks out these two by three and some
uh
previous student asked that
what happened if actually you don't have
q1 here you have like
let's say
c here
then of course
these two by three is true
but these two by three is not true right
then you have end
then that will make
the whole formula unsatisfied
so that's why we can
be sure that such a checking
will
help us
to obtain
a correct
computational
history of one possible computational
branch of nlw
okay
and then
it is possible that
there are many many many legal windows
here
but
you must know that
no matter how many items of the legal
windows
the amount of little legal windows is
irrelevant
to
the length of input stream
why because
the legal windows
how many uh the amount of legal windows
is a property of n
the non-deterministic machine n
itself not the input string
therefore
the amount of
legal windows
is a constant
regarding
the input string length
right
then since
here
the size is constant
i shouldn't use k because k is used so
anyway constant
and
we have
n k by n k
items of this
so no problem here right
then
then we basically
finish the proof here
okay
so that means
back to our um
proof of
uh cook 11 theorem
firstly for any
well where is it okay
for any
language in mp for any language in mp
okay
we take the decider
for that language
and then we consider
we consider
the input w
to be processed by n
then we come up with
phi cell
to make sure
the imaginary table is filled
correctly or validly
and we make sure
the first row of the table
is filled
the starting configuration of n and w
and
we make sure
each
row
as a configuration of nmw
legally according to the definition of
the machine
legally
leads
legally yields the next configuration on
the title
that's the job of find move okay
then we check if there is any
blank on the table
filled with q accept
okay
so
now
this would be our
output
when given n
and w
okay
so that means
again that means
for any language a
if
you want to
determine whether or not w is in a is in
a
the process we just present
is
a computable function
to map
the w
actually into the 5 here right
okay into the 5 here
and
if
w is in a that means
w
given n you will get
accept
right
the file here
there will be
choose assignment to satisfy the file
here
which choose assignment
the machine n
accepts
the computation history of machine n to
accept the input string w
reflecting on the table and those
content can be translated into the
boolean variable truth assignment
satisfying the five year so the five
here is in
sat right and we know that
if w is in a
then
the boolean formula we converted
is satisfiable that is 5 is in set
on the other hand
if we know that
the 5
the 5 here is in set
we translate
the truth assignment for these boolean
variables
back
to the table
then the table
is the computational history of
non-deterministic machine n accepting w
and by definition
w is in a
so the procedure we present
is actually
the computable function
and the computable function
satisfy the definition of mapping
reducibility
why
because
if w is in a
our
formula is satisfiable and vice versa
okay
and more importantly
a here
can be
any language in np
so
every language in mp
can be
reduced mapping reduced to
sat
okay
so
we have proved that
every language in mp can be
mapping reducible to sat
but
is the
computable function here
can be
uh
is the computable function here a
polynomial reduce a reduction
so let's take a look at this so that's a
analysis of the
uh presented in the textbook so you can
take a look at this but
simply put simply put
the whole table
is a
polynomial of n right
and you can clearly clearly see that
the length of y cell
is
well within polynomial of n
probability 2k right
actually 2k okay
and then
this one
is only
this
long right and this one is 2k
and this one is still 2k
as i've explained earlier
the size of the
formula for legal windows
is irrelevant to the length input length
of input string so it's independent of n
so it's constant
then we just need to take a
need to uh care about
how many of it so that's actually 2k so
everything is well
in
big o of n2 d2k
okay
but actually it is a
you know it is a rough estimation
uh
in theory if you really want to
write a program to do a conversion you
actually at least need a little more
okay so you will uh
increase by
big o of log n because you want to do
the memory by numbering i mean
you see that
1 1 1 2 1 3
1 4 stuff like that
and you need
space
to record
the enumeration of your variables so
that would that would need extra log but
it doesn't really matter
for talking about polynomial okay so
that's what we said here
so
as i
as i said
the procedure we present here is making
reducible and now it can be finished
in polynomial time
so the whole thing is a polynomial
reduction
okay
so
cook 11 theorem is proofed
and now we know that s a t
is and b complete
and as it is the first np complete
problem we haven't um well not we but
you know
first and b complete
problem to be proved in history actually
then we
we can uh
have
another theorem that three set is also
and be complete
okay
to prove three set is mp complete of
course we can use
we can use the theorem here
so we now know that that is and be
complete
and
we know three set is in np
right
because uh the same reason as said is
nmp
we can provide a reduction from
set
two
three
set to three sets then we can finish the
proof
but here we do
another approach
which is follow the
proof of
theorem 73
that is mp complete
after we get
you know by sale
five star five accept and fight move
after we get these four
after we get these four formula
the overall formula
is five you know five uh
sale
and
five
five star
and
five move
fi accept right
we can just make
the whole thing
to be in cnn conjunction normal form
okay
if you look at this
more closely you will find that
you will find that
5 cell itself
is already
in cnf actually
and the phi star
is also in cnf
okay
because it's a
you know a lot of end
variable and together if you think of
one variable as a clause com
as a close of one
literal then
the whole five stars five stars is
in cnn the same reason goes to five move
is
one close a single close you have n to
the 2k leader row in that clause so
that's
in cnf
so the only part of it nothing already
not already in cnf
is five sorry
not move
except okay so the only component
not already in cnf is actually five move
you do the legal window thing right but
it's quite easy to make it in cnf
because
you can we can use distribution law
to distribute you know and through all
things like that and you can make it
easy
to be in cnf so after you make each of
them in cnf
then you end all of them that's in c and
f2
right because cmf is
some closed and some
something like this then you if you have
something
in cf and together
still in cnf
so we can easily make the formula
resultant formula from the previous
proof
to be in cnf
okay that's the first step
the second step is that we need to make
it
three c and f
okay that's it that's uh
uh that's what we want to talk about
here
so since in cnf you have
many clothes and together
right
and
you will have some literal ore
or
and what is 3cnf you met you need to
make each of them
three literals
okay so for one literal
close you just repeat that that little
okay for for example you have
one literal of one sorry a clause of one
zero
you just need to make
something repeat twice then you you will
have a three literal cost right and the
same thing goes to
and you just you know arbitrarily repeat
one of them then it will become three
and for everything already three then
it's a three
uh clause or three literal colors you
don't need to change it so what we want
to
what we really want to uh
handle is
more than
more than the clothes more than
three liters
for example if you have
four
uh four liter rows in the close
our approach is to add
one
variable here
to introduce
new variable into the clause and
separate the
four literal calls into
two clauses
so now
we make it
a1 a2
or the new variable
and that's
one close
and then
z bar
the negation of our new variable
or a three a four another clause and we
do an end
then we make
uh three c and f out of
uh
the
four literal clause
and you might ask that
uh
well that they are not equivalent
exactly we we don't we don't need
equivalence
okay
so
you need to be
clear about it that we don't need
equivalence here we just need mapping
reducibility
what is mapping reducibility
the original one
in set
okay that would be the four
little miracles
if and only if
the converted one
is in three set
we only need this relationship okay so
why
this way works
because you see
if the original
formula can be satisfied that means a1
a2 a3 a4 at least
one of them is true
right
so for example let's say s
a2 is true
since a2 is true
the converted formula
this part can be made true by a2 to be
true
right
then we can set our new variable z to
force so z bar is true
then
this close can be made true by using z
we set v to be false then it's true
then the clause is true
then the whole thing
is true
so the original
formula can be satisfiable
the modified can be satisfiable on the
other hand on the other hand
if the modified formula can be
satisfiable
that means
uh
okay i should say you will find that
setting z
the truth of z alone
cannot satisfy the
two
clause we generated right
because if you set z to be true then
first one is true but c alone cannot
make the second one to be true
and the vice versa if you set z to false
we can make the second one true but not
the first one
so
if the whole modified formula
is true
a1 a2 a3 a4 at least one of them is true
right
so the original formula
is satisfiable
so that's why
the procedure works
that's why we have
a mapping with disability relationship
between
the original formula and the modified
formula
again they are not equivalent and we
don't need equivalent
that's the
point
okay don't be confused with
we are actually maybe your disability
right
we have emphasized that
don't think too much don't don't
overthink it we just need this
relationship
okay
so
for l variables we can do the same
we separate a1 a2 first then we add z1
then we do z1 bar z2
with a3 z2 bar z3
with a4 and finally
the
arrow minus 3 bar with the last two
variables
and the same argument
if
the original
if the original
formula
is
in that
we know that
we can manipulate
we can manipulate z
to make everything true
so let's count it okay so we have
totally l minus two closed
and we add
l minus three new variables
so if the original one can
be satisfied that means one of a one
through a l
at least one of them is true
so
that one can make one of the l minus 2
closest to be true
then we can manipulate the arrow minus 3
variables to make the
whole
phi prime to be true that's no problem
and
on the other hand if we know that phi
prime is true
that
that means
at this the 1 of a 1 a 2 to a l
must be true one of them at least
why because we can only manipulate our
new variables actually l minus three new
variables
to satisfy
l minus three clauses and the final one
must be satisfied by the original
variables from
phi here
right and that variable alone
can make the whole thing true
okay
so
we may
easily convert
the formula obtained
from
the proof of cook 11 theorem and convert
it to 3 er 2b uh
to a formula in 3c and f
so
go
based on the same logic we know that
three sets
is come np complete
okay so he said it's np complete
okay
although sap satisfiability is our first
mb complete problem but
we use
we usually use
three sets to prove other problems to b
and d complete
why because threeset is you know
uh the form the form of threeset is
quite
regular quite limited because you have
clauses and each clause is exactly has
three leader roles in this way it's very
easy to manipulate
that is why we usually use three sets to
prove other
problem to be mp complete
let's have some
cases here
some showcases here
so see
we now prove that preset is and be
complete
then we want to apply
theorem here okay oh sorry it's bad i
should draw this way
right
so
don't forget the all uh
i don't know that order by the procedure
here
we now
know that
three sets
is and be complete
and the four
sum
problem in np
as long as
we can
develop
polynomial time
reduction making reduction
to the problem
we prove that the problem is in
sorry is empty complete
right according to this theorem
then
what we already we
we already have
because
we already
showed that
there is a polynomial time
actually we already showed that first
clique is an emp
right
because click is one of the
uh
let me
be sure about it
no okay
firstly clicker is in mp
why
why clicker is empty
uh
because if
actually we we we have clinton
okay doesn't matter
we can have a polynomial time verifier
for click
right because for
g
k
if uh it's it should be quite uh
relatively easy for you to write a
program a common program
and take the graph here and take
a sorry take the problem here and
someone give you k notes
and you verify if
these nodes is
on the graph and then
these nodes
really connect to each other then you
report yes so that's verifier the
implementation of such a
polynomial time verify is
straightforward
so one
click is in mp
two for the definition of polynomial
time
reduction
we have clique as our example
right
if you don't remember that you can go
back to
this part
whenever you are given
a boolean formula in three cnf you can
convert
a graph here
with
the number
of
clauses here
and this one
is the instance of click
right
so we have polynomial reduction from
preset to click
then combine these two facts
we know that
click ask and be complete
okay
so let's see another example here let's
say uh word is cover
okay where is color
if
given a undirected graph and
k
if that undirected graph has k note
where it is covered
as k node vertices cover
then
the input string is in
the
language
and we want uh
that let's have an example
for uh
if you have a graph like this
okay
so it's a bad okay this is much better
because we have one color of that graph
see if we choose this node
if we choose this node we cover
this uh this age this age this age and
this edge
uh this yeah
then you uh
you if you choose this one then you
cover this one and
choose this one or this one you cover
another one so
this graph has a three color
right three notes three vertices cover
to cover all the h you choose vertices
to cover h
that's why it's
very discovered
then we want to reduce three set to
vertex cover that means if we are given
a three cnf
we need to output you know a graph and a
k
4 vertice color
so
as an example here
if we have
formula in string c and f like this
okay
so of course you can go through the
formula first
then you know
you have two variables x1 and x2
so to produce the graph we output x1 and
x1 bar
and x2 and x2 bar
okay
so
this
the upper part is for boolean variables
so we write uh we output
something like this way something like
this to represent each boolean variable
the variable and its negation okay
then
we output
this part for each clause so you see x y
x and x 2 first clause
x 1 bar x 2 bar x 2 bar second cause
x 1 bar x 2 x x2 third clause
okay
then
we just connect the upper part
and the bottom part
connects the same
literal so you see x1 x1
x1 bar x1 bar x2 x2 x2 bar x2 x2 that's
it
so
the conversion is pretty easy
go through the formula ones and you will
know how many variables you have and
then output you know
this thing for each variable
and output
this thing for each clause
and then connect the same one that's it
and then
how many
since we have
g here right
g here
and
what is the k
we need to set for this problem instance
for
this part
we want to
uh
okay
we have three clothes right so three
cross
and uh
multiply by two plus
two boolean variables
so in this case we want to set uh
eight right
eight
so that would be the output of the
conversion
so again
we output this one
and
give eight so that would be the versus
cover
instance
then why um
why this uh conversion
why
is this conversion of maple reducibility
because you see
if this formula is satisfiable that
means
that means
at least the one of literal for each
cause is true
right
so
uh
if we choose
if we select the node correspond
for the upper bar for the upper body we
choose the literal the true literal and
for the bottom part we choose
the close
uh within a clause we choose the two
variable uh the two literal the two
liter rows
that are not that
are not true
then that will be a versus cover
okay
why
because you see uh let's say
uh
i really don't i really don't remember
which one
so let's say uh if x1
if x1 is true it's false
then we choose these two and this one is
true right
and
choose these two
and uh
okay so that would be a uh sorry
it doesn't really matter we choose which
two which two hit here right or for
example these two
so
if x y is false
x two is true
so
this one's true right and this one is
true and o is true okay that
x one fourth x two true is a boolean
uh variable two assignment to make the
original formula to to satisfy
and then according to
the truth assignment we have x1 bar
selected x2 selected
and then for each close what we select
the lateral not true
but if you have more than
one literal to be true you can arbitrary
select two or two
uh literal okay
so in this case
we can have
eight vertices cover why because you can
see that for all the edges here for all
the ages here
the node we selected covers o h why
because
for the three
nodes representing close
as long as you select this true these
two
you cover this one this one and this one
right
and
cover this one and this one this one
okay
then
the boolean variable we selected on the
upper part covers all this h all this
edge
okay
and
for not
true we cover from the bottom to the top
so that's why
according to the truth assignments the
node we selected
covers all ages
okay so the converted instance is really
inverted cover
that'll
be this direction right
now the reverse direction
what how to uh how can we be sure that
if
this graph has a vertical eighth note
vertices cover then the original
formula is satisfiable
the reason
is the same and the easy because
look at
the structure here
look at the structure here
for this one you must select one
for this one you must select one why
because you if you don't select one of
the two
then the h in the middle will not be
covered at all
you want to cover this edge you have to
select either one of the two nodes right
so
we must select one like select this one
select this one right to make sure this
h is covered
then for the
three node structure here
for each of the three node structure you
have to select
two of them
to cover
these three edge
as long as you don't select uh select
two of the two of the three nodes you
won't cover the h so in order to cover o
h you have to select two of the three
two nodes out of the three
node structure
right
then
we have three
structure here
you have to select two of them
and for the upper part
you have you must select this way eighth
note
select eight note this way you don't
have other notes can select so eighth
note
so
after you select eighth note and up
a vertice cover
see
you select
that for example
these two nodes to cover the edge here
right
and you select these node
to cover the edge here
and you select
this node arbitrary to cover the
edge here and the cover latch here okay
after you have a node and you tell me
that okay it is a vertice cover that
means
in addition to
those edges we think the structure to
node structure and the three note
structure
those notes also cover
the edges
between the upper
part and the bottom part
so for this example see
it cover these two
and
that one cover this one
and this one cover this one and the same
thing here and here
and also of course both of you know
covered
if this happened
if the eighth note in this case selected
really is a vertice cover
then we just need to translate
the selection
to
boolean
choose assignment
and
that's green choose assignment while
satisfied must satisfy the original
formula
why
because
all the edges between all the edges
between the upper body and the bottom
part
are covered
this one
covered
those two so
that means
these two clothes can be
satisfied by having
this variable to this little row to be
true
and this one cover this one right
then
that clause will be satisfied find that
literal to be true
so that's why
the vertices cover can be translated
back to the truth assignment
that satisfies the original formula
so
it is a mapping reducibility
property
okay
and of course the whole
the running time you need to convert 5
convert 5 into this graph and
the
integer here
well
well uh actually well within the
polynomial bound
okay
so since we have
a
polynomial time reduction
from three set
to where this cover oh sorry we have to
prove that vertical is in mp but that's
easy right you can have a polynomial
verifier and that someone give you k
notes you just you know check if that k
note is really a vertical
so versus cover is no doubt in mp so now
we know that vertex cover is mmp
complete
sorry is can be complete
okay