now we will introduce reductions via
computation histories the computation
history
for a two machine on input is simply
the sequence of configurations
that the machine goes through as it
processes the input
we actually have seen
computation history before
like the one
we
encountered on
chapter three when we change when we
trace the machine to process uh
the input string zero zero zero zero
so
this one is the starting configuration
and after one transition it goes to this
configuration
then
after the second transit uh transition
it goes to
this
configuration and so on and finally it
stops
at the
accepting configuration
right
so
the whole
sequence
of
configurations
is called
computation history
so
is simply the sequence of configurations
that the machine goes through as it
processes the input
okay
[Applause]
so
and accepting config
and accepting computation history for
machine m on the input string w
is a sequence of configurations
let's say c1 c2
2cl where c1 is the start configuration
of n on w and the serial cl is n
accepting configuration of n
and we
have defined accepting configuration
right that that is any configuration
with the state uh with the
with the accept state
and then each
ci
legally follows from ci minus 1
according to the rules which
defined by the transition function of m
so
and accepting
computation history
for m on w is
like we just uh
saw on
m2 running on
input string 0 0 0 0 it is that is an
accepting computation history for m2 on
0 0 0 0
and then
if the
final configuration is a rejecting
configuration that is any configuration
with the rejecting state reject state
then the whole uh sequence we call we
we call the whole sequence of rejecting
computation history for m on w
okay
so after defining the computation
history let's define a new
well a
slightly new type of machine which is
called
a linear bounded
automaton
okay a linear bounded automaton a linear
boundary automaton or we say that lba
is a restricted type of tuned machine so
basically it is turing machine okay it
shares
the fundamental definitions of two
machines
and
it is a restricted type of two machine
wherein the tape head the tape head
isn't permitted to move off the portion
of the tape containing the input
okay
so
perhaps it's easier for you to think of
this
you have a turing machine okay
a
regular turing machine
and you put
your input
on the tape
right the input on the tape and
when you
after you put the input on the tape and
when you want to put the machine at that
moment
you cut off the tape here
so there is no more infinite tape in
this case
and everything is as usual the most the
machine can you know can uh read write
the tape and move the
head left and right
unless it goes to left
it will stop here
if here it goes to right it will stop
here that's it
so
if
you use the machine this way and the
restriction that
when after you put the input on the tape
you cut off the tape
so
before you
well the concept is before
you put the input the input string
the type is infinite
so
you can put
an arbitrary
length of input string
okay
we have
sufficiently long tape for any
length
of input swing but after you put the
input string on the tape
the tab is cut off
so you only have
the length of the input string
tape
to manipulate
so this kind of tune machine we call
lba
okay so lba
and
if you uh think
again for the
for many languages we have uh proved to
be decidable
including
adfa acfg edfa ecfg and
every context-free language
basically
you don't need extra table
okay basically in those proof
you don't really need extra tape
okay
or in a way you can
think of that
you can
by using some programming technique
you don't need to
use
a
tape extra to the length of the input
string
so lba can be used to decide
the languages we listed here okay so lba
is you know also quite powerful but
it doesn't have when run when when uh
during operation it doesn't
has it doesn't have infinite tape
but
to decide many many languages you
actually don't need extra extra tape
space so lba is some kind of restricted
type of tool machine
okay
so according to this type of machine
let's
talk about the language regarding this
type of of machine okay so let's define
alba
so it's very interesting that for
what is aroba first
give you
the input string
has two parts the first part is an lba
and the second part is the input for
that lba and
if there will be a accept the input
string
the pair of n
w
is a string of
in a lba
okay
and we know that
atm is undecidable right atm is
undecidable
but how about aoba
actually we can prove that aoba is
decidable
it's decidable
okay how do we prove that we can just
count everything
so that m
b
lba with q state
and
in the tape alphabet which is you know
gamma capital gamma there are g
type symbols
and don't forget that for tuning machine
the
alphabet
is included in gamma right
so
gamma contains all possible symbols
written on the tape
we can simply calculate that since after
you put in the input string
let's say
in the length of your input string is n
then you can think of that each symbol
here
there are
g
possibilities
right and you have n
so
total possible tab content
is g to the nth power
and then
you might have
q
states
and you will re your
head reading writing head
the position possible position is n
because
the length of the table is in right
so
that's all possible
configurations for an lba
running on a string w
and why this
why this quantity is important
because
talking about
if aoba is decidable means
can you design a turing machine to
decide
some input
in lba in aoba or not
right
so we write since we are using a turing
machine
we have infinite tape
so we can record
all
configurations when we simulate an
lba running on the input w
then if we simulate a tree machine on
the string it is possible it runs
forever right
but
when we simulate lba on
an input string
lba may be
well lbn may still possible run forever
but we will know that
why because
there
are
finite although this may be a very big
number but it is finite lba
has only finite possible configurations
so you can think of that
when lba
run one step one step one step
if it goes into a loop
it must be something like
go back
to
some previous configurations
right
and again
you will find that this technique cannot
be used to regulate turing machines
because i have
described that it is possible for a
turing machine your head
keep going right and you have infinite
tape right so your configuration will
never
be repeated that's possible
so such a technique doesn't work on
regular tm but it works on lba because
lba has only finite configurations
any
infinite
sequence of configuration will have
repeat will have repeated will have
duplicated
configurations and if we are using a
turing machine to watch
to simulate
to simulate an lba running on
an input string and watch the sequence
we will detect the infinite loop
we will be able to detect it
so
if
we detect the loop we know that
the mw
is not in lpa because
it will never accept w right
other than this possibility there will
be a either rejected w or accept w so
we
are able to design a tuning machine to
decide
alba
so lba
is decidable
that is the proof
okay
so simply put
because the number of all possible
configurations can be exactly computed
and the looping of a machine can
therefore be determined so we can
determine the three possibilities first
accept no problem reject no problem and
runs forever still no problem
okay that's why aoba
lba
is decidable
okay so to be formally
to formally prove that you can
refer to the
construction here we can construct a
turing machine
and simulate m
on w well in the in textbook it just
simulates so many steps
okay then
if m will hold it will hold within this
step
either accept or reject otherwise
it will run forever okay so that's a
simple concept for eoba
however
how about
oh sorry aoba however how about elba
that's
given an lba and
the machine
recognized the language of the
machine is empty set
and we can prove that
elba is undecidable
that's interesting
let's prove it first
so
the proof idea is that
we want to
use
the decider
for elba
okay we assume that the decider for eoba
exists
so we assume
eoba is decidable
since eoba is decidable
we can use that decider
to
decide atm
okay
that's the interesting part
so
think about it
when you
have a turing machine
and
a input string w for that turing machine
it is possible to construct
and lba let's call it b
okay we construct an lba b
according to the given m and w
according to the given n and w
why because you can
you can think of the lba
expect
an input string
of which
and
the content of which
is
the accepting
computation history
of n
running on w
you see the the interesting part is that
we don't know
whether or not the accepting computation
history of nmw exists
but if you are presented the computation
history you can examine it
right
so we can't shock
or simply
you can think of we construct a turing
machine b
but you know that when b
gets its own input
there is no need
for extra
tape so
b is effectively an lba
and then b just need to check if the
first
symbol
is the separator is a separator
and
then
follows
the starting configuration of m
on w
if no reject okay
if yes then check if
the starting com start configuration
follows followed by a separator
and followed by
the configuration c2
which is
the legal proof the legal
move
of
n
we can just check
the transition function of n regarding
the difference between the two
configurations right just like we trace
the two machine m2
in chapter three
okay so
you can
surely
check
if two con configuration or two strings
are
converted configuration c i
minus 1 to c i according to
m's
transition function
right
and all these
only require you have the your head goes
forward
back and forward back and forward on the
input tape there is no need for extra
space
okay so if you have a turing machine
it it can surely do this kind of
processing
so after you check if
everything goes wrong you just
reject this string
right
then
you can check each step of m on w
after
you get
an acceptance
accepting
configuration then you know
the whole string
is the
accepting
accepting com computation history of n
on w
right you don't know whether or not it
exists
but
if someone put on your input tape you
can surely decide it you can surely
knows
you can surely know it is
the accepting computation history
that's what lba do
that lba only check
if
the input string
for it
is the accepting
computation history of
m on w
okay
so
when we
are given m and w we construct an
lba
from the given mnw
and which will accept only one string
which is
the accepting computation history of m
and w
but
see
as i said we don't know whether that
string
exists
so the interesting part is arrow of b
is empty set
if
m
does not accept
w
l of b
is a set of only one string
and this three this string is exactly
the accepting computation history of m
and w
and therefore it's not
empty set if n except w
right
so we basically still
use and accept w or net
as a switch to change to determine the
behavior of b
but
we
let
the
assumed to
exist
decided for elba
to determine
whether or not the lba reconstructed
of which the language is empty set or
not
if it is not an mps empty set if the
elba decider reject that means
the language of b is not
an empty set then we know
the only string accepted
possibly accepted by b
is the accepting computation history of
m on n l sorry m on w
that means m accepts w because
that's the definition right
then
we accept
so s
accept its input
if r
accepts that means
l of b
is empty set
right so we know
and the
the accepting computational history of m
on w doesn't exist
so
either m reject w or m enters you know
in infinite loop or runs forever we
don't know
anyway the the accepting computation
history does not exist so m does not
accept w
then we reject s reject its own input
okay
so
we proved that if
a decider for elba exists
we can
use it to construct decider for atn
but
you know that's a contradiction because
we already know we cannot have a decider
for atm so
uh decided for eoba does not exist
okay so eoba
is undecidable
so uh to
describe more detail you can see that
we
the elba only need to check if q
3a
of the transition function m
does it
have the transition to
q5
and
change to x and
goes right
right
if there is
such transition
then
c i
is uh
or i should say c i plus 1 is a legal
move from c i
so it is
straight
it is quite straightforward to implement
a checking
like that
we don't know the answer but we can
check the answer
okay so that's the eoba
and
now
let's uh
have a quick review here it's very
interesting so for dfa we know that
a dfa
right
edfa
and eq
dfa
and
acfg
ecfg
and the eq
cfg
and we have atn
etn
and the eq
tn
now we have a lba
elba
of course we didn't introduce eql va
right
and we didn't prove
eq cfg
so
uh
but we can
according to what we already know
so we know
atm is undecidable
right and we know aoba is decidable but
eoba is undecidable
although we didn't prove eq cfg to be
undecidable but we have
talked about that in chapter four right
and we know eq dfa
is decidable
okay
so
it is it's uh uh
well interesting to me
uh comparison
uh table here so dfa cfg a uh lba turing
machine
they
the different languages regarding their
behavior behavior and
we can see that you know they the
computational power and how to uh the
related language has some similar uh
some interesting property here
so the line here
here is undecidable and
there is decidable okay so kind of
interesting
anyway
so let's use the
technique to prove one more language
that that is ocf g
we know ecfg means give you and
give you a context-free grammar
if the context-free grammar
can generate
no terminal strings right
and then ocfg here is that
give you a contextual grammar can you
determine that
the language of the contextry grammar is
all
possible
it's the set of all possible strings
well we can determine
we can decide ecfg but we want to prove
that we cannot decide
all cfg so all cfg is undecidable
okay it's undecidable
then
we can now use the same
way as we did for eoba
and
we want we want that
if ocfg
is decidable
then we can use that decider
we can use that decider to decide
atm
okay
and the proof idea is quite similar
firstly we uh
since we want to build a decider for atm
so we have a turing machine
and the input is machine and
input right
so this one is s input and the w is m's
input
and when we are given
mw we can surely because we have the
details of m
we can surely build up
the
pda
and remember that pda is intrinsically
non-deterministic so it can fork
many many many
sufficient
branches
right
and all branches
you have a stake to use
so imagine that
we want the pda
to reject reject
to reject
one string
which one
the string
is
the accepting computation history of m
on w
we want to reject
it and why do we want to reject it
because don't forget that the property
of non-deterministic computation
any brand sheet any computation
computation branch except then the whole
machine accepts
right
in a way
that is a
that is an or
relationship
right because
as long as one
computation branch accepts
there's no need for others to accept or
reject because the whole machine is
considered accepting that string
but
any one computation history of a pda can
only finish
some limited task
it is easy to
understand that
it is uh we can
use pda's stack
to
push
c1
onto the stick
right
so c1 will be
if c1 look like this
then on the stack
it will be look like
see the
arrow
look like this
c1
then it is possible to check
with the reverse
direction c2
right
you pop a symbol and check
the input string and the consumer input
string
and the check if
from c1 to c sorry yes to from c1 to c2
is that
a legal move
of m on w you can check that because you
can embed the
transition function into the pds state
and the transient function is a finite
possibility right so you can do that
and
by using the stack
you can check the reverse direction
configurations
okay
so we can
that
we can fork
computational branch to check
a pair of configurations
is it legal from c1 to c2r
and
is is it legal from c2 r to c3
because you see
for c2r you have something like this
then
the top
top you can check that by using pda
right
and then a branch check this pair a
branch check this pair a branch check
this
this pair and so on
so it is possible
it is possible
to check
if ci
legally goes to ci plus one
by using pdas many many many
computational branches
and then we have a branch check
if c1
is
starting configuration
and the see another branch check if cl
is
accepting configuration
okay so you have many branches one
responsible for checking this one and
the one checking this one and
many branches check a pair check a pair
check a pair right and so on
as long as any one of the check
fails okay
fails
any one of these
massive checks fails
you accept our pda
accept its input
okay
so
it's easy to know that
only
the accepting
configuration
accepting
accepting computation history of mlw
will be reject
will be rejected by the pda we
constructed right
so if you have no problem
then
we convert the pda
constructed for mrw
to
cfg
then we will have a cfg
like
l of g
is
all possible string
if
m does not accept w
right
because if m does not
accept w our pda will reject all
possible strings because there is no
accepting computation history of 4n on w
exist
and the converted
context-free grammar will be able to
generate all possible strings
otherwise
f g
is
all possible strings
except
the
computation history
in
you know uh
reverse order every other configuration
written in reverse order
other than this string
so
if m accepts w the accepting
computation history exists
then pda will reject that string and the
converted
grammar from the pda will generate
everything except this string
therefore it's not
it's not all possible string right
so
we can use
the decider for
all
c f
g
to check if a given grammar
can generate all possible string or not
if
the grammar can generate all possible
string that means
the given m and w
and will not accept w then our decider
for atm can
answer
reject otherwise we can answer accept
because we know
the accepting computation history for n
on w exists
right
so all ocfg is undecidable because
its decider cannot
exist
okay
and finally we want to introduce a
simple undecidable problem
also using the skill
of reductions via
computation history
and firstly the problem we
want to talk about is pcp
what is pcp
which is uh post correspondence problem
okay
post here is
a less than
the less than of the scatter so he
proposed the problem and what is a pcp
a pt a pcp is a collection of dominoes
like this one we have first domino top
is b bottom is ca
and the second type of domino tub is a
second c
a b etc
and
we have infinite
copy of you know every type of dominoes
we have infinite copies
and what is the
problem here the problem here is that is
it possible to find a match
is it possible to find a match
so
for this particular instance
yes there is a match
if we put the second type first type
third type
second type again and fourth type
you will find the top string is
a c a a b c a a a b c and the top of the
string is also a b c a a a b c
that's a match okay
and
for
for some instance
like this one we can determine that it's
not possible to have a match
because for this one
top is always longer than bottom
so it's not possible to have a match
so that's called
post correspondence problem okay
and formally we can describe
pcps
you have
k
instance of pcp
is that you have k
dominoes
is there a string sorry is there is
there a sequence
exist
such that
the top
the top of the sequence of the dominoes
the uh the top string of the sequence of
the dominoes
is equal is identical to that of the
bottom string
okay so that's the formal description
and to
use our tier machine
terminology to describe pcp we can say
that pcp
is an instance with a match
and can we write a program to determine
that the instance with a match
okay
now we want to prove that actually pcp
is undecidable
okay pcp is undecidable so the idea is
that we are
we want to use a decider for pcp
as decided for pcp to help us to
decide atm again yes atm
so given turing machine m and input w
let's construct a pcp
and then that pcp has the property that
if the pcp we constructed has a match
then m accept w
otherwise
m does not accept w
okay so we have uh
three technical points here
first
we assume that
when m running on w it never attempts to
move its head off the left hand end of
the tape
okay that's our first assumption
and
actually you can
use another if if the m
you are given really does it
you can write a turing machine to
simulate it first and detect this event
and do some correspond corresponding
action to
handle it okay so that's not really a
problem so we just for convenience
we assume
the behavior mw is like this
and then
if the input string is you know nothing
is empty string we put
blank
in place of the string to do the
construction i think that's not a
problem right
and then
we talk about
a modified version of pcp first for
simplicity and then
we change we change or we modify the
changed pcp
back to the normal version
okay
so
the modified version of pcp is like we
require that a match start with the
first domino
okay
so in the original version of pcp or
regular version of pcp there is no need
to start from the first domino see this
match is the second first
third second fourth
right so there is no need to start from
the first
but for simplicity in our proof we
require this first then we remove the
requirement
okay
and we call the
modified
pcp
as
there's an instance of pcp you have to
start the match have two starts we have
to start with the first domino
okay so with the three
technical points
let's build up the decider for atm
let's say
assume that there is a decider for pcp
r
actually mpcp but you know pcp
okay
we want to con we want to construct
construct the decider for atm
and
for atm we will
for atm for instance of atm we will have
n and w right
and the m is a turing machine so we will
have everything regarding that turing
machine and we will have w
as the input string
firstly we construct
the first
domino
which is you know t1b1 here
so we put
a separator
on the top
and a separator on the button
and then
starts configuration
and separator
on the bottom
okay
so that's our first domino
so since we require that
the match must be stopped we must start
with the first one so we imagine that
we put first domino here
and then you can find that
the string on the top is a separator and
on the bottom is one separator and then
starting configuration
and then
another separator
so
start from this situation
okay so that's our first domino
and then second domino
well not really second
second
category or second part of the domino is
that
for every since we have the spec of the
two machine
for every
going right transition
we put
dominoes like this into
a pcp
so if
there is a transition q
reading a
change q to r and the reading b
and head go into the right direction
we put one
domino q
a
b r
okay
and if there are
transitions goes left
we put
q
a
b because a change to b right
and your head goes to left
but
for this part and this part
you need to fill in
all possible
tab symbols
okay
so
for part two
if there are
you actually create
the number of
the transitions goes right
dominoes
but for part 3 you will create the
number
of
transitions goes left
times
the number of tab symbol
dominoes because you need to fill
symbol c here
with every
with all
symbols
in
type symbols
okay
so
and for part four for every
simple
in tab symbol we put a domino like this
into our collection
so you see if we don't
if we don't require
the match start from the first domino
then the domino in part 4 alone
gives a match
right that's why we need to
we need to limit we need to restrict
that the match must start
from the first domino and for part 5 we
put
separator separator and
blank
separator separator
and for part 6 for every symbol in type
symbol we put
this symbol q accept accept and the q
accept this symbol and this symbol
and finally
the last part we add these domino
we add these domino into collection
and
checking all the parts you will find
something interesting that
first part we have starting
configuration right
and then
part two path three
reflects the transition of the
two of the given two machine n
and then
part four
is just you know copy the tape content
path five
copy the separator
and part six
remove
tape symbol
and then part 7
give enough balanced separators
because you will you can see that
part one has two separators on the
bottom and the one on the top
and other parts of the dominoes
either
no separator or same number of separator
so it will never have a match
right
only that we have something like this
okay
so
let's have an example here
so if there if you are given a turing
machine
with type symbol 0 1 2 and blank
and start from
0 1 0 0
then
we put the starting configuration as the
first domino
so
since the
match required starting from
t1 b1
so we will have string like this
okay
then think about it
you want to match
the string
right
then it's matched so you want to put q0
here
0 here right
what domino will have something like
this and q0 is a state right so you need
to check
if the machine has a transition
q 0 q 0 and 0
make q 0 q 7 and make 0 2 and
goes right
so
in our collection there will be a domino
q 0 0
and what
goes right right so 0 becomes 2 and the
q
7 will have this one so
we will have this one in the collection
and in order to match q0 so you use this
one use the q0 here to match q0 here
right
and since you used this one
there will be two q7
growing on the bottom
right
and then we just
we have matched this
then we just use
part 4
to copy tab content
to copy type content
to copy tab content and use part
5 i guess to copy
separator
so you see the interesting thing is that
in order
for the design of our dominoes here in
order to
match top with the bottom
you will
simulate one
move
one transition of that two machine
on the input w
right
so you will be able to do the trying to
do the match and keep going and keep
going and keep going
and let's
say so from this one and the two we just
copied
using par 4
and assuming that there is a
q1
sorry q7 1
and
q05 going to write that would be this
kind of domino so the same thing
happened in order to match q17 you use
this domino so q17 okay but
you will have 0 q5 here
then again copy
type content copy separator you go one
step
again
see
when you try to match in the domino you
are simulating
the turing machine if you
do this way
and let's have another example here if
there is a
left going transition like this one
then
remember that
q
five zero
q five become q zero uh sorry q nine but
it will go left so q9
and
zero becomes two this one becomes two
and you need to fill all possible type
symbols here
so for the turing machine we have right
now as an example the type symbol is
0 1 2 blank right
so for this transition
we have
four
dominoes
so
copy
type symbol cup uh sorry
we know that q 0 0 q 5 we can use this
one
so
match this one and have
these on the bottom
then copy zero
copy separate
so we go one more step
of the two machine
so as i said
we can go on and on and on and on
and assume that okay
if the let's say
if the
machine n on w will never
stop or machine and actually reject w
then you will not have a match you will
never have a match because there's no
dominoes for you to finish the match
right so that's first thing the second
thing is assuming that
after some steps
the machine actually goes to accept
like this one
so from starting
configuration the second one to
this one so c1 c2 to cl is a accepting
computation history
let's assuming that
then
starting from this point
we can use the dominoes in part
seven and six
to gradually finish the match
how do we do that
for example you actually have many ways
but for example
we copy the tape we copy the tab content
here and here
and then we use the
uh
we use the dominoes for part
to match this one
but
the button only goes one except
so you see
we match this one match this one but
here
we eliminate a zero
one zero one
symbol zero right
then we still match
two and the match separator
so
one tab symbol
eliminate removed
so keep going this you can remove all
tab symbols
and finally you have
only q accept and the separator left
then
now
is the
opportunity to use
the domino of sec uh part seven
so
we finally
use
these tape as this domino
of
to finish the match that will be a match
right
so
we will have something like
this so the top string and the bottom
string is a match
and this only happens when a match
oh sorry
when the machine m on w and her when
m enters
q accept
during
processing w
right
so our
modified pcp
or modified pcp
can
[Music]
have a match if and only if
m the given machine m running on w
and accepts w
right
because
m accept w there is a accepting
computation history
and that accepting computation history
is exactly the match of our mpcp
on the other hand
if our mpcp has a match
that that must be caused by
the machine enters q accept
because there is no other design for q
reject right
so we can we if we have
if we have
a decider for mpcp
we can use that to construct atm decider
so mpcp is undecidable
but actually we can further remove
the requirement
to match with
for the match to start with
t1 b1
after let's say
after we have
the set of
our dominoes of mpcp
we can convert them
into an other
set of dominoes but that is a pcp that
is we don't need we don't require
to
have a match from the first domino
how do we do that
that's for simplicity we introduce
a notation
like this
if we have
this notation
in front of a string
that means
we put star in every symbol in front of
every symbol of that string
and also if it put behind
the string
we put stars
behind every symbol
or
if we have the same both on both sides
then we have star like this
okay so that's a easy notation for us to
change a string
then
then for a set of dominoes as
mpcp
so remember that
for this
collection of dominoes
the match required
to start with t1 v1
then
firstly we copy
we copy
all dominoes like this
and
for the top we put
sorry i shouldn't use this one
we change the top string like this and
change the bottom string like this
okay
so that's the first step so if you have
k dominoes we
copy it and change the top string and
the bottom string with k dominoes
then we
add two extra dominoes
the first one is
also the copy of the first domino but
we change the top string
like this and change the button string
like this
and finally
another new
dominoes
is
we introduce yet another symbol
and then have a star here
okay
so that's it
we have done the conversion
and you will see
it's pretty straightforward that why
for these
collection of dominoes
we don't need we don't need to specify
that okay you have to start from the
first one
okay
because
let's say
because if there is
a match it must start from this one
otherwise it
won't happen
but it doesn't matter we want to prove
that
if
the modified the pcp here
has a match
then
the converted pcp regular pcp here has a
match and the vice versa
okay and it's pretty easy to see that if
there is a match according to the
definition
that will be
i1
i2
i3
il right and
t
[Music]
it's identical to b i 1 b i 2
through b i l that's definition right
and
for the
modified uh pcp
it must start with t1 so that's say
one
a modified pcp mesh is like this
and
this match
must exist for these converted dominoes
because
you
use this one
as this
and you will get
e here
and everyone you just select it from
this area
and finally you put the final one
here and here
so
the match
for the original folder npcp
can
that you have a match in the converted
pcp
on the other hand
for
the converted pcp if there is a match
if there is a match
you can be surely know that it will
although we are not we we don't require
start the match start from the first
domino but
it has to
right because if you don't really you
don't you don't start from this one
you will not have a match because all
other
button string has no star
so it's it's not possible to start from
other ones
but we will not require that okay
so start from this one there will be a
match end with the last one right
because
start from this one
the star
the star will always
you you will always have more star on
the bottom
you must close with
the last one
to balance the number of star
then
if you really get a match
you remove all-star and
remove the last one you will have a
match
of the mpcp
that's why
we can convert mpcp to
regular pcp and
if the
mpcp has a match
the regular pcp have has a match and
vice versa
so the whole proof is
like given
given
m
and w
we construct
the domino for part one
part two part three
four five seven
then we convert
through this process
we convert through this process
to the pcp instance
so if you have a pcp
decider
we can use the
construction procedure to construct a
pcp instance
then
if
the decider for general pcp really
exists
we can use that to decide our
atm
so atm decider can be constructed in the
way we just introduced
but again that's a contradiction because
we know that
deciders for atm cannot exist
so decider for pcp
cannot exist
right so pcp is undecidable
okay
so that's our reduction via computation
history and
pcp sound decidable