uh chapter three
in chapter three we introduced
uh turing machines
the definition of turing machines and uh
proving some proved some
equivalence of variance of two machines
so uh
for two machines there are
let's say
if there is a language and you can find
the turing machine
for all possible strings
in that language the turing machine says
accept
for strings not in that language the
turing machine says reject
if in this case we call that
the language is decidable or too
indecidable
if for all the strings in the language a
two machine can say accept but for
strings not in
the language the two machine maybe
says reject or
no answer at all and you it never stops
we say that such a language
is tuning recognizable
okay so
there will be decidable languages and
recognizable languages right
and
for the viewpoint of computation
since we consider
languages are problems
languages are proven and
computational models are computation
to
you know the the way you can do the
computation to handle or to solve the
problems
we are thinking about uh
decidable languages and recognizable
languages in a way that um
in practical for practical use
i guess many of you or basically all of
you may agree that decidable languages
are
really what we want right because
if you have a problem instance as a
string
and
the turing machine
always gives you an answer either that
the string
is in the language that is yes or the
string is not in a language that would
be a no
string
if you have
algorithm to handle that kind of problem
then
it is what we want so we start from
decidability we start from decidable
languages
then
we will talk about other advanced topics
later so from decidable languages
we uh
will introduce some
decidable languages concerning regular
languages and don't mix them all okay we
just
use some example regarding regular
languages as
decidable
problems
okay
so
the first thing we want to look at is
adfa
okay
so in this text in this book we use a
as acceptance
acceptance and dfa means
the acceptance of dfa
okay in a way you can imagine that we
can
we can encode a dfa
into a string
right and
how to imagine it
actually you can
in a way you can think of
encoding a machine
the encodings of a machine is actually a
program you write you can think of a dfa
written in
let's say python
c
and the python code the c code
is actually
the encoding of that machine
okay
so
let's say uh
b here is a machine which is a dfa so
you return it as some text file or text
string long text long text string
and you have a string the string is for
the dfa okay so the string is the input
of the dfab
then let's say
we
pair
a machine a dfab with
the input
for that machine
and
if b
accept
w we said that the whole thing here
the whole thing here
okay is in adfa
so
we want to
prove that adfa is a decidable language
then by definition
we need to build up a turing machine and
don't forget that
for the transmission we want to
construct
our input is the whole string here
okay it's the whole string here not b
only not w only it's actually b and w
and
the whole string is the input of our
turing machine we want to build a turing
machine
for any
possible don't use w anyway so for any
possible string
if x is in a dfa the two machine must
answer accept
x not in adfa the machine must answer
reject
okay if we can build up such a turing
machine we prove that adfa is a
decidable language
so
let's do it okay
so let's say
we build up we construct a two machine
like this
on input
b and w
where b is a dfa and the w is a string
okay
here we need uh i must note that
you need to pay attention to how
uh the trim machine construction
all through this course
remember what i what we just said what i
just i just said that for any string in
all possible
for any for all possible strings
actually
the alphabet here is the turing
machine's input
alphabet right so currently maybe you
can consider like utf-8 utf-16 or some
other
code you can
use as input that doesn't matter anyway
for any string that's a key word here
so
we usually consider that
at the zeros step here there is a step
zero here
actually to filter out all
invalid
male formed
input okay
so if you have an input
gibberish input here then
the machine we can we automatically
consider the machine reject
invalid in reject strings of invalid
format okay
and we consider
determining
if the string is
in a valid format the string is valid
is a first is a first step or a zero
step so we don't uh write them in our
construction that's always a there's
always a check for that
so
that's why we write
we have the input then we focus on the
problem we need to solve which is to
determine if
b that given dfa can accept
w or not okay so where b is dfa w is a
string
any string any input string the whole
input string
not
formatted as
this
is automatically rejected
okay
so you can think of that all possible
strings of the encoding
of the turing machine
there is a
adfa here and others on
b
here b accept
w here b reject w and many
string of invalid format and for this
part we already reject them
okay so we don't consider them even in
the proof
always remember that but
reject
strings from this part is still
the task of the turing machine
okay it must do it
anyway so let's say we have a input here
and where b is the dfa and the w is a
string so our two machine just need to
simulate b
on w
okay
and the simulation
will always stops
right
because for
dfa
it's consume one symbol and
do one step and consume one symbol to
one step so you just need to
do
so many
steps of the dfab
then b stops
after b stops you check
if b
stops
in a
in an accept state
the machine and
accept
okay so
this accept
is for m here
okay
this accept means and
accept
sorry
this accept means m
accepts
its own input what is the only input
it's b
w we use oh we use
angle here
to indicate
these
uh math objects are encoded as text
string okay as encoded as text string oh
not really text but a string okay string
of of the alphabet of the two machine
if
b ends in a
non-accepting state
okay then of course reject and the least
reject means n
rejects
the whole
input
string and apparently i guess
we can accept that these two machine can
accept all strings in which b accept w
and reject all strings
in which b reject w or not except w
and of course as i said all in all
strings of invalid format will be
rejected so
and is apparently a decider for adfa
and by definition since
the decider of adfa exists
adfa is a decidable language
okay so that's how we prove it
okay
then next one
that'll be a and f a okay now you know
that a
is for acceptance and f a means we are
talking about
a
noun deterministic finite automata
so the same as we said
we have if we the string for our
turing machine for the termination we
will
construct
b is an nfa and
w is for nfa and if b accept w we say
that the whole string as our input is in
anfa and our two machine the two machine
we want to construct
should accept it
accepted it otherwise it should reject
it
okay
so how do we prove that actually we
already did in a way
because we have proof
via
theorem 139
we have proof
a conversion procedure can convert an fa
into an equivalent dfa right
then we just need to convert a turing
machine
on bw
remember that all strings
of invalid formats
will be rejected automatically so we
don't you know mention that anymore
and
b is nfa and w is a string
since b is
an nfa
we can
implement the procedure actually you
have done a procedure
on your own right you have you have
practiced that
to convert an nfa to dfa and you know
that given any well-formed nfa
converting it to an equivalent dfa is
just you know some
probably very
tedious but it's and
it
it the steps are easy
you just need to be careful
and the careful is not a problem for
computers right so we just use the
procedure to convert b
into
an equivalent dfac
after converting that we know we have
proven that we have proven that
any string
fit into c will
have we will obtain the same result
accept or reject as we fit the string
into b right we have proven that so now
we just need to
we just need to use c
with the same input w
and put the whole thing
into
the turing machine we just construct for
adfa right
so our two machine you can
well not exactly but you can think of
it's like a function called
we
the two machine end here
calls m
as a function
as a procedure call and on
cw on the string cw on the whole input
set of cw then
if n accepts
that means and accept its input cw
we know that
that means c will accept w
and we know that b will accept w
so
our turn machine n
accepts
its input b w
otherwise
since m is a decider it always stops
with accept or reject so if not exact
if not accepts
it's reject so otherwise the two
machines we are constructing here just
need to reject its own input because we
know
c will reject w
then we know b will reject w so we
reject our input b w
okay
then
the two machine we construct here is a
designer for an fa
okay is a designer for an fa
since
nfa are actually decided for a and fa
since the designer for anfa exists nfa
is a decidable language
okay
so next one will be a
regular expression
okay
so if you have a regular expression and
a string
how do you determine that
that regular expression generates the
string w or
the string w is in
the language specified
of the regular string
how do you can you decide that
well
we want to prove that yes it is
decidable we can write we can write a
program which is a turing machine
besides such language
or you can say handle such a problem
okay
so for the same
procedure
we
build a tubing machine p
for a regular
expression and a string 2
to check
then
we use
the procedure we
have on theorem 1.45
to convert the regular expression into
an equivalent nfa
okay
if you don't remember that we we know
that
for three
for three basic uh regular expression
definition and the three advanced
regular expression definition we can
build we can build any equivalent nfa
for the
well for avail for a well-formed
regular expression okay so we convert
that
into a and fa uh sorry f nfa and then we
just need to call
we just need to call
the
tune machine we have on
a
and
f
a
right
on input and f a a and the corresponding
input w
so the same thing goes on here
if and accepts
our turing machine
for a
regular expression accept
that means
this regular expression r
really contains a given string
if n rejects
we know that
w is not in r so our p reject its own
input
okay
so that's about it again you can see how
mathematicians think about the problem
if we have solved a problem like we have
theorem 1.45 we just need to
make our problem
can be solved by the previous
solution then we
we prove it
okay
so again since p is the decider for
a regular expression
then a regular expression is a decidable
language okay we'll prove that
now let's see another type of problems
we are going
to prove here that's that is edfa
the e here
well
maybe for emptiness
what means by emptiness that means give
you a dfa
a dfa
if
the language recognized by this
particular dfa is
empty set
that means
this
this given dfa doesn't accept any string
okay it doesn't accept any string
then we say
the encoding for the dfa or the program
representing a dfa
of which the language is empty set
is in the edfa
edfa okay
all
dfas of which the language is empty set
is in edfa
okay so the language or the problem
means
if i give you
a dfa
for example as a python source code or
or as a c or c plus java source code as
a file
let me give you that file okay it is
possible is it possible for you to write
a program
to read in
the source file i gave you
and
tell me that
that
dfa
accept no strings
or that dfa accept some strings
can you write the program to answer that
question
that's what we are going to prove here
if we prove that edfa is a decidable
language that means you it is possible
for you to write a program to do this
otherwise
it's not okay so how to prove it
for edfa
then we want to uh
yes we want to
oh i want to prove it is decidable so
again we want to construct a turing
machine
which can decide it
okay
so we know uh according to the operation
of dfa we know that
a dfa accepts some string if and only if
from the start state
by traveling along the arrows of the dfa
it is possible to reach and accept state
right
remember that for dfa you have
many states and star states and some of
them are accept states right
then
if there is a path let's say if there is
a path
going from start state to accept states
then
by definition for this example ac will
be accepted by this dfa
right
or something like a b c
a
then
this then the the
dfa here also accept
b
a also accept a c a something like that
right so as long as there is a path
directed path from the start state to
any of the accept states defined by in
the for the dfa
it accepts some string
okay
so
we can just
use the following algorithm to do
the graph traversal okay
so we mark
first uh when we have a dfa
imagine that
we can conceptually
think about the dfa as the graph
directed graph right
then we mark the star state of a
the star state of a
and repeat
the loop here
from any state marked
we see that
if there is a transition
coming from a marked state
to any state
from sorry from any marked state
and to any state
unmarked then we mark that state okay so
that's it
this procedure is just a
graph traversal
so simply put
for example
if this is a star state then and
there is some
directed path here
sorry
like this
then we can we just say that we mark
start state
and there are three transitions right
then the three transition from a max
marked marks state to sum a max state we
mark those states then we mark those
state then we mark this state then we
mark this state we just repeat the whole
the whole procedure and the mark
unmarked state
and since
the states of a dfa
is finite the number of the states of
the of a dfa is finite it's you know
it's a requirement for dfa so
uh the loop will stop because in every
iteration of the loop
there will be
more than one
not more than one one uh there will be
more than zero
states to be marked if no if no states
can be marked
if no state can be marked the loop will
stop right
so
it will mark
either
marked all states connected from the
start state or
marked all possible
states in the dfa
then
we check
if any accept state is marked during the
process
if yes
then we know that their excel if there
are some paths from start state to some
of the accept states in the dfa so we
accept
because along
the arrows
that we collect the symbol along the
arrows we will know at least that those
strings will be accepted by that dfa
if absolutely
no accept
oh sorry no accept state is marked that
means there is no path from star state
so we need to
that means the dfa
recognized empty set it accepts nothing
no string right so t
accepted
t accepted because no accept states will
be reachable from the start state
otherwise otherwise we just need to
collect
we just need to collect the symbols on
the symbols
on the
arrow for example the symbol we just
need to collect the symbols on the arrow
we know that this dfa will accept those
strings since the dfa will accept some
strings that means
arrow of a
is not empty set
then
a
the string ace encoding will not
be in edfa
so
t will
will reject
its input
okay
since
this procedure
very similar to
the previous example we
uh introduced to
detect connected graph
right
and you can also see that as long as
accept states are connected from sarsat
then the dfa must accept some strings
then it will not recognize empty set and
will not be in edfa otherwise
the dfa
accepts no string it recognize empty set
then
the encodings of a will be in edfa and
the whole
the whole problem here the language is
decidable that means we can write a
program to decide it
okay
so that's for edfa
then
we want to check
the equivalence
eq
of two given dfas
okay
if you have if someone give you two dfas
and b
and xu
the language recognized by a and the
language recognized by b are they
identical
if they are
this
input string is in eqdfa otherwise it's
not
and
whether or not eqdfa is
a decidable language means that
whether or not we are able to write a
program as in turing machine
to decide this language
okay
so the answer here is yes so we want to
construct that during turing machine
and to control that turing machine
well uh we use the closure property for
that
okay
so
let's uh think about it this way
um
input a b which a and b are both the
face
okay dfas
and think about it
for
the uh for dfa a
it will recognize
language l of a right
that's uh imagine that
this is all possible strings and
the most general situation here is that
you have
l of a here
and you have l of b here
right
and
when
a log of a
and l of b
are identical
that means you don't have
the gray area here
right
if they are exactly the same
it's like this one
there's no gray area here
so what is the gray area the gray area
is
a
l of a
airbase here right
and
arrow of b complement
that'll be this part
right
the intersection of l of a
and the error of b com a complement of l
b is the gray area here
and for the same reason we have
l of b
the intersection of l of b
and the complement of l of a here
then we do the union
sorry we do a union of these two
we will have
the union of the gray area
right
then let's call the union of the gray
area
uh
a language
okay is it possible to construct a dfa
of which the language is the gray area
it is possible
why because
we have a here
right
and we can manipulate a to hat to give
a lot of a complement right we have done
that for commercial property proof
how do we do that this case is easy we
just need to uh change accept states to
non-accept states and
non-accepted to accept states then the
answer will be reversed right
and then we do
intersection with b then we get
this one right
we get
a prime which
recognized
error of a complement
and we do intersection
with b
it's a wrong notation but
we can do
a new dfa
recognizing such a language
and for the same reason we can
have a dfa we can construct dfa
recognizing this
language and since we have dfa
let's say
a plan b
recognizing this language and also a dfa
that say b a prime
recognizing this language
we can
construct a new dfa
c
by doing intersection
of
a prime b and a b prime sorry
b a prime right
oh
i should do this right
okay sorry about that
that'll be this
b prime a okay
so we do a
union which is also in a closure
property here
then
l of c
is
this thing
and why we why would we want to do that
because
after we
have dfac
after we have the fac
we just need to call
e
dfa
the transmission of edfa to check
if the dfac
the language recognized by c is
empty set
if
l of c
is empty set
t will accept c
except c as a program then
the two machine we are constructing
accepts
this input because these inputs are two
dfas of which
the languages are identical
otherwise
if t rejects that means l of c
is not empty set that means something
here or something here or both of them
then t rejects then we
reject
our input
because there are some strings in the
gray area that means l of a and error of
b
are not identical
see
via the
construction of
dfac
we can use
our two machine for edfa
to check
if
the the dfac recognized empty set and if
dfac
empty set then we know that
l of a and the l of b
are identical so we can decide the
equivalence of two given dfas
we can write a program to do that okay
so that's for dfa that's for regular
languages
let's see decidable language concerning
context free languages so
the same thing
acfg that means give you a grammar and a
string can you determine that
the given grammar generates the given
string
and of course you do because
you know that's uh
basically uh
cyk algorithm is what it does right so
give you a grammar you run
coik algorithm on that string and yes
yes no no you know that so it's possible
and here we also
we can also prove that
so
we build up a two machine here
that would be contextual grammar and a
string
so we
convert
g
to an equivalent grammar in chonsky
normal form as we
introduced previously right
and
here actually as i just described you
can run a cyk algorithm then you will
know the answer so that's decidable okay
but the step two here is more
well
a stupid but
safe way okay
we
try all derivations
with n two n plus one steps
where n is the length of w
and is the length of w
we try we released all possible
derivations
then
uh except for n equals zero
you know that um
if n equals zero you just uh list all
derivations with once with one step okay
because it is possible that uh
you have something like this
anyway then
by doing this we effectively effectively
tries
all uh the machine tries all possible
derivations
and the derived length
of n
so you can see that if no
if any of the derivation generates w
that means
from
the grammar the star variable of the
grammar
the terminal string w can be generated
so
we accept the string
we accept the input the whole input okay
and if not that means it is impossible
for the grammar to generate the given
terminal w so reject and the reject here
means as the two machines we are
constructing reject its own
input
okay so that's uh acfg
so the same thing goes to the cfg if a
grammar
given grammar
is it uh
well the grammar generates some terminal
string or absolutely no terminal string
okay
all the grammar generates no terminal
strings
is in ecfg okay that's mt
emptiness for cfg
is it a decidable language
and we want to prove that it is okay so
we need to construct a decider here
then how to construct that
and the uh procedure is
intuitive that
you have for example uh in the grammar
there are many rules right so maybe you
have like a
a b
c
d
and the b
a c c
c d and you have c a a b
d
and you have d
and uh let's say
it's a b and you have d
b or you have b can generate a b d
something like that right
and let's say if a is the star variable
then what we want to do is that
firstly mark all terminals in the rule
of grammar g
so let's say mark terminals marked
terminals marked terminals marked
terminals mock terminals
okay then you check
if
there is any
any
rule the right hand side are all marked
if yes you mark the head of that rule so
for this short simple example oh okay
this one for this short example let's
say you say you see
b may become b d
the right hand side are all marked then
you mark b
if you marked a new head
you go back to see the right hand side
and the mark
all
the
head of the variable so we have also d
here right because this is all marked
then we marked b
b
d
okay
again so you got the right hand side all
marked right hand side all marked
then
you mark the head right mark the head
mark the head
and then go on so
c
and you it's already marked because of
this
right
after you you mark all the variable that
you can mark
because the variables the rules of uh
finite and the number of variables are
finite so for each each uh
iteration of the loop if you cannot mark
anymore then you stops otherwise it will
stop after all variables are marked to
see
not sure which one but depends on the
grammar
so
after the loop stops
you check if the start variable
is marked or not
if the star variable is not marked that
means
from the variable it is not possible to
reach a terminal string
so we accept r our term two machine
accept the grammar g here
why because what we want is f g
m t set
right
so r except g because we know that from
the start variable g
it's not possible to generate terminal
strings
otherwise
for this example we have we know from
the
star variable of that
that
of the example we have we can do this
and then
b become b d
right
and then d become d
so you need just need to reverse the
process of your marking
and you will get at least one derivation
from the variable to return to a
terminal string
that means
the grammar can generate something so
the language of the grammar is not an
empty set so
r reject grammar because it's not empty
okay
so that's why we can
design
a decider to decide ecfg so ecfg is a
decidable language by definition
okay
after emptiness we want to know the
equivalence eq
cfg
if you are given g and h
as cfg
can you write a program to determine
that l of g and the error of edge are
identical is this possible
uh actually no it's not possible ecfg is
actually undecidable okay but in this
chapter chapter 4 we don't discuss that
so
we don't uh do anything about it here
that's uh
do the next
uh theorem
4.9
we want to prove every context speech
language is decidable
okay
so this is a
well
interesting theorem although not very
difficult but it's interesting because
see
before this theorem what we what we are
we were doing is that
for a
particular language
we prove
its decidability by construct
a turing machine a specific time machine
as the decider of this language that's
what we
did
from the start of this chapter
but you see that for
theorem 4.9 what we want to do is
prove
every
contest-free language is decidable
right it's different right we want to
prove a lot of language at the same time
instead of only one
see the difference now
so
so we want to
we want to uh
we need to build up
two machines two machines
for
all the context free languages
that means for
you if you give me any one context free
language i want i need to
give you one two machine decides that's
context-free language
and you know that
different
context-free language you need different
decider right such that the decider
can decide the
some particular
cfl
okay
so how do we do that
well not really difficult i just want to
uh
clarify what we are doing what what uh
what we are doing is slightly different
than what we were doing
from this chapter
and what we are doing here is still use
you know
some kind of uh something like
cyk but that's different
slightly different
what we what can we do is like
let's design
a tuning machine mg
okay
let's design a tuning machine mg
and the two machine mg
as
the
procedure here
it is not
a complete turing machine
g here
is a
is some
extra data
that
you need to provide to make it
a concrete tube machine
well the concept is quite easy if you
think about you know the programming
language they have macro
oh sorry macro right
they have macro
for example in
c
you can do a define
sorry
you can do something like define
uh what am i doing max
a b
you can do that define next a b
and to be what to be
a
larger than b
if yes
a
otherwise
sorry that's a column right
b
and something like this
and see
you use
this one in your program
and
when it encounters
next a b
this part
will be plugged into here
and before that
it is the program here is not really a
com complete program it's not really a
whole concrete program right
only if you provide a definition here
then it will be a complete program
and if you you know although we don't
want to do that but if you give another
weird
definition
or just a
anyway it will work as a concrete
program but maybe the
uh the
result is wrong but
it will be a concrete program so the
same thing goes
here g here
is unknown when we write the program
here
so it is not
a complete program it cannot be wrong
unless you define g
okay but
after we complete this program
you know
someone gives you a g
you just need to put g
here
then
the
program here becomes
runnable becomes a concrete
machine turing machine instance
then
this
turing machine
is the decider for what for l of g
right
so
after you get a g
you plug into here then mg becomes
the decider of l of g
that's why
every context free language is decidable
right
because for every context language
as long as you give me the context free
grammar of that language then i put into
the corresponding
place here then
the program we wrote here can be the
decider of that particular
language
so every contest language is decidable
we
prove
a lot of languages to be decidable at
the same time with you know
the flexibility of the programming skill
something like that
okay
[Applause]
so
let's say after we prove
this theorem
what we know
we go back to the language we already
the class of languages we already know
that firstly in chapter one we define
dfa and we define that
all languages recognizable by dfa
is regular right
that's how regular languages are defined
and then
we know that there are something outside
of regular languages which one
we have here right
but this one is context free language
and we can prove that context free
language
contains regular languages why
because pda
without using a stack is an is an nfa
and nfa can recognize every regular
languages
and pda recognize
context free languages
and there are context free languages not
regular so we know the relationship is
appropriate this way
okay
and then we know that
we just now know that
every contest language is a decidable
language
right
so context language must be within
decidable
right we just proof it that's what we
just proved
okay
and then
are they the same class or
they are something here
if there's nothing here then they are
the same class otherwise if there is
something here then you know the graph
here is a proper
uh representation of the relationship
between the two classes
and actually there are something here
and
probably many things we already know
like for this example am
bn
cn
we already proved that the language is
not context-free and you can easily
imagine that this language is decidable
right
it is very easy for turing machine to
you know you give it as a aapb cc
because
you can just
you don't need to write
anything you just need to compare a one
a one b one c okay back to here one a
one b one c and a hit space then accept
right the tool machine is a piece of
cake for turing machine even a m b n c n
d n or
e n or f n doesn't matter for two
machine all can be done
right so that's decidable but not
context free
so that's a example here or we actually
have this one
w
separator w w
0 1 string
right we have this
this one
or
that one
all these you can easily prove that they
are not context free and we already
proved this language to be decidable so
a relationship here is okay okay
then next question
we know that by definition
decidable must be within
recognizable right because by definition
what
what uh the definition for decidable
language is that you have decider for
decider for all strings
it will accept
well
strings in the language will be accepted
and string not in a language must be
rejected but for recognizable
you only need to accept all the strings
in the language
so apparently decidable is within
recognizable because
any language
fulfill satisfy the definition of
decidable language
is automatically recognizable
but the problem is
is there anything in this region
that's the problem right
if there is no there's
nothing no language in this region
then that means decidable and
recognizable are the same class
if there is something here
then the relationship will be
the diagram here
okay
so that's
that is
the
question we need to discuss next time