after introduce the class p let's
introduce another important time
complexity class mp
and
before that we need to introduce the
concept of a polynomial verifiability
and let's take a look at the two
languages the two problems here
uh hamiltonian path and
composite
for hematanium path actually i think
we've introduced the problem that
this problem right
when given
a directed graph and specify two nodes s
and t
if the
problem instance here
over the input string here
uh
is in hemitanium hematanium path that
means
on the directed graph g here there is a
hamiltonian path from
the first specified node as
to the second specified node t
okay
so
uh for this
for this problem let's take a look at
the one example here okay so uh
if we have uh
if we have a
path problem instance here
then
it is uh
of course uh the this one is a simple
uh directive graph
so it's fairly easy for us to observe
one hamiltonian path what is a
hamiltonian path that means uh you need
to pass all the nodes once and only once
okay so for example from s here and we
the the specified path goes to here
here here
here and by six
okay
so we have a hamiltonian path s
one two three four five six t
right
but if uh if you don't have that
information and the directed graph is
very large and the problem becomes very
difficult actually and
for lack of better information you may
need to
try all the permutation of the node of g
right because g is
v and e
and it is possible that you need to try
the
factorial here
so
uh this is a hamutan path and
with without better
uh algorithms we may need
a lot of times to try and get the answer
and the over ends
get the answer
as to yes or no yes there is a
hematologist from st or no there is no
hamiltonian path from snt
okay so a hematime path goes through
every node exactly once that's the
definition
and i'm telling you the problem of
hamiltonian path is that give you uh
again
uh given a directed graph and a two
specified node is there a hamiltonian
path from s to t
okay
and for this problem uh
let's think about if someone
if someone give you
an answer
okay for the for exactly the graph here
we have an answer right
the bold
arrows here
is the is the answer marked by i don't
know someone and
how long can you
uh how how much time you need to verify
if that's an answer and if that's an
answer then that means
this graph here
and s
t here
is
in
hamiltonian past
right
so
here we don't
need to
come up with an answer ourselves
we just need to verify we just need to
verify
if some given answer is really the
answer to proof that
the input string is
in the language
okay so let's see another example here
that's composite
and if you have an integer here
can this integer
be
written as
two integers
written as the multiplication the
product of the
two integers the result of the
multiplication of the two integers
can
x be written as
p
q
that's the problem okay so for example
if we have a
you know like 20 here
then we know that okay uh 20 can be
written as
10 times 2 probably right then
20 is in composite
right
and
here we come up with the answer
ourselves
okay
let's say
is a
a composite
well probably many of
many of you know that 57 is a composite
right but let's say it is a very large
composite it's very difficult or we need
a lot of time to
try a lot of
possible combinations of integers to
calculate if
they multiply together we get x which is
57 here
and on the other hand
if someone
okay if someone
gives you
three and
okay someone gives you 3 and 19
and all you have to do is
multiply 3 and 19 and you found that oh
it's 57
so
this information this information
proof that
x
or let's say more specifically this
information proved 57
to be
in composite
okay so remember this concept
if you are given
some extra information
firstly
can you
use that information
to prove the membership of the input
strings and if you can how much time you
need to do that job
that's what we are going to talk
about here okay
so let's uh
define
verifier which is basically turing
machine okay but
we
use some
slightly different definition here but
it's
uh
a verifier is a turing machine
okay
let's say a verifier for language a
is a turing machine b or an algorithm b
where
a the language a
is the string or the string
that
we
accept
with
some
extra information
okay
and
for the example we just have
we said that
a verifier for language composite
it will accept
v will accept o
x
p
q
right or you have some other kind of
encoding here anyway for this exam for
that example we already have like uh 15
57 and
3 19 something like that and by using 3
19 we know that 57 is in
compulsive right
so
we
can
determine
the membership
of some stream
to some language
based on
extra information
okay that's what we are talking about
here
and
since v uh sorry yeah since b is still a
two machine
uh we need to measure the running time
of b
and here is the different uh slight
different a slightly different part we
measure the time the run in time of a
verifier
only in terms of the length of w
and
what differences you say
actually
since b is a two machine and
the
the input string for v is actually
w and c
right
so how long is w and c that would be the
length of w
plus the length of c
right
then why
why can we just consider only in terms
of w
because here at least in this semester
at least in this chapter chapter 7 time
complexity
we only care about
polynomial time verifier
okay that's it we only talk about
polynomial time verifier we don't talk
about other possibilities
so
because we only talk about polynomial
time verifier and
if you remember that for turing machine
to do the job to execute
it reads
one
tape
location tab space
with one transition
so the time and space is connected by
this relationship
then
it doesn't matter if we consider both w
and c
or just w
because
we focus on polynomial time only
so
if a verifier
runs
in polynomial time
of the total length
then that verifier runs in polynomial
time of only w
and vice versa
right
because
the point verifier can cannot run longer
than polynomial time of w
the
length of c must be within polynomial
time of length w so it doesn't matter
which one
the total length or just w
we use to align the time calculation
because polynomials per number is still
polynomial right so that's the
that's the key here and why do we and
why do we choose to
uh
measure time of a verifier only in terms
of length w because that's easier
for uh
for putting verifier and the decider
together and talk about
some particular language
because the input string is always w
and we know that verify need extra
information and we also know that we
focus on polynomial time verifier so
that extra information must be within
the polynomial of
the input string w we talk about if that
string is in the
target language or not
okay so that's why we do things this way
okay
then
polynomial time verifier runs on
polynomial time in length of w okay
then we
define that a language a
a language a
is
polynomially verifiable
predominantly verifiable
if it has a polynomial time verifier
okay
so consider what we were talking about
previously we talked about a language a
is
decidable
right or not and if it is polynomially
if it has a polynomial time what
decider
right so we replace
decidable design
decider
here with verifiable verify
verifier
then we create
the class of
mp
sorry
we defined that
mp
is the class of languages
that have
polynomial time verifiers
okay
so compared to class p class p is the
class of languages that have polynomial
time deciders
okay so
that uh it's a symmetric definition
right so
a language a is polynomially decidable
if it is if it has a polynomial time
decider
a language a is polynomially verifiable
if it has a polynomial time verifier
and class p
is the class of languages that have
polynomial time deciders
and class mp is the class of languages
that have polynomial time very files
okay
then
for the
verifier we need to we the verifier
needs
extra information
okay
so the c is not constant here the c is
certificate
that's why we usually used we usually
use c here because that's a certificate
what certificate
certify
w is in
the language a so what is in language a
string w and what is c
c is the actual information
act as
a proof
for proving that
w is in a
okay
so let's go back to our
to our example here
see if you have the graph here you don't
know the answer and you need to
calculate it and to find find out if
there is a hamiltonian path
right
and on the on the other hand if someone
asks you this problem instance g
and specify s here
and t here
and
provide you
an extra
an item of actual information that
one two uh
that's i i mark
and mark the note the other way so it's
easier
uh okay uh anyway one two three four
five six okay and someone provides an
extra an item of extra information as
s
5 6 t
okay so somehow you've got the
information here
and according to this information
what can you do
you can
check
s
and okay next one's two check if there
is a directed path from so2
and then check if there is a directed
pass from s24
and repeat the checking here three
one five 6
t
then check if all nodes
in g
if all nodes in g
are passed
or let's say are on the path here so s
3 1 5 6 t
that's the oh that's
those are all the notes of g
so the path here is really the
hamiltonian path on g from s to t
so we know that yes
this problem instance is really
inheritance pass
okay
and
for example here we have 57 and someone
give you 3 19 okay
so
we know that okay 3 times 19 57
then so the existence of 3
proved that 57 is incomposite
okay
so that's why we
say
see there
is certif certificate or proof
okay
and your algorithm acts
on the proof
v
acts on the proof
okay
then here is the important part
previous uh
many students got confused here
that okay
for this example
what if the c is wrong
what is c is wrong like
someone give you
and what should be
here
do
what should we do
actually
we just need to
reject string w here
because
the evidence
doesn't
support
the membership
of
the input string here to be a member of
the language
okay so
the algorithm v
verifier here
doesn't need to know
the correct answer
it just need to act on
correct
evidence to report the answer
if the evidence
that if the given evidence is wrong
then that is
the
is not
responsible for
give out the correct answer
for this example if
the problem is 57 and someone pro
provides you
4 and
12 and the algorithm do
uh
that's
4 x 12 and 48 which is not 57 so the
evidence here does not support 57 to be
composite so we just need to reject the
string
okay so don't get con don't get confused
here
v doesn't need to know the answer read
that the job of v
is
acting on correct evidence and
when the evidence is correct when the
certificate is correct then it must give
the correct result
otherwise it doesn't matter it just need
to you know report rejection even though
57 is really the composite
or for the example here okay let's do
that again so one two three four five
six
we know that the graph from s to t
there is really
an inheritance path
but if for exactly the same proper
instance here and someone provides
for example uh like
s
one two three 4 5 6 t someone give you
c
as
this sequence
then
your verifier just need to verify
if that is a hamiltonian path
so from s
to 1
there is no
directive path right so the c is wrong
and because c is wrong in this case
the verifier just need to reject the
string
again verifier doesn't need to report
correct answer
if
the certificate or proof is wrong
okay don't get confused many times many
students get confused here they think
we must know the answer even
if
c is
wrong actually no
we just need to verify
go okay
so
basically it's quite different from
decider because decider look at w and
decider must be able to know the answer
but the verify here the job of verifier
is
to report the correct answer if the
certificate is correct otherwise it can
it just need to reject the string
w
okay
so
if there is no problem here
that's
uh go on with the definition
and it's quite weird that the class is
called
mp
right
we call the class p because
the language there
the language in that class
the languages in that class are
polynomial time decidable
we probably call it pd or something but
we call it p
and since the language here
the languages
have
polynomial time verifiers why don't we
call it like a pv
something like that
actually np
is not from
polynomial time verifiers
okay
the name
np is not from
pronunciation
the term mp comes from
non-deterministic
polynomial time
okay non-deterministic
polynomial time so that's why
we call it np
so actually cross p
is dp
why because d
not decidable d is deterministic
okay deterministic
polynomial time
and
so for previous
so previous for previous definition
we define
deterministic
turing machines
can decide
some languages and other languages
are in
dp which is p actually
so dp
is the class of languages that can be
determined sorry decided by
deterministic
turing machine in polynomial time and
mp
are
languages
that can be determined decided
in polynomial time by
non-deterministic machine
that's the origin that's
those are
original definitions but now
we change the definition of mp
to
languages that have polynomial time
verifiers
okay so we adopt in in the textbook we
adopt the newer definition the new
definition here
and firstly
we need to prove
the old definition and the new
definition
are
equivalent
so
actually
the class and the class np
does not change at all
okay the old definition and new
definition
are equivalent
so that's our
theorem
7.20 okay
we want to prove that
a language
is in mp
okay remember that we have we we use new
definition here so
a language is in np means
that language is polynomially verifiable
or
you say that
it has a polynomial time verified
if and only if
the language is decided
by some
non-deterministic polynomial time to
emission
okay so you can see that
this part
is
actually
the old definition
and
we want to prove that new definition if
and only if all the definition
that's what we want to do here
okay
so how do we do that
well it's actually quite straightforward
it's not uh
well
it's not difficult but uh slightly
tricky so
pay attention to it
okay so firstly
firstly
if a language is in np by our definition
here
it has a polynomial time verifier
right it has a polynomial time verifier
so
if
a is in mp a language a is an mp by our
definition there is a verb
verifier that runs in polynomial time
okay
and given the information here we can
construct
a non-deterministic machine which can
decide that language
in polynomial time
that is if a language is
in mp by our new definition
it satisfies the old definition okay
so
how do we do the first uh step
for language a
we
have b here
then we construct a non-deterministic
machine m
since we know that
the running time of v
is bounded
by
polynomial of the length of the input
string
okay
so we just
need to non-deterministically
select c
of length at most k
the whole statement here means that we
well first if you uh read some other
books some other books use like guessing
here
guessing here but actually we don't
guess we try everything
and don't forget that
for non-deterministic computation
all the paths
you must you must take all possible
passes and to see the result
let's go through the proof and i'll give
you the example by using the
pentatonic path
okay
and then
for each branch we just wrong run
verifier on the string here
and also the certificate here
if any branch if any branch
accept
remember the definition of
non-deterministic computation
then we accept
and accept w
okay otherwise if
uh reject and if all branches reject
and reject w
okay
so
kind of confusing it right now right but
let's take a look at the example here
okay
so
imagine that
you are given
a problem instance we construct a
non-deterministic computation and we
have verifier
okay and then
we construct a
non-deterministic uh non-deterministic
turing machine what does the two machine
do
okay let's say s here right and that
number the note one two three four five
seven oh sorry one two three four five
six and t seven
then
what uh
for the proof we just
described what does n what does the
non-deterministic machine do
firstly
it starts
right
then we know start from s
i mean uh the path
now
let's
imagine that the non-deterministic
turing machine we are designing right
now it
tries to construct a hamiltonian path
okay
so you can imagine that
from
the specified node as
what
should the next note
b
okay consider this problem
then it is possible that from one
two
three
four
right
start from s and the next
then start from 1
you will have try have to try 2
four
five six
and start from through two
one
three
four
five six
okay from three then you got one two
four five six from five
one two
three four six and from six one two
three four five
okay
then
keep if you keep doing that
finally you will get
a path
possible path on the graph like
as
uh
3 1
6 5 2
and t right
and then you give the path to v
to check if
a given problem instance
with
with the c here
if the verifier can verify the
membership of the problem instance
of time item path
if all possibilities
all computational branches
result in rejection
then
our non-deterministic tuition here
reject
the problem instance
and for this example exactly
we will have at least
one
right uh there is a like here
two
one
sorry a two
2 4
3 1 5 6 t
so we will have a computational branch
here
try
certificate s
as
two three
two
four three one five six t
with this certificate
our verifier
verifies the problem instance here to be
in hamiltonian path
so
this case will result in accept
as long as there is one branch
accepted then
the whole time machine accepted
right
so we constructed a non-determination
machine
this which can decide hamiltonian
pathway
and
the verifier
is a deterministic machine so
each branch of our non-dimensional
machine can simulate that two mission
so the key point here is that
our non-deterministic machine
try actually generate all possible
solutions
and give v
try
all possible problem
possibilities
and as long as one of them
accepted then the whole machine accepted
and you can see that
the number here
in this case is actually about
the factorial of the number of vertex
right
so this one
is greater than polynomial of the input
string but it doesn't matter
because
what we care about of
running time is the height
of computational tree not the width
okay not the width
so that's a very important concept here
okay
so
and we know that
the verifier the
the running time of the verifier
is within polynomial of the input string
and
our
non-deterministic
turing machine only need
about also
polynomial time of the input to generate
to generate
the certificate all possible certificate
see so for this example how
for exactly this example containing path
how many steps approximately
our the non-deterministic machine need
to generate
a certificate
it's about the number of verdicts right
that's well within the
polynomial time
polynomial of the
length of the input string
so that's what
the proof described here
okay
so
if you have if for language if the
language has
a polynomial time verifier
we can
construct a polynomial time decider
by
generating
all possible
by generating all possible certificate
and let's
verify to verify
based on
the certificate
to verify if that string
is in the language
[Applause]
okay
okay so
if you have a polynomial time
a non-deterministic machine to decide a
language
why
can we say that
there is a
there is a polynomial time verifier
okay that the tricky part here okay
let's say
it's quite a tricky okay it is quite
tricky so you need to pay attention to
this
so let's say
if if there is a
non-deterministic machine which can
decide language a
okay so that's the old definition of
class np we have a non-deterministic
machine running in polynomial time
and
how
the non-deterministic machine decide
the language
for a string w
the
non-deterministic machine
well you know run
like this right if you remember
a computational tree we talked about
previously
so you will have something like
this and that
and this and this
and and so on
right
so the process
the process
of the non-deterministic machine
is running this way
then
we stimulate and
enter
and the question you were asked
immediately is that how can we do that
if we simulate
and here
then we will re we will have an
exponential time
determination machine right
because the tree node the total number
of tree nodes is about the polynomial
time sorry polynomial of the length of
the input string
well
we want to simulate the n but not
exactly simulate everything
remember that verifier can ask for
extra information
why we
use the term extra information instead
of and answer
in the first place
because
the c here certificate certificate or
proof here doesn't need to be the answer
okay although
for the previous examples we
gave the answers as certificate
but certificate doesn't need to be the
answer
in this case
we ask
the certificate to provide
which
computational branch we need to simulate
okay pretty tricky
so for this example let's say
and eventually accept w
and the path
the computational path
for n
to accept w
uh let's say is like this
this one
and
this one and this one
and this one
and this one and accept
okay
for example here
so
let's see
here
the certificate c here
we want
it to be
the branch selector okay
so when we simulate and here
we know that okay
from the starting configuration
there are four branches
then we took a look at c
okay we look at the c
and c is a sequence
and so
c tell us
for the first step although you have
four branches you need to take the third
one
very tricky huh so
three here then we know that okay we
don't need to simulate this part this
part and this part we just need to
simulate this one okay
then when we hit
the second configuration here
and c tell us you only need to go the
first branch you don't need to take
about uh take you don't need to care
about the third and the second oh okay
so let's
ignore that
again
we need to
simulate the second one
and for example
assume that it is the fourth
branches and
six branches
okay then accept it
so you see
it's quite weird but if you have a
non-deterministic machine which can
decide
the language
in polynomial time that means
that means
the height here
is a polynomial of the length of length
string
right
since the height here is the polynomial
of the length of intersting
how many branches you have
about polynomial amount of the
uh
you you uh of the input string length of
the input chain right
so the length of c here
will be within the a polynomial will be
bounded of a polynomial of the length of
the input string which is w here
okay
so you see
in this way
v
here the v we construct here
can
verify any
input string
to see if it
if this
if the input string is in
language a or not
if you provide
suitable
appropriate information
to guide our simulation
to reach the accept
accepting configuration
okay
and as we explained the whole process is
polynomial so verify the verify here is
total polynomial time verifier
and it is pronoun the highest polynomial
the length of c is of course
bounded by the polynomial of the length
of w
okay
so as long as
a language has
some polynomial a non-deterministic
polynomial timer uh decider
we can construct a polynomial time
verify
so
any language
satisfy the old definition
it is
it is in class mp by
new definition
okay
so
we prove that
new definition and all definition are
equivalent
that means
we can use the new definition as
okay we can use the new definition as
the definition of class and p here
okay
then why why why do we want to do that
or
what's the reason for the textbook
author to choose new definition instead
of all definition
well
i'm not sure i'm not i'm not sure why
they
do it but
but i think there are some reasons and
first one
okay the most important reason is that
you see
for all definition determines the two
machine polynomial time and the
non-deterministic to machine polynomial
time
they both we consider
a decider for both
computational models right because
deterministic non-deterministic
however non-deterministic computational
models are
not so practical it's very it's kind of
difficult to imagine
right
now
we use the same
computational model from in in our new
definition we use same complete
computational model which is
deterministic two machine
that's easier to imagine
that's easier for us to think about it
right because
for example our computers are
deterministic
computational models
so
based on
identical computational models
we define
polynomial class p as
you can use this computational model to
decide the languages
and
mps you can use the same computational
model to verify to verify the languages
okay
so by
using the same
computational models it's easier for us
to get idea regarding
how difficult
the languages are
easier than you know switch to different
computation model which is
non-deterministic that's uh
more difficult
okay
okay then
let's
extend uh sorry
follow the same definition let's say we
define
n time of t of n
remember that we define t time of t of n
now we define n time of t of n
okay we define that
a language
can be decided by a
big o of t of n times
non-deterministic machine
we say that
the language is in n time of t of n
okay
so for example if the t of n
is
n squared
so n time
of
n square
means
the language has a decider
running in big o of t of n and the
computational model
is non-deterministic transmission
okay
and
by using this different
definition and firstly connect back to
old definition
we know that
mp
is actually
union of all possible k
n time of
n to the case power
okay
so
the expression here is exactly described
the class divided by the old definition
of class mp
since what we already
proved the equivalence of our definition
a new definition so we can surely have
mp equals to
expressions here
okay