hi
uh last time we talked about the
definition of
finite time 10 and
actually regular language
we defined a format or specification
of final automata and says that
the length any language if you can find
some finite automata to recognize it
then we call that language regular
language
and i also mentioned that in this
analogy
we you know kind of consider
languages as problems and
strings as the problem instance
of that kind of problem and someone
might ask
that why do we want to
think of computation this way problem
solving this way
well the answer is well not
everyone's answer my answer to this
to this question is firstly
consider that
everything
computation is basically
uh we need to
make it we need to
symbolize the whole thing in order to
do the operations the computations
right actually everything
we communicate with languages
by languages i mean natural languages
like
i'm trying to speak uh english right now
and i am a mandarin or chinese
native speakers so
i can communicate with either language
without difficulty but
the point is no matter
we communicate with speaking or
writings like currency
i write something here so i draw online
regular language and the regular
language is actually
a string of symbols right r e g
u l a r a space
l n g u a g e
so everything is a string
the problem is only what kind of
alphabet
the string belongs to okay
so imagine that imagine that
if you have a alphabet and
from the alphabet you compose some
string like one plus
one equals two
and you can also compose that 2
plus 3
equals 5 and
you can compose that plus
1 1 plus
or something like 1 plus
3 equals
1 2 and go on
and go on then
if there is a machine maybe find
automata maybe not
anyway an abstract machine
can correctly it's a
it's just a showcase okay can correctly
accept all correct
addition for example accept this string
accept this string not
accept the string not accept this string
okay so perhaps uh
you have that machine and
you give it like 20
plus 1 1 equals
31 and this machine accept
or you give it something wrong like
two plus one equal to five and
another except or in
uh in some wrong format
like one plus
1 plus another accept
okay so in
in some way we must consider that
this machine and
know how to do addition
or we can say that the machine m solves
the addition problem it knows how to do
addition if you can accept
arguments like list you probably can
accept that accepted analogy
i said languages are
problems and strings
are instances of that problems
okay that's why we discuss
computation this way as
if we are only we will be
discussing only string process
in a way yes but
by doing this we are actually thinking
about
something more fundamental more uh
more uh we are talking about core
properties character corrects the
characteristics of computations
okay so that's why we start from
the simplest computational model final
temper
and talk about string processing but the
string processing is not really
stream processing we are using this way
of processing to model computation
itself
so
according to this concept
the whole thing goes like uh firstly we
define
final automaton it's kind of
it's a kind of machine right then
since it's a kind of machine
what kind of language can this machine
process firstly we
we define this kind of machine final
automata
can process regular languages
so regular languages at least in our
textbook
is defined by finite automata
if i give you one final automata
it can recognize exactly one language
right then
on the other hand what language can be
recognized by this kind of machine
we define those language as
regular language okay
so regular language represents
a set of problems
which can be handled or solved
by finite automata
okay don't forget that languages
are problems and final automata
solves some problems maybe all but
we we we leave that later
but final automata can solve
some problems and we want to discuss
what kind of problems can find out
not really this way but we are this we
will be discussing the limitation
the boundary actually of
regular languages which are or which
means those languages can be recognized
by final auto
in analogy those problems can be handled
by
computational machines like final
automata
okay so
since we want to talk about or discuss
the boundary of regular languages
and regular sorry languages
itself as we mentioned language
in this course is just a set
of strings so we call that languages
then in order to facilitate
our discussion on regular languages
we want to introduce some operations
and discuss the property of these
operations
so regular operations okay
and don't be confused by regular the
term we just
okay we just talk uh just mention it as
operations let a and b
be languages and don't forget that
languages
are set that's it
okay sets of strings
sorry pretty difficult to
write this way
okay then
as you may already know
there are some operations for sets and
there are some operations for strings
right operations for sets um i guess
must be introduced
to you in math classes and
operation for strings maybe programming
language
or course regarding programming right
but more or less
everyone knows something about it
so since a and b are languages
and sets of strings
we want to introduce three operations
based on sets and strings
first one is union okay i think
everybody knows this one union
if you have two sets what is the union
you just put them together and there is
no
duplicate elements no duplicate members
okay that's unions so let's have an
example here
if a is
1 sorry
0 0 0 and 1 1
and let's say b is
1 1 0 0
0 1 0 then what is the union of a b
that would be since 1 y is duplicated
member
so we have 0 0
sorry 0 0 0 0 0 and 0
1 0 okay that's the union of a and b
and don't forget that in mathematics
in mathematics there is no order
in the set okay so it doesn't matter if
i write
0 0 0 0 0 or
i write 0 0 0 0 1 0 and 0 0 it doesn't
matter
okay that's very important because
there's no order in
sets of math and the next operation
is concave concatenation
well
in a way it's a operation
of strings right because if you have
one string zero zero and the other
zero one zero when we
denotes this way if x is 0
0 y is 0 1 0 when we
write x and y that means
you just connect the two strings 1 0
0 0 1 0. that's it
that's concretion okay but now
our a and b are sets of strings
not only strings they are state of
strings
so we define concatenation
as everyone
every string in a and every string in b
pair together
and connect the two strings
and form a new set okay
so for the same example a b here
a b what would be
the result of complaining concatenation
it would be 0
0 0 1 1
okay 0 0 0
0 0 0 0
0 0 1 0 and then
1 1 1 1 1 1
zero zero one one zero
one zero that would be the result
of our a and b
i i think it would be easy right
but actually concatenation defined
in this way
in addition to operations of strings
it's also an operation of sets
what operation is called cartesian
product
all right cartesian products between two
sets
are pairing all the possible elements
together
with order by order i mean first one
in the first set and the second one in
the second set
okay so you can see that we are we
actually
also did a cartesian product here
because
you see first elements in a and the
second element in b
first element in a second element in b
and so on so forth like this okay
so that would be cartesian product
but in any way it should be a
known operations it's not anything new
here
okay so
next one is a
probably new operations but actually
it's not
why what is star operation we can write
definition this way okay
but another way to introduce
star operation is that star version
if you have a string and the star
operation
is no matter what
you put an empty string
here okay no matter what empty string
quite artificial but you put empty
string there
and don't forget that empty string means
nothing no symbol
and the empty string's length
is zero the zero is the integer
zero okay not symbol is integer
then you union with a itself
then your union with a
concatenate with a
sometimes we write a
calculate it with a we write it like
a square
okay and also sometimes we write it like
a times a and usually the times
means cartesian product like i just
said and then union let's say
three eighths union
four eight times together union
five and
two many many of them
that's star operation okay
and sometimes we just not sometimes
we use to define this one
a language contains only the
empty string as
a to the 0's power
a a is any language
any string any set of string and its 0th
power
defined as a language contains
only empty string so
for short notation
we can write as oh sorry
not sigma we can write as
with union everything from
i from zero to infinity
hey sorry i
like it okay so let's start operation
so the definition of the three operation
we are trying to talk about
is defined okay and why we want to
you know introduce some operation here
because
by using operation it may help us to
discuss the border of
regular languages and
as mathematician not me i'm not and
i'm not in sorry i'm not a mathematician
i should say in mathematics
they like to scholars they like to
discuss closure properties
why why why would they do that because
uh
by discussing closure properties we can
find many
interesting we can find many interesting
things or new discoveries okay
so for example
uh when you define
addition on integers
so 1 plus 1 is 2
and 2 is an integer so
integer is closed right under the
operation of addition
our positive integer or natural numbers
are closed under the operation
of addition but it's not closed under
the operation of minus like
subtraction one minus two
[Music]
the answer cannot be found in natural
numbers
positive integers nope so we create
negative integers to do uh the closure
and follow the same thing we
create uh like rational numbers
real numbers and complex numbers
right because there is no
real numbers correspond to the quantity
here
so we create complex numbers and the
complex number is closed
under captioning not available
anyway
so
through the operations
we can expand our knowledge
regarding particular sets
and in this case we are talking about
regular languages
so first thing first thing here we want
to
prove that regular languages
a set of languages okay
and we call a set
of languages class
okay so class is nothing more
than set only that
this kind of set the member of
this kind of set is also set then we
call it
class that's it you can also think of
its
set okay anyway so we are
we now want to uh
discuss that whether the class of
regular languages
is closed under the union operations
okay if regular languages are closed
under the union operation
you see we can find any two regular
languages and create
new regular languages right because it's
closed
we don't need to worry about that
i use two regular languages and after
the union
the result is not regular okay
so we want to do the proof here
and this this would be the first proof
in our course it's very important
because
it's it's not complicated and it's
in informative and also
give us many things we will be used
we will be using later and how to
how do we do the proof
we want to construct a new automaton
simulating the two given automaton
okay so that's the idea
so let's go to
the proof of the text textbook
since there
we want to prove that two
two languages the union of two regular
languages
it's still a regular language and okay
here i forgot that don't
be confused that the three operations
here
they can be applied to any languages
okay not
really not regular languages they can
actually for union they can be applied
it can be applied to any
sets right and
so a and b here doesn't need to be
regular languages don't they they don't
be they don't need to be regular
languages
and for
theorem
1.25 what we want to prove is that
if you have two regular languages
after union the resultant language
is still regular that's what we want to
prove it doesn't mean that
union can be only used to handle
to process regular languages okay
okay so how do we how do we want to
prove that
it's weird okay
since we have two languages let's say
a1 and a2
and these two languages are regular
languages
by definition of regular language what
is that
that means a1 you can find
some automata
recognize a1 and
and remember that a1 in this case
a1 recognized only
sorry m1 only recognized a1
no other language only a1 but
on the other hand a1
can be recognized by
other machines other
final automata why because let's say
that's that's say m1 recognize a1
right m1 is the final automata right
so let's say the five components of
m1 are q1 sigma delta 1
q 1 5 f 1 here and imagine that
you add one more state
which is useless which will be not will
not be handled by
will will not be touched during the
operation
of the machine
you create and
other final automata
behave exactly like m1 but it's not n1
and that new automata recognize a1 2
right so m1 recognize only a1 but
a1 may have more than one automata
recognizing itself okay
then let's say m2 recognize
a2 and we have m2 here
okay and for convenience in this proof
we assume that the two language
the alphabet for the two languages
or the two uh final automata
are exactly the same so we don't handle
the different
alphabet here if you have to
if you have to explore
the possibility for this kind of thing
you can do that okay but it's very easy
you just need to uh do a new alphabet
which is this
which is a union of the two alphabet
and you you need to tweak the transition
functions
okay because delta 1 won't be able to
handle sigma 2
symbols in sigma 2 and the delta 2 won't
be able to handle
symbols in sigma 1.
that that would be a you know tedious
details
which is not helpful for understanding
the proof
so we
assume that the
alphabet is the same
okay okay
now we really want to
do the proof and how do we want to prove
a one union a2
this resultant flank uh
language is still regular how do we do
that
we do that by using the definition what
is the definition
we say that a language is regular
because some automata recognize it
right so now we want we what we want to
do
is to construct a new
final automaton based on
n1 and m2 okay
well in a way you can think of this kind
of thing
like uh you download some source code
from github
or bitpac bitbucket gillette and then
you merge some
source code you download it
together to create your own program
something like that okay so
now what we have we download m1 m1
is like this and also we download m2
and the m2 is like this now we want to
prove that
a1 and a the union of a1 and a2
is also regular we
construct a new machine which recognize
a1 the union of a1 and
a2 okay so that is
what we want to do here
since m we want to cons the machine we
want to the final time that we want to
construct
is
is also has also uh
is composed of five top five
component we just need to describe each
of them
and for alphabet we are
already described that we assume that
they are the same
if you don't want to do that as i said
you do this
and you need to tweak the transition
functions
okay and firstly uh
except for sigma here we want to this
we need to formally describe
for the the four other components in
detail
okay okay so how do we construct a new
final automata
m according to m1 and m2
okay let's consider this
if you have m1 here
if you have m1 here and the m2 here
right then
when something some string
you want to determine if the string
belongs to
a1 or a2
if you throw it into m1
it will process like this
right
perhaps like q1 q
3 q c 7
q 2 and something
and maybe accept
okay then you throw it into q2
m2 it will go
through the same length of the
computation process
right so what
our goal is try to
our goal is to try to merge
the two machines but not really merge we
want to create a new machine
and keep track of the response of the
two machine
at the same time imagine that
if the m can do what
the state of n the state of
n processing the same string
the state of m keep track
m1 state and the m2 state
then the state here
representing these combinations
well not combination it's actually
permutation but
well uh it's a tuple of m1 states and m2
states
okay so we want to do
what we want to do is like this
so we use one state of n to keep track
the composite state of m1
and m2 for example if you have
m1 like three states let's say
uh q1
and the q2 and the q3 three state
and m2 has two states
p1 and the p2 okay just for example
at any given moment how many pass the
possibility of
m1 and n2 you only have
6 right so
that would be q m1 is
on q1 and m2 on p1
m1 on q2 and m2 on p1
m1 on q3 and m2 on qp
p1 and the q1 p2
q2 p2 q
3 p 3 right
so it's all the possibilities there's
nothing more
so we only need n
to have six states
to trace all the possibilities
right then why is six because
three times two that's it
so firstly you need
the multiplication of the number of the
states of the two machines
and secondly you need a naming system
to name each state to name
each state correspond to
what combination of m1 and
m2 okay
and luckily we already have a set
operation called
cartesian product to provide
us the two functionalities
when we do a cartesian product of q1
and q2
we get the multiplication of the number
of states
and we also get something like
q1 from okay q1
and the q p1 from q2 and
imagine that on the machine of m1
each state is marked by
q1 and the another states
q2 and the nasdaq q3
right and also for m2 like p1 and p2
and we do a cartesian product here
and you can we can consider
this notation directly as
a label attached to the state
so for m we have a state
like this named as q1
comma q2 p1 okay
and a state named like this
a state name like this a state
named like this okay
so that's how we define it
we say that we define
we define the q here as the cartesian
product
of q1 and q2 and q
here will be like r1 and
r2 and r1 from q1 and r2 from
q 2. that's it as
the example i just give
okay so that's the q of m
then let's say
for transition functions
we just need to copy delta 1
and delta 2 into our m
exactly our m's delta okay
so for each c
we want to write this transition
function
and our transition function is a
function from
q m1 q times
sigma mapping 2q right
don't forget that and everyone here
you can know that r1
from q1 r2
from q2 right
when our transition function sees
a state of within q
with a symbol in a string
where is the destination state
in q we should go
we just need to look up
delta one and delta two so we feed
r1 and the same the same symbol
into delta one and don't forget that
for delta 1 delta 1
is a function making
q1 times sigma to
a state in q1 so the result
of this one is something
in q1 right the same
goes to delta 2. so
we feed r2 and also a to delta 2
we will get some states
in delta 2. now you can see that
a states in delta one and a states
in delta two the pair of these two state
is exactly a state
in queue right so we finished
the transition function here
see our program is composite
of others programs
and it is also the beauty of using
cartesian product to produce
the state of machine m okay
follow the same idea then we know that
which st which uh which state of
our m should become
uh set as star state it's easy
that would be the pair of the star
states
of m1 and m2
okay so
we need to have the describe the last
component which is the accept states
and we just need to describe describe
that
all states in queue
q is a cartesian product of q1
and q2 right
so all possible pairs are in q
and we just need to check for any pair
as long as
first one is in
[Music]
the accept state of m1
or second one
is in the accept state of q2
then we define these states
one of our accept states
okay so go back to what we have here
for example if the string
w fit into m1 and
n2 and m1
accept the string and to not accept the
string
for union we should accept the string
right if both of them accept the string
yeah we accept the string only no
no acceptance for the two machines
neither of them
accepts a string we don't accept a
string
right so we just need to define
the accept
accept states of n as
either one of them except the
string or you can
write the expression like
this one sorry
okay
then we have finished the proof here
see we define m1 as a final automaton
and this is describe the five components
the states of m1 is the collision
product of m1 and m2
and the alphabets we are we
assume that they are the same for
convenience
and without loss of generality
and for transition function we just
create a new transition function as
uh i should say uh look up
of the two transition function delta one
and delta two
and combine them as the result of
our transition function
okay so you know in a way you can think
of that you write the program here
and you get your input here
then you call others program and
combine the final result as your own
result
and that's it okay then the start
state is obviously
this state and the final
accept are that are those states
which contains one
at least one of the states of m1 or
m2 as their accept states
okay so
we finished the proof of union
but i have to give some notes here
first this
this proof is quite simple so
we don't or in the textbook
the authors don't provide the
correctness proof
to the construction of this machine okay
because the construction of this machine
is you know
quite intuitive so we i think most of us
can believe that
this machine really recognize a1
union with a2
but for some more complicated
operations we need to
prove the construction the machine
constructed
by the construction pro process
really can
do what you want it to do
okay we will see that kind of proof
later
but we don't have that here in a formal
way
we should have that here okay
because the proof of theorem in
mathematics
is in some absolute sense
you have to absolutely convince people
that
it is correct otherwise you cannot say
it is correct
that's the mathematical theorems
the second note here will be
that this proof
is easily extend
to intersection okay
intersection
how do we change the proof into proof
the cultural property of intersection of
two
regular languages we only need to change
this word to a
and d
okay so see
if both machines accept the same string
that string is in the intersection of
the two
regular languages
so we construct another
machine another final automaton to do
the job
okay so it's very easy and
when you change to end
that would be this
okay so you see this is
intersection
and this one is union
which is also over
okay so that's the second note and the
third note is
you see we proved that
the union of two regular languages is
regular is
a regular languages yeah so
the closure property goes to the union
of
two regular languages can it
extend to like union
another regular language and the union
another regular language
and union infinite regular language
for this proof the answer is no
why because you see
when we construct a new machine here
we do a cartesian product so the number
of the states will be the number
of the two
uh the multiplication of the two sets
so if you in a way
if you add more
machines you cannot
bunk the number
finite why do we need to do that
because the first definition of final
automatic is that
the states not the number of states is
finite
because q is a finite set of states
okay so we cannot extend this proof
to that kind of
to the union of infinite regular
languages
but we can do that
to
finite regular languages
sorry
because when you wait when we do this
the cartesian product of finite
finite finite numbers will be finite
so there's no problem here okay
okay so
we proved uh
the first regular operations
union so next time we want to prove
concluding okay