so now we are going to talk about the
time complexity relationship
for
the three models we have introduced in
uh chapter three to
you know to
investigate the difference
uh
raised by the variance of different
turing machine models
okay so the first one
oh okay the first two are determinatory
machines and the first one is our
fundamental
uh
type of tube machine which is a single
type two machine and the second one is a
multi-tab two machine
by multi-tab there are
uh k which is a finite number k test
then we are we will be talking about
non-deterministic emissions
uh okay and
for com computability they are all
equivalent
there is no problem with that okay for
computability from conversability they
are equivalent but for
time complexity they are not
why because they are different
you need
different steps
on
these machines to finish some job
by computability we we know that they
can
eventually ultimately ultimately to do
the same thing but
you need different amounts of resources
that's the uh difference here okay
so let's say
for theorem 7.8
we say that um
that t of n be a function
where
p of n is
equal to or larger
uh greater than n
every
t of n times
multi-tap dimension
has an equivalent
big o of t
squared
of n
times single capital machine okay
so firstly we need to
discuss a little bit about the
assumption here so we assume that
t of n
is
the complexity time complexity for a
multi-type dimension
and why do we need assumption
here that t of n is equal to or greater
than n well
basically
we
don't want to discuss trivial cases okay
or what is trivial cases and what is
this assumption uh
tells are telling us
since t of n
is the time complexity
or running time
and
you can always remember that there is a
interesting connection
between space
okay
tape space
here
space and time
which is the transition numbers
of
two machines
when you read
a symbol from
a type space
in one transition
you can move
to another space
of course you can also move left doesn't
really matter but when you want to
do
one
[Music]
tab space you need one transition steps
you see the connection here
one
tab space
one transition step
so
if you have
to
read
the whole
input string
at least
you need to go through
so many
transition
steps
okay again
space and time
has
a connection
by the operation of two machine
whenever
one symbol
of
on the tape
is red
you need one transition step to do that
so one step one space
on tape
so if your input string occupied
occupies
type spaces
then you need the machine need at least
and transition steps to
read the whole input string
so
we only care about
the languages
that
can be designed that can be decided
with reading the whole input
well that's not unreasonable right
because if a problem for you
to solve and you don't need to read the
whole problem the whole input
then that problem is kind of trivial or
you know um
probably meaningless or something
let's have another example if i give you
you know a midterm exam exam 1 or exam 2
and for some question on that exam you
don't need to read the question you can
answer that
then they'll be
not that would that would not definitely
not be a serious problem right because
you don't need them you don't need to
read the whole problem
so we discard those possibilities there
let's say
if a language defined as
one
and
anything
oh that's it
that's it so you only need to read one
accept it
not one
reject
then your
decider always need like one or two
steps that's a constant machine right
so we don't discuss that possibilities
that's uh
something too easy okay
so we focus on some we focus on
languages
that if you have a decider for that
language
in the worst case the decider always
need to read
the whole the whole input
for decision
otherwise
that would be
you know that the language is uh
basically trivial or meaningless and
then we don't need to we don't want to
talk about that
and actually uh
if you we really allowed t of n may be
less than n
there will be contradiction cases okay
so
here we are we make and we make a
reasonable resumption assumption that
you can
answer the question after you read whole
input
so that's why we have this part
okay
so let's uh describe the whole theorem
again so if there is a running time t of
n
d of n
larger to or greater
than or equal to n
then
every t of n time multi-tap to machine
has an equivalent
big o of t square of n
single time dimension
okay
so since it's equivalent that means
they finish the stand exactly same
computational job okay
so we just go back to
uh what is that theorem
3.13
so we use exactly the same
simulation turn machine and we
analyze how much time
that
simulation that machine needs to
accomplish the same task then we know
that the running time will be this way
okay
so uh this is the
figure from the
chapter 3 if you don't remember it we
actually prepare
we use the tape
one infinite tape to simulate k
internet tapes and k is a finite number
so there's no problem
and we have two versions for symbols on
each tape
so
the dotted version means that
the head is at that position
and the not started
version
means the head is not there
okay and we have separator for
tips
okay so that's it
and
we know that uh for the single tapping
machine to simulate a multi-tab two
machine what shield the single type two
machine tool
for every
transition made by the multi-tab two
machine the single tap to machine need
to scan across
the tape
okay scan across the tab
and collect that
the on the first tape one will be read
a will be red
b will be red
right
then it
implements
delta ends
for example it's on q
m
so q m and then read one a b
and check
where it goes
and
implements the
transition
on its own tape
so if u
r uh if m replaced
one as zero and the gold left
so it will make s will make
b symbol 0 and this symbol 0 dot
right
and then go
see the second one
how it will change be changed and the
third one and stuff like that
so
as the single tap two machine can
absolutely do the same test uh
computational job
with
well a lot of
a lot
more
steps
so analyze the steps described in
chapter 3 we have results like this
so
we know that
each active portions which
corresponds to the type of the multi-tab
2 machine
at the most
has length at most t of m
why
see
again
for tuning machine
for two machine
one tab space connects to one
transition step
don't ever forget that because that's
very important
then you see
t of n
is the running time of the multitapping
machine
what does that mean
that means
for a particular string n length of m
let's say
length of n is the input right
okay
we know that
t of n is the worst case
so the machine
at most
do t of n transition step
no problem there right
okay then since it goes at the most the
t over n transition step that means
initially
this tape is empty right for example you
have a four step
and initially it's empty
and for every step
executed by
the turing machine m here
the full step always write a symbol and
go right write a symbol and go right
right and similarly go right so
for this extreme example here
how long will this tab be written
apparently
at most
so many
spaces
right
so that's
in fact
an upper bound
of the length of the tape that will be
used during the computation
that is why we say that
the active portions
of the lens oh sorry
has length at the most t of n
because it is impossible for that tube
machine to go beyond t of n
steps because d of n is the worst case
okay as long as you understand this
point then there will be no problem
there because we have an upper bound t
of n
for
either the transition steps
or
the length of the working tape
okay
so
uses t of n tab cells in tl fn
steps that's what i just talked about
and you you won't be able to go beyond
that
so
how long
will be
our single tattoo machine
at the most at most you only need
k times t of n
tab cells
right
and don't forget that k is a constant
because
the machine here is you know k tips then
k is a constant and a finite number so k
will be
will disappear in bigger notation
okay anyway so
when again whenever
our single tab turing machine need to
scan
curls and reposition how many
how many steps will it need
like we go of let's write it first okay
k of t of n something like this
but k is a constant so we will have this
notation here
then you well
uh it will be easier to
read the this part of an analysis with
that that knowledge okay
so
scan the active portion of
the single tap tune machines tape we
need so many steps here
it is actually a lot but
many
factors are constant so they disappeared
from the big notation so we know
skin wants
you at most take so many steps for that
single type dimension
okay
then
we start to
in a way
you can think of that
to simulate one
m's step
simulator one
s need
so many steps
okay
so that
then that's pretty straightforward that
how
totally how many steps
s
need to simulate m to finish the whole
job
that would be
t of n times big of t of n
okay
so
again what is t of
what is big o of t of n
by definition there exists c and n0
and after n0
the real exact function you want to
describe
is equal to or less than c times in this
case t of n
right
and then you multiply t of n on both
sides
on both sides
you get this side become t square n
right
and then
you don't need to
find another c and n0 they
are still applicable
so the whole term the whole term here
can be described
by
big of t square of n
that's why so
so many steps
so using a single type 2 machine to
simulate the whole multi-type 2 machine
use
so many steps
okay
so initial stage the same thing so
that's why it goes to here
and assume that
t of n is larger than or
greater than or equal to n
this term dominates this term
okay
otherwise you will eliminate this one if
if
there is no such assumption and you
don't need the whole tab
then this one will be larger okay that's
that's not what we want we want to hand
deal with non-trivial languages okay
so we have this assumption that's why
this expression
can
derive
this
expression
okay so
we have that
again
that t of n be a function and we have
this assumption reading the whole input
and for every t of n time multi-tap
turning machine has an equivalent
square
to the machine
okay
but don't uh
well you need to correctly impl uh
interpret this theorem
this is
a default case or
a safe net
that means for every
t of n time
type to the machine
we know that
has an equivalent
square time transmission
uh single type division but
this one
might not be the best one
okay
so this theorem only tells tells you
there is
an equivalent
square time to a machine
but
this theorem doesn't tell you that
the square time tube machine is the best
one no
you can go back to see the
to see the example we just have
see
use a two type two machine m3
we know that the longing time
is big off and
right
in a way
m3 the running time of m3
is something like n
okay maybe some constant but something
like n
so by using
theorem 7.8
you will have an n square
two machine
okay
so
that this is as much as this theorem
tells us nothing more
okay this theorem doesn't tell you that
these
two machine is the best one no
so for this example we can better this
we can design a better tube machine m2
which is better than performed performs
better than n squared right which is n
log n
so
theorem 7.8
tells that
you can uh you can think of it this way
for the worst case
we have a squared
single type two machine that's the worst
case
but can you have a better one maybe
maybe not but this one
you always have
by hand okay
okay so that's the relationship
between a time complexity relationship
between single capturing machine and the
multi-type 2 machine
okay
then
we want to uh
check the non-deterministic machine
but for non-deterministic machine we
firstly need to
define a running time for the wrong uh
multi-tech uh sorry
non-deterministic machine
why remember that for determining
machine
the computational path is like you start
from the
starting configuration and finally you
get accept or reject
right
and in this case there's no
problem that
because the language is decidable the
machine always stops and there's no
problem with
the definition of the running time
and of course we said that for
particular length
we stay the running times the maximum
number of all possible to
all possible input strings right
but for the case of non-deterministic
machine
even for one
the same
input stream
you actually have many computational
branches like this
okay so
is
this one count as
computational steps or this one or this
one or this one or some other ones so we
need to define that
so
we
define
also the
worst case
okay
so you can we consider
the longest the computational path
so the worst case
so we define the running time for a
non-deterministic machine n
is also
a function from positive
financial number to natural number
and f of n is the maximum number of
steps
that n okay here
use this on any branches of its
computation
okay on any input of
length n
so for non-deterministic computation
we add
this part
to the definition
of course we can also use this
definition in determining machine
because there's there's only one branch
of computation okay so that's that also
applies to deterministic machine
okay
then after define this we now have a
clear understanding regarding
the
uh complete
time complexity or running time of
a non-deterministic machine
so then
theorem 7.11
that's t of n be a function
where t of n is equal to or greater than
n
every t of n time
non-determinative a single capital
machine
has an equivalent
q to the power of big o of t of n times
deterministic machine
and still remember that that's the worst
case at least that you can have a
deterministic machine act as this
but can you have better one maybe maybe
not but at least you have this one okay
don't
be confused with the
meaning of the theorem here
okay
then how do we
how do we
prove that
well the the proof is also go uh use the
simulation
provided in theorem 3.16
so the uh the textbook use the three
type two machine to simulate the
non-vitamin two machine
and calculate how many steps
needed by the single tattoo mesh
deterministic machine to simulate the
non-deterministic version
okay
but
it's kind of
easy to
really uh
to think about
what i uh
proposed to
simulate the
non-deterministic machine right so what
i said is that
you make the tape as a queue
and then
from this
from this configuration you know there
will be this configuration and this
configuration you push into the queue
then
like
this one and
then you pop
the left
congregation you know there are three
and you push into the queue then you
traverse this one
and you have these two
and then you suffering from it
so basically you can think of the whole
thing
is a b
f s
right it's a bread
a breast burst search
so
the whole simulation thing is a tree
surge so it depends on how many
nodes of the tree
okay
so
in this
way you can understand
the analysis
here
okay so
let's make a
upper bound estimation
we that b
is the maximum number
of the legal choices given by n's
transition function
that means
for some
transition there may be like uh three
choices and for some
transition that mean maybe two choices
and for some transition maybe
like
four choices
and assume that four
is the maximum number so we say that's b
here
we won't just want to estimate
the upper bound
of the three node number of the three
nodes
okay
so since b is the
let's say branching factor for you know
ai or
data structure chorus terms
the total number of leaves in the tree
is at most
b
to the
power of t of n
right that's pretty
straightforward because
in this case
the height is t of n right so how many
nodes in a tree
we actually we don't want to calculate
the same number but
b
to the power of t of n is no doubt the
upper bound
one over the upper bound for the number
of three nodes right
so as soon as we need another zoom we
actually need to go through every node
right
so
when we
the simulation like like i said the
simulation
explore in the tree
by using breakfast
search
process
okay so
how many uh
we can bounce the whole computation
and then
to try
to drop to from the
from the root note
to travel down
the whole thing
by
the single tattoo machine
we
need to take
a
big go of t of n
okay starting from a little note and
traveling down
is uh
for the for the uh
for level four uh sorry for the
virtual machine
so running time of d
of the
dimensional machine we need to simulate
n
is of course
big o of t
of n
times
so many nodes
right so many nodes
so finally
we change the base of the exponential
time
component we get this expression
okay
and
of course we don't
we actually don't need a
further
discussion if we
consider the breakfast search and
traversal the whole the whole tree
so we will have this one but
since the
proof of the textbook
the proof of the textbook
established and simulates the
non-deterministic
turing machine with a three
three tape two machine
so after
it's derived this
expression
it needs to consult back
to
uh okay now this one
to the
theorem seven point eight here
so there is a square here okay
so that's why
we need
this one
squared
okay
so since this one squared so the square
goes back to this one we got this one
and the two here is you know constant so
go back to the
expression so the same thing
so we know that
if uh for a non-deterministic machine
for non-deterministic machine
if you have a t of n-time
non-deterministic machine
in the worst case you will have a 2
to the big goal of t of n-time
deterministic deterministic machine
okay so that would be a
exponentially different
two machine
uh running time intermission and don't
forget that two here is not really two
it's a
we just we just want to emphasize that
this term goes to
exponential part
and 2 here is just a placeholder
there are some
number there
we don't care about which number it is
but we know there's a number there but
we have to have something there so we
write a 2 there okay the 2 there is not
really two it's just a placeholder for
some numbers
and anyway we know that the term here
will goes to
exponential part
remember
in the worst case
is it possible
we have a better better situation maybe
but
the worst case is like this
okay
then after the
uh
discussion on the time complexity
among different
variants of two machine
we basically know that
single type two machine and the
multi-temporary machine
we have at most remember that at the
most maybe better but at most
and most a polynomial difference why
because if you have t of n turing
machine
you will have a big o of t square and
tuned machine at most
maybe you have better one but at most
this one right that's the worst case
and for non-deterministic machine if you
have a t of non-deterministic machine
at most
it is an
exponential difference
and you will have
to
truly
be go of t of n
your machine here
okay
maybe you will have better one but
that's the worst case
so
goes let's go back to what we
uh to the to why we want to investigate
the relationship among different
variants of turing machine
because if you you use different type 2
machine and you get different
results different calculated result then
you you cannot compare them and
for example
someone says that
for length for language
a
it uh we can handle that by
like a linear time and someone say no
it's n log n
but they are using different type of
machines then it's really different
difficult to
unify unify all these possible results
that's very bad
for
uh theoretical development okay
so
in light of what we know here we know
that uh single type two machine material
type two machine at most polynomial
difference and the determination
non-deterministic machine at the most
exponential difference
and then
basically we consider
polynomial differences in running time
is you know small
in a way
where
exponential difference considered large
why why do we want to think though
because it's pretty easy
for
for us to see the uh the growth the
growth rate
for example let's say n cubic and the
two to the n
so you say okay uh let's say and cubic
for n equal to one that'll be one
and two right so
n
one and equal to two then you've got
eight
uh sorry a other
and
four
right
and equal to 3 that'll be what 27
pretty fast but
and you see
it seems slow but actually
let's say n equal to one thousand what
is that
it's pretty easy to write this right
that would be nine zero
what is nine zero
thousand million right
but
how large is this part
i i don't know i don't even want to
write it right because
that's we can calculate how many digits
remember that log
10 bit
base 10 right two what is the number
here
like
this one
and
one thousand so you got one thousand
and the plus one will be 302. what is
2 to the 1000 the
value the number here
has
digits
okay
that's why
we consider exponential differences
large
because the growth rate
of exponential function
is terribly high
where
we
can
tolerate
the growth rate for polynomials
okay so that's the key idea here and
then
we know that
all reasonable determining computational
models
well what does that mean
that means
basically we can implement
in the real world
okay
non-deterministic computation basically
um
well
in a way but not exactly but in a way
maybe content computation or
a lot of
traditional computers connected
with
very very fast
networking
may
uh
maybe
slightly close to
non-deterministic competition but still
not the same thing
okay
so
reasonable deterministic computational
models
are
practical and we found that they are
polynomially equivalent
by polynomial
polynomial equivalent equivalent that
means
if you have a model one
uh let's say model a single type two
machine and the model b multitap turing
machine
if you discuss the running time
with
these models
the result of the roaming time
will
differ at
at most
in polynomial
okay so they will have at the most
polynomial difference
so
how about
we ignore
the polynomial difference
by
well ignorance is what i use okay
let's say we consider
the polynomial difference
is the uh
or let's say we define a time complexity
class
including all polynomial difference
then the result
derived based on
the reasonable deterministic
computational models will be compatible
okay will be compatible you you
you will have the same result
okay let's see the definition and go
back to this question
so we let's uh based on the concept here
we define
a class
of languages
that
all languages
are decidable
in
polynomial time
on
deterministic
single tab
to the machine
okay
again
we
consider a class
include
all languages decidable in polynomial
time
by
determining single tap to emission
in other words with the notation we
already have we define the cost
as union of all
time complexity class of
n to the power of k and for all possible
k
okay see then we don't
we don't distinguish
now we don't distinguish time
like n log n
oh sorry
time
n
time and square
time
and
cubic and stuff
we don't distinguish these time
compensat time complexity cost
we union them all to be
p
okay
and
we discuss only
a language
in p or not
okay
why do we why do we want to do that
because
firstly
all reasonable deterministic
computational models are polynomially
equivalent
so
if we only discuss a language in p or
not
we will have the same results across all
reasonable deterministic computational
models right
so for the
uh examples we
have uh previously m1
m2 m2 m3 for a
uh
even if we use different models two type
two machine one type two machine
we get the same result one result a is
in p
right because use m1 or m2 that the same
model
we know that a is either n square or n
log n
in time complexity of n square or n log
n
or we use m3 which is a two type theory
machine
we get the result that a is in time of m
but if we
check
is a in p or not
they are in p
sorry the
both results tells us
a is in p
okay
that's why
we found that
reasonable deterministic
completion models are polynomial
equivalent and then we define a class p
to include
all languages decidable by deterministic
machine in polynomial time
then
this class is interestingly
that it is invariant for all polynomial
equivalent models
then we can you know bring our
discussion on this this model that model
or another model as long as they are
polynomial equivalent
the results we get are all compatible
actually are equip uh are identical
actually
if a language is empty or not
okay
so that's the first
first purpose
and the second purpose is that
for the
polynomially
growth the earning time growth growth
ratio
p
basically not not uh well it's still a
conceptual problem
p corresponds to
realistically
solvable problems
okay
so
for example if you have a problem
and
n is the input size right
if you have an algorithm which is
exponentially grow
then
maybe a very small problem can be solved
by that algorithm
for larger
you know even a little bit larger
problem
you will you won't be stopped that
uh well in your lifetime or in earth
lifetime stuff like that so we don't
consider exponential
algorithm
practical
but if it's a polynomial time problem
then maybe you can try it
so
again
in theory we think
p corresponds to realistically solvable
problem
but
you know it's a
it's a theoretical viewpoint don't get
confused by this
even in p there are many problems that
are not
practically solvable why because if
let's say n
1 median
well
it's not pretty good uh it's not
particularly solvable right
if you have n to like one thousand uh
you can you you will not be able to
solve such a problem
so
how do you interpret the theoretical
result
it's very important to
understand the
content of the chapter of chapter 7 in
this course okay
so we will have more
well cases to discuss
along the uh the the chapter but don't
forget that
all this
you need to correctly
get the
concept of
the theoretical viewpoint then you then
you can really
apply the thinking in your i don't know
daily job or
in your task
okay
you