let's get started with chapter 2
context-free languages in
chapter 1 regular languages we introduce
computational models like deterministic
final tampon
nfa and the regular expressions
and we use we use
chapter one mainly to introduce
the definition of computational models
and the use of computational models and
discussing the capability and the
limitation
of computation in a mathematical way
which is uh we
tried we we were trying to obtain
to obtain to explore to discover
knowledge via proof of
theorems and via discussion on closure
properties
of operations and in this chapter
we essentially we'll be doing
that all over again only that we will be
doing that
with a slightly more advanced
computational models okay so
let's get started with
the formal definition of context-free
grammars
first and remember that
in chapter one
we introduced regular expressions
i said that
we want to describe a language
in a more direct way so we
[Music]
design we designed regular expressions
to do that
in opposite of the machine way right
in the machine way actually our
definition of regular languages
we after we define
dfa and nadfa
in fact represents
a language which one the language
this machine recognized and this machine
recognizes
then that will be a that will be an
indirect way to describe or to indicate
to specify a language so
uh you can you can think of that
as uh there's a language there's a
language here
and using the machine is like you define
a dfa and the language of that dfa
is the language you want to specify
and you can also try to write a regular
expression
and the legal the regular expression
describe
the language you want to specify
something like that
and in chapter one we do this way first
right now we do this way first
okay so we want to
uh define something called contextual
grammars
and use grammars
to describe in this case
to generate a language in a more
direct way so a context with grammar
is a full tuple okay so there are four
components the first one is a finite set
the first one is a finite set we call
the variables that's why we use capital
v
here usually you can use other
name but we in history we use v here
and then the second one is also finite
set
it's actually a symbol set like
sigma in chapter one so we also use
sigma here
it is also the alphabet of the language
and sigma here must be
disjoint from v okay that that is
v intersect with
sigma must be empty set
the there cannot be a
same symbol in these two sets you will
see why
uh just a minute and we call sigma here
actually the alphabet here the terminals
and you will see the reason
a minute later so that's the two
major components okay the
fourth one is one
of the variables we call start variable
okay starbase so there is a particular
there is a spatial variable in v
like star state in the states okay so
there is a start variable in variable
set then in variables in a state of
variables
okay and the third one
here we use r is a finite
set of rules or
we call productions okay
rules or productions each rule
each rule is
a variable and
a string of variables and
terminals okay so it's a miss
it's a mixture of variables and
terminals
so each rule basically consists of
a variable in v which we call it
head and a symbol
let's say uh right arrow okay
and a string in
we use this one to
indicate a mixture of a mixture string
a mix a string of mixture or in
variable and also
terminals we call that the body
the robot so each rule
is head
body and the head
is something in v and the body
is some string in v
union with alphabet and
substring yes
so that's the definition of a
context free grammar
let's see uh let's see an example first
okay
so let's see this example
so context-free grammar g3
is a
for tuple right according to our specs
so v here only
has one variable and of course since you
have only one variable that variable
must be start variable
okay and then there the alphabet
has two symbols and the rule
has three rule first one is
let's call the symbol here
[Music]
i don't know it's informal uh
way to describe it i would like to say
s may become okay x
may become a s b
and the symbol here is or
okay or so actually
we write the rule set this way
means there are three rules so the first
one will be
s may become a as b
and the second one is s may become
ss and the third one is
s may become epsilon
which is empty string okay so you can
see that
each one is a mixture
is a string of the mixture of variables
and
terminals okay also alphabet
okay so here
uh you have to know that here
the symbol here means over and
it is not a part of a definition
of contextual grammar and
we write grammars this we write write
the rules of
grammar this way only for you know
convenience
so you should write grammar
this way it is the set
of the three rules and
also note that there since
r here is a set
of rules okay the set in the
mathematical sense
so that is a set what what do i
what what do i mean i mean since it is a
set
there is no odor okay
there no order here
for writing rules we must have some you
know
writing orders so we write the
rule first here the second rule here
the third row here but
from the viewpoint of set there is no
order
so you you cannot think of like
first first rule has higher
priority to be applied and second rule
has the second
highest priority to be applied no
there is no such such thing okay
there are three rules these are the
three rules
and there is no higher priority or lower
priority here
in the sense of mathematical set
okay you must be noted that
so there are three three rules here
then it is a grammar
the whole thing here is an example of
grammar
okay for components
variable terminals rule set
and which variable is the stuff is the
start variable
okay so that's an example of the grammar
of the contextual context free grammar
we are talking about
so
since a context with grammar
is as i said used to describe
or to generate in this chapter to
generate
a language how does the
generate thing go okay
so let's say
since a rule look a rule looks like
this form okay
we say that
uav some
string sound string of a mixture
the mixture of variables and
terminals some string yields
another string
we re we write this way
u a v
derives
oh sorry yields u
w v okay
so this string yields this
string
and if some string
if some string yields
some other string and
then use some other string
then etc finally yields
this string b we say that
u derives
v okay
and we write the derivation
as u derives
v and you can see star here
means the steps
the number of steps is 0 1 or more
okay so
u yields u1
u1 yields u2
and go on finally v we say that
u derives v
okay and apparently you can say that
u derives u
well see zero steps
give you the same thing it's itself
something like that
so based on this let's see the example
here
so we can say that
that's the arbitrarily ss
right because you have a rule as may
become
ss then let's say
s and second as that
that's used this row
a s b right
and of course you can say that okay the
let's use the second s do the
second rule again so s u
e l s a s b
yields s a
s s right
so you can do that arbitrarily you can
generate some string
so let's say that that make the first
s a s b so
a s s b right then
okay then
let's make the first a the first
s epsilon so you get
a b a s s b
okay so that's we can
actually do anything like this so let's
say
a b a we do uh
a s b again so
s b okay so this has become asb
then let's make uh all the s
epsilon so this string yields
a b a a s
b b okay so let's do the as
this as first then the second s
a b a a b
b okay then finally we get some
uh string of terminals only with
terminals okay
and in the process you can easily
observe that
you have many many many possibilities
sometimes you can do this as well with
applying some rules one of the three
arbitrarily so there are many
possibilities
okay then
we define that the language
the language of a grammar
so you define a conditional grammar and
like i said we we are we will be using
context-free grammar to
specify to generate language and what
language
does this context-free grammar generate
the language of the contextual grammar
is
from the start variable
via sum derivation
process all the string
derived from
the start variable okay all the terminal
strings
sorry terminal strings derived
from the start variable is
the member of the language
of the grammar and the language of the
grammar
is all possible
terminal strings derived
from derived according to the rules
described in the grammar from
and from the start variable
okay so that's the definition
of the language generated
by a context programmer
okay so let's go
to the example again so you can see that
what are the strings in describe
what are the strings in the language
described by
the grammar g3 so that we can see some
examples here
so you can see s may become
epsilon so we can derive from
s to epsilon so you know that
epsilon is one string
in g3 right
and let's do that like s can
do a s b
and then s become epsilon you get a b
right so a b and you can also
see that s can become a asb
and do that again you get a
a s b b then
has become uh epsilon
then the string yields a a
b b so a a
b b and apparently you know that
you can repeat that uh steps
in definite indefinite times so
sorry again a a a b
b b right
and etcetera here you already know
well if you can connect with the
thing we discuss in regular language see
if we don't have rule we don't have this
rule if we don't have this rule
the two rule the two rules here
already can generate
what a language
already can generate a language
this one right
because you replace a and b
with 1 and 0 you get that language
and we already proved that that language
is not regular language
right interesting but it's informal
let's uh
do that later okay
the language of grammar g3
has more right not only that
but has more so let's say
we do second rule first
and you can see that we
do the first s asp
and then first as epsilon
right and then do s b again
and then epsilon again you get a b a b
right
so when you has
this rule you can duplicate
two sets of the same thing
the same strings so you can
get a b
[Music]
a b right and you can also get
a b a b a b
why because you can do ss again so
like
ss right and the first s do
ss again you get 3s
right so you can easily get this one
and also every s
here can repeatedly doing
this part so you can get it
very very complicated like a
a b b a b or
a b
a a b b or a b
b a abb abb stuff like that
right and apparently you can
observe it and know that
since you get empty string
so s can disappear and you get
whenever you generate terminals
you can only generate terminals
via the first rule here that is
when a
appears there is a paired b
appears right so if you consider
a as the left parenthesis
and the b is the right parenthesis
you will the language of grammar 3 can
generate
all strings all strings
with proper nested parentheses
of proper nested parentheses
right so everything like this one
or this one or
this one or this one can be generated
okay so that's uh
that's an example of context free
grammar
and why are we talking about
contextual grammar or
what's the usage of contextual grammar
well grammar is not directly from
computational
theory or complexity it's actually from
linguistics
okay because we want to
or the scholars you know
those uh scholars want to understand
the structure of a language mainly the
natural languages
not computer programming language at
first they want to understand like
chinese english
or french or other languages
if there is any let's say structures
or any
systematic way to understand
a language they propose
a concept the concept of grammars
and from grammars if you
the grammar of natural languages are
well analyzed from existing you know
words sentences
after that we define all sorts of
grammars like
the contextual grammar here we are
introducing
uh the we are introducing context free
grammar here
and we use context grammar to
understand a sentence which is a string
in this case what does that mean for
example
let's go back to discuss something like
programming language
okay so for example if we have a grammar
g5 here then
of course you need to do the uh proper
formal definition way
for g5 that would be uh
you have a variable
first right you have a variable e x
p r you can do that as
variable right one variable not not z
x pr and two angle six
symbol no expr is one variable
all right then
let's say the terminals in this case
will be
plus times
parenthesis and a so
let's say plus times
parenthesis a
that's the symbol okay then we have
uh one two three four
four rules like here
so i don't want to write that you know
therefore there are four
rules so let's say it's our rules
or productions then since we have only
one
variable that variable is the start
variable here
let's get a very limited small
uh example of context grammar for
programming language
here okay so when we have this
this grammar g5 you can think of
we can use this grammar to write valid
programs what is valid program what is
uh
synthetically correct programs that is
when you write a program you go through
compiler
you don't have synthetical errors
okay you may have semantics warnings or
something but
you don't get arrows because
you are you will be synthetically
correct
and by synthetically correct
the compiler can understand basically
understand what your program
wants to do okay so for this example
according to this grammar according to
this grammar
you write a plus a times a
something like this okay so think of
a plus a times a is your
source code and how compiler
understands this line
it use the grammar
it tries to start from the
stars variable and use the derivation
and to construct the
derivation to
the program you wrote okay so for this
example
the compiler may understand a plus a
times a as c
start from the start variable here
and it applies rule2
first so it gets
expression times expression
right then compiler applies probably
this one so it becomes a that would be
the fourth rule
so you get a then
so let's say uh first first step
second step third step
and probably applies not probably must
apply
the first rule right then
you have expression plus expression
then let's say fourth step
fourth rule derive this one and oh five
step
the right this one four rule four rule
number four
okay that's one way uh to
understand the source code a plus a
times a
okay then okay firstly we call the
structure generate with the derivation
past three okay past three
so the past result is like what we have
now
on the left but
in a way you know that there is a
and there is another way to
derive and obtain exactly the same
exactly the same
uh terminal strings which is your source
code right
so you may first one
first step you have uh
first rule so you get one
expression plus expression and then the
second step
for example we do this one first
and then you get you apply fourth rule
you get a and then
third step you do the second
rule you'll get expression times the
expression
let's say so uh four step
you get a and the five
step you get a
okay but
uh then go back to what i said
compiler use or we use
grammar to derive the target string
and in order to understand what
target stem means the meaning
is represented by
past three okay so in this case you can
see we have
two totally different parts three and
what's wrong with this
the problem is since past three is the
meaning of the
sentence the string so in the left
in the left part your program will do
a plus a first
then do times a
next and on the right
your program will do a times a first
then do plus a
okay of course we artificially
impose the order of operators
so usual uh not usually in mathematics
we do
multi uh multiplication and the division
division okay anyway before
plus and minus before addition and
subtraction
right so we have well the order is
artificial but we have that
in mathematics so basically when you
write
a plus a times a you
really want should be
time a times a then pass a right
uh yeah so the right
path tree is what you want
for the program you wrote basically
usually
right and
you can find that so what if
let's say compiler misunderstand your
program
then that will be a disaster right when
you do the programming
class the homework assignment in a
programming
class in a programming course then you
always
get wrong results why because compiler
misunderstands you that's bad right
and what's the problem of this case
the exact case here is that
we have to pause tree for the same
terminal string
then you don't know which parser will be
chosen
as the understanding of your source code
by the compiler
okay so that
is a problem of
ambiguity here okay
and ambiguity not only
exists in programming languages or
context-free languages actually we have
a lot
many of them in natural languages okay
so here is some example
here so i saw the man
with the binoculars
and how it is ambiguous and ambiguous
because you saw them
you you saw the man you saw
the man with the binoculars or
you saw the man
with binoculars okay
so the ambiguity we discussed here
is caused by the structure of the
sentence
not the meaning of words
many ambiguity many interesting
ambiguity many ambiguity
you know funny in languages is not
the structural it's not unstructured
it's our meaning
so you may have a different meaning for
the same word
and it is interesting to mix them
but not structured and here we talk
about structures
okay structures so it is a an example
another example like look at that dog
with one eye
so it's dog with one eye
or you look at that dog with
one of your eye okay
that's the structural problem that's the
word all meaning
the word of meaning is the same
okay so the final
example in english is stolen painting
funk by tree
it's very interesting because uh i
i didn't find i tried i tried but i
didn't find the source
of the newspaper but rumor says that
this is this was a
an actual newspaper headline probably 97
or 92
i don't know or even 87.
so stolen painting
found by tree so there's a tree
with intelligence finding a painting or
stolen painting font
by the tree okay
beside the tree so that will be a
structural issue here so in natural
language we have
also the structural ambiguity here
and also since we have a most of
most of students in this class is a
chinese mandarin speaking including
myself so this is an example
so in this sense in this sentence
i guess some of you may think
you should wear as much as
possible with many as many curls as
possible
or the other part of the student may
think
you should wear as
few clothes as possible right
it is very interesting depending how
your brain
understand the structure of the sentence
if you think this one
is an adv to
modify that one you will think you
should
wear as less as
possible if you think
this is a
unit to describe many
you will think the sentence tells you
you should you should wear as many
clothes as possible
okay it's very interesting for the
structural
uh ambiguity and another
sentence is like this well most of you
may think
uh i think something bad actually
but this sentence is not about that at
all
in the first place what is that i have a
i have a friend he uh she said that
she when she was a girl she went to
disney
and see all the princes and the
characters in cartoon they treat her
like a princess
okay so being
treated as
the real princess feels good
okay but most most of you probably
understand this sentence as here
right so it's not a happy feeling but
you know it's ambiguity actually
so the final example is also interesting
so it's a hand dryer but
you may
understand this sentence as the
structure here that would be
mobile phone okay
so it's very difficult to write here
mobile phone so everybody try to dry
their mobile phone
although it should be hand dryer
or not washer sorry and dryer
here right so all these examples are
ambiguity in sentence structure and i
i have to say that uh
not many examples here not many examples
can be found for structural ambiguity
usually in natural language the
ambiguity rises with the
thematics and the meanings not structure
okay so these are
great interesting some examples
and let's go back here so
we need to handle the uh
link uh issues with ambiguity
but that's not that is not the job
uh for this course okay we are we need
in this course we just want to introduce
there is a sub there is such an issue
and
we study it a little bit okay
so what in the
in essence what is ambiguity ambiguity
basically
are
multiple parse trees more than one parse
trees
for some string
for the identical string you have one
you have two or more
parse trees then you don't know which
one is what you want
and what what uh
what what's the relation between the
derivation
and the parse trees is the
order of rules application
well you can see that for the
left part you can see
the application of the application of
the fourth rule here
right you can actually move this one
down
without changing the result right or
we move this one up here up to here
without changing the result
so the order of rule application
cannot be the
deciding factor and then
we found that if
we derive a string
if we derive a string always
from the
left most remaining variable
then we call such derivation left
most derivation okay and why
why do we want to define this term
because
left most derivation
corresponds to unique past tree
okay so go back to this slide
you can see that if you always
resolve the leftmost
variable for this example we result
first one only one right so that's the
leftmost one
you you you use row two
and then this one you must use rule
one and then this one
four four
and four
and it's the same thing with uh the
right side right hand side of this
so one
four this one
two is one four
four the last one right so left
most derivation corresponds to
a unique posture here
in this sense we can know that
if
there is a string if there is a string
in the grammar in the language of the
grammar
has two or more different
left-most derivations
according to that grammar that string
has two or more parse trees
then we call the string is derived
and ambiguously because
it is possible this derivation or
that derivation or more actually
and if there is a string in the language
of that grammar
is this case we call that grammar g
is ambiguous okay
so if you write a grammar
then the grammar represents a language
right
if in that language there is
one string as long as one string
it can be derived ambiguously
we call that grammar ambiguous
grammar okay so
let's say you have a context free
grammar g
and in the grammar there is a string
and the string has two or more
different leftmost duration that means
there are more
more than one pass threes
we call such a grammar ambiguous
okay and the interesting thing is
it is possible to write
an other grammar
describing the same language
that other grammar is not ambiguous
it is possible okay it is possible
but you know there is no systematic way
to do that
so we don't go into that iteration
so continue with our discussion
some for some language like this one
you may have an ambiguous grammar and
have unambiguous grammar that's possible
but it is possible
that it it is also possible that
there are some context-free language you
know described by context-free grammar
no matter how for the language here
it can be described by context-free
grammar right
like this one and also you can write a
lot of possible context-free grammar
to describe the same language let's say
the same language it is possible that
all the grammar you can write to
describe
that language is
each grammar you can write to describe
that language
is ambiguous grammar okay
it is possible so we call that
language that's language inherently
ambiguous
okay and we give an example here
so this language is a complex language
but
it is an inherently ambiguous language
that means any context free grammar
describing this language have to be
ambiguous okay so we got
we defined ambiguous grammar in
currently ambiguous
language okay
and we will formally prove
this language to be inherently ambiguous
in our course later
okay
you