according to my here on the row theorem
we know that
if language l
is recognized by a dfa with
k states
the language l has index
at most
the key word a key word is at most here
k
and if you know that exactly
the index of l is k a finite number k
you know that
the language is recognized by a dfa with
k states
okay
so by
considering these two
results we know that
we know that
the the index of the language
the index of the language
is
exactly the size
of the smallest dfa
recognizing it
okay
because somehow you got the dfa
then
the dfa has like uh 100 states then you
know that
that language recognized by this dfa has
indexed at most 100 it may be less but
at most 100.
if you already know
there is a language
has an index of like 50
then
then you know that
the smallest
as as in
fewest states
dfa recognizing that language
will be
states
okay
so
well firstly what is the situation of
more states
well it's like that for all strings
for example
all possible strings there is a maybe a
language classify all strings into like
let's say
five classes
five groups
then
for the corresponding dfa
maybe you have some
you know
equivalent states
then
after processing strings
let's say
dfa stops at
state 1
state 2
step 3
maybe
stop at state
and 5.
and the stop at
7 and 6.
it is possible
because
for the language
as the equivalency relation it can only
classify
all possible strings
into five classes but
in your dfa you may have more states
then
those those states
may be subclasses of
the class classified by the language
that is why if you find a dfa
recognizing in
a language l with k states
the index of the
language at the most is
at most k
so
here we want to
find out the equivalence
equivalent states
okay
so what is equivalent states don't
forget that when you see equivalent you
need firstly you need to check
what is the criteria judging the
equivalence okay
now we are talking about states of dfas
so we define that state p
and the state q
are said to be equivalent
if
for all strings
for all possible strings
you see start from p
and start from q
for the same string
they both goes to
[Music]
accept state or
another accept states
okay if and only if
so
if
start from p
processing string q
goes in
some
accept states
and
start from q
processing w also goes to accept
accept states or
they both goes to some non-accept states
if it's always so for all
possible strings
then we say that
the two states in that dfa are
equivalent
otherwise they are distinguishable
okay
and why we
why we define equivalence this way
equivalence of states this way
it's straightforward that because for
dfa processing strings
we only care about whether or not
after processing that string the machine
stop
on
some accept states or
not accept states right
so
on accept states stop and accept states
or stop at not
accept states
is our result
so we if
from start from p
and start from q
always
get the same result then they are
equivalent
right
so that's why the definition is written
in this way
so
for equivalent we need to check all
possible
strings
and if they
start from the two states always gate we
can always get the same results then we
say they are equivalent
on the other hand
we can try to do
finding distinguishable states
right
if we found some string to separate two
states then they are distinguishable
after we process all possible situations
then
those
states
are not distinguishable they are
equivalent
so
we are
will be using a table filling algorithm
that's
given a dfa let's say a here
we use the following hydrogen to find
all distinguishable pairs in the dfa
okay
all the distinguishable pairs
firstly
if
any pairs
with one in the accept states and the
other
not in the accept states
such a pair
we know
in the beginning initially
is distinguishable
right
you can
consider that we use an empty string
here
to do the examination to do the check
start from for example if p
is in f
and the q is not enough
so processing
empty string
what you get
you get p here right which is in f
and you get q here which is not in f
so they are distinguishable
so
initially we know that
any pair between
accept states and not accept states
are distinguishable any pairs
okay
then think about that
if you already know that
a pair
of states
rs
is distinguishable you already know the
pair this pair is indistinguishable
and you go back
you go back
one symbol let's say
from p
process
a goes to r
from q process a the same symbol goes to
s
and
assuming that you already know r
s
is distinguishable
then
we know pq
is distinguishable
right
why because
the same reason here
start from p
you process a
you go to r
and start from q if you process a you go
to s
and since rs is distinguishable you know
that eventually processes some same
stream
you will get the results one of the
results here in f the other is not
right
so
we know that pq
is indistinguishable
okay
so that's what we have
on this one
so we know that pq
is distinguishable if you already know
rs is distinguishable if because
for this
result and this result one of them
will get you
and accept states and the other of them
will not
okay
then
if we if we try to do
finding distinguishable pairs of
states of a dfa
it is possible
that we can find some equivalent state
of some dfa of the given dfa then
we can
reduce the number of states of that dfa
that's why we called this process
minimizing
a dfa
and you actually can find the
this detailed algorithm on our textbook
as
a problem
on page
324 to 325
the
740 here is for the uh second version
second edition sorry second edition of
the textbook and the number here is for
third edition okay
so no matter which edition you are using
it contains all the materials we will
cover uh this semester
okay
so
that's uh
do an example
as the
how the
minimizing
process go
so given the dfa here
given a dfa here
you can see that
let me
okay uh for the
example dfa we have eight stated here
and uh only one accepted and the other
seven are not accepted
okay so c is the only accept states
of the dfa
and according to the table of building
algorithm we need to construct our bases
the basis is that initially we know that
the pairs are distinguishable and for
this example we know that
uh
well c a c b c d c e c f c g
c h the seventh pair here
are distinguishable so
let's
mark them
here
they are
initially
distinguishable
pairs of states
okay
then we try to use the uh
algorithm to find
all other
pairs distinguishable pairs
so uh imagine that the process is like
you have
let's say cue
to help the whole process and whenever
you find a new
pair a new distinguishable pair you
append to the end of the queue and then
you pop one in front of the queue
to process
okay to process that pair
so in this case initially we have the
seven pair here so we
push
ca into the queue cb into a queue etc
then we start to do the iteration
then firstly we pop one pair one
known distinguishable pair out of the
queue
so we got ca
right
so now we are processing c
a
okay so when process is ca what we want
to do is that we check
we check
which state
the
symbol 0 goes to c and which states goes
to a
okay so via symbol 0 that would be
goes to c that'll be d and f right
symbol zero here
and we know that
d
and f for c
and for a that'll be
c
right c
so
three uh sorry two pairs here now b
dc
standard cd
and
fc
they are not new pairs because they are
already waiting in the queue
right
so waiting here
and
here they are waiting
then
it it's for symbol zero then for symbol
one what what is that for symbol one
for c that will be b
c
h
right
but for a nothing
so since nothing here there's no pair
here
okay we already processed
ca the first pair and
no new
information found
then
we processed ca here
c
b
right
okay the same thing
uh check symbol zero so for c that'll be
d
f
for b
for b that will be
a
right
because you see
from a
symbol zero to b so
a will go to b be a symbol zero
so there will be d a
and
f a
or
adaf okay that's the same
so
we know that
a d and
af
okay
then symbol one
for c
that would be b
c h
for b
no
so no pair
see so in this round we got two new
distinguishable distinguishable pairs
adaf
okay
then
cb is processed so let's record it
cb is processed
and
we got
the
and
adf 9 here
okay
so next
we
pop out
cd
right
c
d
and same thing 0 so for c
that will be d f
for d
no
so no pair
and symbol one
there will be states b c h
for d
no so no
then
cd is processed
and no new information generated okay
so
here
then
next one ce
c
e
right
so symbol zero symbol one
d f
no
so no
right
and the symbol one
b
c
h
and for e
there's a g here
right there's a g here
so we got
bg
three pairs okay c g
and h
g
three pairs
but we know that c g
is waiting in the queue
right here so it's not a new information
we got two new new pairs the first one
is bg
bg where's bg here
that'll be 10
and hg
right hg
that'll be
here 11
okay
so
then
the pair ce is processed
so we
mark that this is proposed processed
we got
here
and here
okay
then next one
we pop we pop
cf
from the queue
cf from the cube and the check symbol
zero
when check symbol zero
for c
d f will go to c beer 0 and the 4 f
nothing
so no pair here
for symbol 1
b
c edge
for symbol one a
e
right so there will be six pair out of
the situation here
so there will be a b
oh let's say ba then b e
then
c a
c e
then h a
then h
e
and
after checking you know that ca
is the first pair we processed so no new
information
ce
already processed just processed so no
information measure here
so there are four new
here here
that will be
what a b
is one
and
b e
this one
and h a
where is this here h a
and then
h e
for new pairs
okay so let's mark it and finish the
pair
cf
so
cf is finished
and we got
okay
thirteen
[Music]
fourteen
right
okay
then
we pop
cg
the plcg
and
check
symbol 0 and 1
for symbol
that's d
f
for g
that'll be b
g
h
then there will be a lot right so
d b
[Music]
d g
d
h
and then
f b
f g
f h
and you know that the sixth pair here
are all new
right i think it's all new yeah
so
db
will be
here
okay so let's just put it
because they are
too much here so
db here 16
right
then
d g here
d
g
here
[Music]
and d h
and
fb
and the fg
20 here
then fh
[Music]
then cg is processed
okay that's seven
oh wait uh we still have symbol one
then
for symbol one
c will be
b
c
h
g
will be
d f okay still sixth pair
h f right
by the b d already here because
we got here right
bf we got previously
and the cd already processed cf already
processed
and
uh okay
hd
we just got it and hf we already got it
so there's no new here
okay
then let's save it okay
so
the final pair for the first round
we have ch
right ch
that's the final pair
for our initial pairs here
for ch
symbol 0
df
right
and the symbol 0 for edge is e
so
we got d e
and
fe
okay
so d e
that will be
[Music]
22 here right
then for
fe
i'll be
23 here
then symbol 1 bch
b
c h
and uh
here is nothing so no pairs
okay so then we processed uh the initial
seven pairs and find out others
and push into the queue so now we have
uh pair
a
10 11 through
okay
after processing all the initial
seven pairs
we
obtain
what
more than
[Music]
10 actually close to
15 i guess
new distinguishable pairs
then
we need to still process
all these pairs one by one
until our queue
becomes empty
okay so we need to process all
pairs
until the queue is empty
so
of course that state
now we process the number
eight
okay
number eight here that will be a d
right
so process a d
you will find that
a d here
and the symbol 0 symbol 1.
for symbol 0 a
c
goes to a via 0 and for d there will be
no pair
so nothing here
okay
and for
symbol one
nothing for a so no pair okay so 80
processed
okay ad
then
for
af
for f
let's go this way
af symbol 0
c
right and for f symbol zero
nothing
so no pair
no pair and symbol one
a
no pair
nothing
and so
no pair so nine processed
then we pop 10 right pop 10.
for 10 here that would be bg
and
we know that for symbol 0
for symbol 0
b will be a
and for
uh g symbol zero
will be b
g
h
then we will get three pairs right a b
a g
and a
h
okay so
a b is uh 12 right the the 12 12 pair so
not new
information waiting in a queue and a g
yes c a g is a
is a new pair so that'll be 23
should be correct right 23 here
and then
it's new ah edge is 14 waiting for
processing so
new
information and symbol one
so symbol one for b is empty so no pair
then we processed the tenth
here
okay
then
the eleventh
pair popped
that will be
gh
oh or hg right g h
then symbol 0
for symbol
0 g
[Music]
is b g h
and
for h that'll be e
o okay so you see
b e
g e
h e
okay
so what is b e
be is uh 13
pair 13
so
waiting in the queue
and ge
is actually new so
all right 24
then
h e
h e is
uh
15 so 15
not the new information within the queue
and symbols are simple one for symbol
one g
is
a single one
df
for h symbol one known
so no pair generated okay
so
we now processed 11
pairs
okay
and frankly we need to process you see
13 14
and go on
and until 23
24th
that is
on the table here we discovered all
distinguishable pairs
okay
so
of course i already did everything so we
i know that there will be no new
information
in a later stage but you can do that as
a practice
and
it need
need you need to pay attention to
details otherwise you may
miss something okay you may repeat the
whole
process uh from start okay just
for a practice
so
finally we get
it doesn't really matter about the uh
odors or all the marks we did here
it only matters when
we find
you know those x marks in the
in the table as shown here
okay
so
now we know that
all the
uh
all the distinguished
distinguishable pairs of the dfa has
been found
that is for example
hg
for example hg here
and the edge here
etc they are distinguishable pairs
so
what we
need to
look at is
any unmarked
pairs
so for example
this is unmarked this space is a marks
and this one
they are what they are a e
they are bh
and
df okay three pairs
so that means
ae
in this dfa ae
bh and df are
equivalent state pairs
okay
so
by definition
we can actually
merge
a e
b h
and
df
okay
we can do that
and remember that
when after you find
the equivalent
state pairs
and
if you decide to merge
if you decide to merge the equivalent
states you have to
merge
all these pairs
at once
in a single stage you cannot say that
okay i merge ae first and and i don't
want to
merge b
h and df that doesn't work why because
you see
if you only want to merge ae in this
case
in this
case for zero
okay for zero
you want to merge a e for in this case
for zero
a goes to b
right symbol zero a goes to b
and for symbol zero e goes to h
right
then you don't know
uh if you only want to merge a e without
merging bh
and df
then it creates
a problem for dfa that
after merge let's say this is one state
called a e
and when c in symbol 0 where do you want
to go
since you don't want to merge b and h
then for symbol 0 you don't know
you need to go b or
go edge you can only go one way right
that's the way of dfa
that's why it doesn't work that if you
don't you only want to merge partial
uh
equivalent states pairs
you either
merge then
o
otherwise you don't merge any of them
okay so that's the issue here
if you merge
each pair of equivalent states then
there's no problem why
because you can see that
if you merge a
also bh also df
then
for
ae
and the symbol zero
it goes to one state which is bh
right that's one state because you need
to merge b and h
and
that will be
so let's see uh what
happened if we
merge all the
equivalent states we have found okay
so that'll be the next page like this
so you will see that there will be no
problem here
that
you have
one state for a and e one state for d
and f and one state for b edge
so uh in this case we
[Music]
well
merged three pairs so
eight
state
become
five
state
okay so that'll be the minimization of
dfa
and you can find
uh you can find the detailed
algorithm
on third edition
textbook third edition
page
three two four two three 2 5 which is
problem
7 25 problem 721 okay
so that's it for uh chapter one regular
languages
you