okay
last time we
proved that the union of two regular
languages
is still regular so
that's the closure property of the
union operations
union operation on regular languages
then
we
want to prove concluding now the closure
property of conconnation not
available any languages
when you do conclination that would be a
cartesian product
so
that would be cartesian product like
this and this
but
for the concatenation for languages we
don't do the notation here we just
concatenate the two strings
so for example if you have
a language one zero zero
and the other languages that say are
one
then the two languages will be in
cartesian product that we usually use
the notation that's one one right
then zero zero one
but for
here we write
one one a string and zero zero one the
other string so that's it
so that's concatenation
okay
now we want to prove
the class of regular languages is closed
under the combination
operation
well
can we use the same idea
when we prove the closure property of
the union operation
and here
that's
that's one way
i'm not sure if that works but
apparently in history no one ever
succeeded to do that
why why it is difficult because you see
in the proof of union operation we try
to trace
two
machines together
we use a
combination of states
to trace
two or finite
machines
at the same time
but
for concatenations
you actually need to
break the string
and check the first part and the second
part right for example if you have two
languages like a
let's say 0 1 and 1
and b
let's say
0 0 0 and
1 0.
so the combination of a and b will be
0 1 0 0 0
0 1
1 0
and
one zero zero zero and one one zero the
four strings here right
okay so
when you have
let's say
one
zero
how do you know it's one and one zero
one in a
and is one 0 in b
how do you know that it
it's 1 and 0 1 0
is not
1 1
0 is not in b and
one one
is not in a
right how well to where to break the
string you don't know that you can you
can just try one because for this
example
if you try
1 1
0 and another accepted by the machine
for b
and
not accept by the machine for a you
cannot go back because it's not in the
specification of final automata
final automata is that you give it a
string and
it process step by step by step by step
and stop
and you see the answer
accept or not
okay
so it's probably
probably impossible
to use the same concept
when we uh
prove the
union of
two regular languages
so
what do we what do we do now
okay
okay uh
interestingly that's uh set aside the
whole thing here
let's introduce another type of machine
okay
kind of weird but that's that's just do
it so we want to uh introduce another
type machine called
which is called
non-deterministic finite automata
okay non-deterministic finite automata
so
for non-deterministic
the previously previous
final automata
the let's say fundamental financial we
defined in our last class last two class
it's called it is called can be called
deterministic uh finite automata
okay so now we want to define
non-deterministic final automata
okay what is deterministic computation
what is deterministic final automata
it's quite simple actually it's
our you know
our usually day life is more like this
we have
determined next move
okay
well
for some people maybe it's not true but
for
programs or for your computers at your
hand like
your
your cellular form your notebook
all computing machine right now is
uh except for those you know content
computation
all the traditional computation machine
right now is
deterministic computation which has
determined next move
for our uh final automata you see if you
fro
you are from
p1 the state p1 and you see the
symbol a
you go to state
p
and you have a transition like this
p1 a
sorry
a
and
p4
so that's deterministic
you know exactly
your next step
think about that if you are writing a
program and the computer doesn't give
you what you expect
unless you have a bug in your pro in
your program if you don't have a bug in
your program computer response responds
differently than you expect that would
be very bad right
so
that's deterministic computation
on the contrary
the computation what is that
in our textbook i
in our textbook
the sentence says
several choices
may exist for the next move
okay
but
i have to say that
don't be confused by
choices
okay
there is no choices
also
there is no probability
in our course
not in formal languages because for
advanced materials they have
you know probability probability or
something like that but
in our course throughout the whole
semester
we don't have choices
we don't have probability
don't forget that
okay
and it's not a choice
i will explain that further when we see
the formal definition you just remember
that
choices
choice is not
really a
good word
here
although it's on our textbook
anyway
so
for the final automata has the
capability of non-deterministic
computation we call then
nfa
okay we call them nfa
as the uh
as we define
deterministic finite automata we give an
example first now we also give it an
example here
we will define something like
you have several states
actually finite states like final
automata
then
for the states
when
as
when you see a symbol
when the machine see a symbol
it can go to several states instead of
exactly one
see
so for this example
if the machine sees zero
it goes to q1
okay
the behave here is like
uh determines a finite automata but
when it sees
one
it can go
q1 and also q2
remember that also q2
or
it can
see nothing
goes to another state
okay
it is kind of
confusing here
that
epsilon here is not a symbol
f epsilon here means the machine
doesn't consume any symbol
okay so it's kind of mixing two
notations because
for zero and one it consumes zero or one
right but for epsilon
it doesn't consume epsilon
it consumes nothing
and goes to q3
okay
then
whenever the machine
has
several
way to go several passes to go
that
like i said it's not a choice
it's not choices
the machine will go
how
by focusing
process
okay
think of the
current computer you have you can do the
uh
you can do
multi-thread or multi-process program
so you can think of the
non-deterministic computation is that
whenever you have several way to go
you go
only that
you folk process and one process goes on
the set of the original path and the
other process
or the other uh
other more process goes to all
the passes
another choice just go okay
so it's more like
when you uh so for the uh fundamental
deterministic
finite automata
when it process a string it's like
from start state
process the first symbol
goes to next state
and
processes the next symbol and the next
state
next symbol next state and
[Music]
last symbol
last
accept or not
or not
okay
but for non-deterministic computation
it's more like you start from the start
state the same star state but
for the
example above you see if the first
symbol is one
there will be one
process
goes to one way
and
another process in this case the other
process goes to the other way
so one process from q1
one process from q2
and this part
are irrelevant they don't communicate
each other
okay
the same thing goes on so
when
at this stage
the machine sees a symbol there are
three paths to go
it will folk
one process goes one path the other goes
this path and the one process goes
the other
okay
so that's the way how
non-deterministic final time that
handles the string
so
let's say
it will focus process
on every possible choice computational
path
so that's why i said
it's not
choices it's not a choice
you must go
okay you must go
so
how do we formally define such a
machine
pretty simple actually
we just need to extend we just need to
extend a little bit
our original definition
so let's go through this
a non-deterministic finite automaton is
also a five tuple so you have five
components
q
sigma delta q zero and f is basically
the same
so
finite sets of states the same
finite set of symbols which is alphabet
the same
so then
the fourth part
a star state within
the states
okay
a set of accept states which is a subset
of states the same so you can see that
1 2 4 5 is the same
so the only difference in the definition
is the transition function
we change
the definition of the transition
function firstly
we provide
epsilon
to be
the input
but it's kind like i said it's kind of
confusing that
uh usually we express we denote
epsilon with uh
alphabet with strong is like alphabet
with
epsilon
but you must know that for example
alphabet 0 1
when we write this alphabet with epsilon
it doesn't mean that
there is a
epsilon there is an empty string in the
symbol set it's not
it's only for
the definition of the function
it means that
if the function makes
the machine is on some
states and sees
something from alphabet
or
epsilon
but when it sees epsilon
it doesn't mean it consumes an empty
string
it means it's used
it used no
input symbol it used nothing from the
input okay
then delta will map
the combination of these two domain the
member from this two domain to
a power the power set a member of the
power set of q
okay
so uh if you are not familiar with power
set it's
all possible subset of a set
okay so for example if you have a
set like this
what is the subset of
what is the possible subset of this set
that will be empty set right
that will be only a
and only b
and a and b
it is
all possible subset of this set
that said let's say a
so
the set of all possible subsets
is power set of a
okay sometimes we
denote the power set by 2 to the a
something like that or something like
that sometimes
different different notation systems
so
why why do we
define transition function like this
because you see
for a finite automata you have only
finite states like this example you have
four states right
and you want to provide you want to say
that okay uh start from q2
i can go to some
other states
maybe or maybe not other you can go back
to q2
but where can you go
you can go all possible
states only
no state
right
q1
or q2 or q3 or q4
or
q1 and q2
q1 and q3
q1 and the q4 or you see
q2 q3 q2 q4 etc over
three states or four states
so
all possible
way to go
is the power set of
the set of the states
so the the
the
domain of the transition function will
be like this
okay
so
for the
example
here
we can
write down the formal definition of the
example here so let's say
the
anova here
we define n1 as
the five tuple here and the states are
q1 q2 q3 and q4
and you have uh the alphabet zero one
and again don't forget that zero one
here is not integers zero and 1. okay
then q1 is the start state
okay q1 is the start state and we have
only one accept states q4
okay that's our definition
then for transition function you can
absolutely see that
when q when you when the machine is on
q1
and the c is 0 the symbol 0 it goes back
to q1 only
okay
and if is this one
it goes to q1 and q2 so q1 and q2 and
don't forget that when it goes to q1 and
q2 it actually focus process one process
to q1 and once processed to q2 and they
never communicate with each other
okay
and
if it sees nothing
it goes nowhere
okay
goes nowhere so it doesn't
do that
it's nothing and go somewhere
on q1
and if the machine is on q2
c0 goes q3
right
and
you see here
if on q2 is this one
goes to nowhere
you can also think of this kind of
notation
like
undefined instruction something like
that
if you are using windows it probably
gives you
what uh
blue screen of death bsod right
so
if the cpu encounters
illegal instructions undefined
instruction
then you know the competition stops so
it's probably like that you can think of
it
as the situation
and then
for q2 we have an epson transition here
so when the machine is on q2 it can
just go to q3
no matter what and the input string is
not consumed
so you can see that
when it goes to q2
actually it will folk
another process
to go to q3 and the one process stay at
q2
okay that's the
non-deterministic part
then
for q3
there is no
there is no way to go for 0
and the 1 to q4 and the no epsom
destination and for q4
loop
at q4 and the no epsilon definition
so that would be
the the formal definition
of the example here
okay
so
so how
how do these
kind of
non-deterministic finite automata
operate
still
i use an example to let you know how it
operates
okay then we
give the formal definition
okay
so that's the
we have an input string
one zero
one one zero
okay
so the when the machine
starts it starts from q1
so let's say start from q1
then
you see the machine sees zero
the machine consumes the input zero
okay
so goes back to q1
so that's this one
then
the next symbol would be
one
one will
q1 go back to q1 so
there is a one process here q1 back to
q1
and the other process
goes to q2 right
and not over yet because there is an
amstrad here so every time
the process hits q2
one more process forked and go to q3 so
actually there is a process fork here
because of the app strong goes to q3
so for convenience
textbook right uh
using this one but actually it goes to
q2 and epson two to three
okay
then next symbol is here zero
so for q3
there is
no way to go
so
the computational path stops here
we don't need to chase that process
anymore
so we have q1 and q2 q1 c3 0 goes back
to q1 okay so it's the
road we have taken
and the q2 c0 goes to q3
right 0 here
then
q1 c1
is the same
as this part so there will be
q1
q2 and
you know epsom 2 q1 q3
and the q uh q3 here
this one goes to q4
okay
then
q1
c1
also
q1 q2 epsilon q3
and the q3 c6 1 goes to q4 and q4 c1
goes to q4
okay
and the final symbol here
q1 goes back to q1 q2 go to q3
and the q3 bank
stops
and q4 stays at q4 q4 states at q4
so that's how
this example
of nfa operates
you can also
trace any zero one string in this case
and i don't think that would be too
difficult for us to you know trace any
machine
unless it's very complicated
so
how do we
determine
even we know the machine operates in
this way how do we determine that if the
machine
accepts this string or not
it's pretty easy
as long as
the string
are all
consumed
the symbol of the string are all
processed
you know
that's a very
important criteria as long as
there is no
symbol left
you check
all the process
you check the states
which
you still have process on the state so
that would be q1
q3 q4 and q4 right because this process
is that this process is that here it was
done here
instead
so
as long as one
process stops
finally stops at
one of the accept states
the string
is
accepted see in this case we have
actually two process
stop at q on q4
it doesn't matter how many other
processes stop on non-accept states
doesn't matter
as long as
one
process
after processing all
the
symbols
stop at
one of the accept states then we
consider that the machine accept
that string
okay
so
somehow i remember that
many students ask a question that
it's
walk through the accept states
does not mean
does that mean
the machine accept the string
basically the answer is apparently no
why because
we still need to determine
accept or not
according to the definition
you can easily check that for
uh determined finite automaton right dfa
and
for
nfa how do we
define
if
an nfa accepts a string
how do we define that
the formal definition
is
also
a little
extension
of the
definition of dfa
so let's say
a non-deterministic finite automaton
a non-deterministic final automaton
accepts a string
where
each part
is
in
alphabet with
empty string
you can check that
with the definition with this definition
of dfa that
m here
is not the length of the string okay
so
in dfa we say that
the length of the
string is m so the each symbol of
the string can be
written as this and you have a 0
1 r 2
r n
something like that
but here we use the
symbol m here that means
y 1 y 2 through y n
is not exactly each symbol of the
string
some of them may be absolute that's that
means empty string some of them may be
nothing actually
anyway we will look back to the example
but we go on with the definition here
so
we say an nfa accepts string
w
w can be written as y1 y2 to ym
where each y i
is either a symbol
or
an empty string
then if a sequence of states r 0 r 1 to
r n which is exactly n plus 1 okay
exists with the three conditions
first
first condition
r zero is the star state it's the same
as dfa
second condition
rn
is a member of the accept state it's als
it is also the criteria the condition of
the definition
for dfa right
and
here
since the transition function of
nfa gives a set right because the
transition function of nfa
reads
a state right
and
some symbol
or epsilon
what will
the transition function for an effect
give you
it will give you a set
for example you go tell you goes to p
and the x
and y
three states
right see for dfa the transition
function gives you the
deterministic next step like
p
but for nfa it gives you a set
so this difference reflects
in the definition of acceptance of
strings
for nf for dfa you can see that we have
delta
ri
w i plus 1
equal to r i plus 1
that's the that's the uh that's what we
have in the definition for dfa and here
we
write the whole thing like this
it is because
the function here gives a set like this
and we only need the next
state
is one of
the
one is one member in the result
because the result is a set
right
so that means
when you have
when you uh when the pro up when the
machine is on ri
and it says y i plus one
ri plus 1 is
within the passes
of the machine
right
so
according to
you can
try to
read the definition based on the
definition for dfa
it will be easier
to
catch why we use
this
formula and this style of
definition
then we go back to our
example here okay
so
we say that
this machine
and
accept the string
0 1
1 1
0 is because
we actually can find
a sequence
of states
satisfying the three conditions
actually we can find two in this case
so let's go
uh first one
which is
easier
we separate the string here
as
y
y 2
y 5
y 6.
what is the corresponding
sequence of states that would be
q 1
q 2
q3
q4 q4 and q4
right
so you see
firstly
q1
which is r0
is the start state
and finally q4 is one of the accept
states of course this machine has only
one accept state
okay
and you see that q1
is within delta of q1
right because there are delta of q1
sorry it's a comma here
difficult to write it
so q1
0 will return something uh will what
what will written
just q1 as a set right so q1 is in the
set
and
you can see that q2
is
in
q1
and the q3
is
in
q2
q4
is in
q3
and also
q4 is in q4
right
so
why we say that the machine is machine
and accept the string one zero
sorry zero one one one zero
because we can actually separate
divide
the input string to y1 y2 to y6 which is
exactly one symbol each part and we can
find
the sequence of states
0 through
one two three four five six
r six
which is exactly
uh
one q one q one q two q three q four q
four q four
and satisfying the three conditions
okay
and
like i said actually we have two
sequence
in this case
the definition says that
if any
such sequence exist the machine accept
the string right so we already know that
the machine accept the string
but in this case we can see another
sequence
so
if you remember
there is a
absolute here
right
so this
transition actually need to break down
like this so we actually have y one
y 2
y 3
y 4
wi-fi is here
y
6 oh sorry
wi-fi is here
y
six
y seven
see
so there is a y here is empty string now
the symbol of the input string
and what is the sequence
corresponding to such a division
so the sequence will be q1
q1 q1
q1
q2 q3 q4
q4
so we actually have r0
1 2 3 4 five seven
ah
five six seven seven here r7
okay you can also check
if
the next one is
within the return
results of the delta function of the
previous one with the input
okay
so let's check this one
q3
this one
is
actually in
q2
epson
right because q2 epsilon is
a set of q3
so
for this machine to accept the string
0 1
zero one one zero
it actually has two paths
corresponding to two
uh two ways to
divide the string
and the two corresponding respectively
the sequence of states
so in this in this way you can
you can know that
why we say that okay uh here the process
is dead here process that it doesn't
matter
because
there won't be any sequence of states
generated by such path computational
path right
so
as long as one path
got
finally got the
accept states then we consider the
machine accept that string and the
formal definition can be returned
this way
it's not actually very different from
that's for dfa
as long as you know
where to look at
okay
so
the way to divide the string
and the corresponding
sequence of states
as long as the three condition is
satisfied then we say the machine
accept the string
okay so we have introduced a new kind of
binaural automata right
which has the capability of
of doing
non-com non-deterministic computation
and
here is the question
why
we want to introduce a new kind of
machine
i remember that we are trying to prove
the class of regular languages is under
the concatenation operation right
so
we need to
go we need to
go back
to proof
that how do we go how do we go back to
proof that
we want to
know
what kind of language do
the non-deterministic financial automata
recognize
you see
when we tweak the machine when we change
the machine when we define a new time
machine the machine is probably probably
different from
the original one
so
now we next step we want to
know
what kind of language
do
non-deterministic final automata
recognize
to see
if the new machine
is
if this kind of new machine is helpful
for our original purpose
okay
so we will see that
in the next lecture