okay uh the last part of this uh course
chapter seven time complexity and uh
as you may know that uh chapter six
advanced topics will not be covered in
this course if you are interested in
advanced topics in computability theory
you can consult uh chapter six
so uh
in chapter uh actually in chapter three
chapters three four and five
uh we introduced
turing machines
and of course other computational models
but um
basically we are we we are using turing
machines as our
computational models to discuss
computability
in
chapters
four and five
and
for uh chapters four and five
we roughly uh classified
all
computational problems
into
okay i would say three
uh regions the first region the first
region is decidability
sorry decidable so we have problems
decidable by turing machines that is for
any possible strings
in
a decidable language
you will have a turing machine as its
decider that is for any strings in that
language
you can use that to machine to decide
whether or not this
the input stream is in that language
that's decidable
and then we have something undecidable
but recognizable right and of course all
decidable languages are recognizable
because
by definition
the decider is exactly a recognizer okay
and
we have some languages
undecidable which means you cannot you
will not
be able
to
find decider for those languages but you
can find recognizers
right so for example atm is within this
region and we have other
uh
we have other
examples here and
the third region the
the third region is
something outside of recognizable that
means you have no way
to handle those kind of languages
and we have
examples too right like atm bar here
or uh we have defined ld here right
so
that's basically the computability
theory gives us
and of course you can uh you know keep
doing some other hierarchy
classification but we basically stop our
discussion
at this point
okay so that's computability that means
we discussed
what can be compute and what cannot be
compute
and we use these
regions to
[Music]
uh to indicate to demonstrate the
conclusions
then make him back to the
computation uh actually
making back to what we want to know
give if you have a language which is a
problem right
if you have a language then
what means
what does that mean by the language
for in this region
or
this region
and according to our definition we now
have
a clear idea of
how
uh or uh whether or not the given
language the given problem can be
computed or not right in a way if a
language is in
decidable languages that means
you will be able to find
an algorithm
as a turing machine to decide any given
input string is in that language or not
so
there's no problem that we consider such
a language or a problem
computable right you can
oversolvable via computational
devices
and then for all
languages outside recognizable
then you know that
there is no way no any way
to
solve those problems
by using computational devices
computational machines
so that's you know basically
uncomputable
then how about undecidable
and
uh sorry undecidable but recognizable
like
languages in this region well that
depends how you interpret
the concept we developed along the
course okay you can you actually you can
consider this language solvable
but i think
uh most people
will not agree to this because
well to some extent yes and actually
to some extent in our real life
many problems are undecidable but
recognizable something like if you
if you want to buy some
clothes list or you want to buy
something even
consumer electronics
you don't really know what you want but
if you find something you want you know
it
right so
of course such a scenario is not really
computational problems but
you can
probably see the analogy between the
situation and
languages that are
undecidable but recognizable something
like that
so
whether or not
let's say languages within undecidable
but recognizable computable
uh
maybe contr controversy but
controversial but uh
language we think decidable
basically
can be considered
computationally
solvable
right
so
in this
chapter chapter 7
we focus
basically we focus
our
uh the languages within
the decidable region okay
so
from this well
from now on
for most
cases
we focus our
discussion
we think
decidable that means
if a language can
be
decidable then we discuss how much time
we want to
compute it
okay
how much time we we we are willing to
spend on
solving this
then uh solving this problem or handling
this language
okay because even a language
is decidable
that means it is
computationally solvable
okay that's that language is
computationally solvable however
solvable in theory or in practice
okay
theoretically it is solvable
but if i tell you yes you can do it in
1000 years
then
do you think
it is solvable or not
okay actually so main for many
scientific computation you can estimate
pretty precisely estimate how much time
you need to do the computation
well for a famous
problem of for a famous topic like a
human genome project
when i was in
undergraduate i i guess
uh scientist scientist says that uh it
probably needs to take
20 to 40 years
to
finish the whole job the whole project
of course there
then there are many uh
there are many new technology invented
and speed up the whole process so we
years ago we already have a human genome
project finished but
if we don't have those new invention new
technology we probably really need like
30 years to
finish that project
of course it's not a computational
project but
we can estimate how long the project
need
then we determine that it is practically
doable or not
okay so in this chapter don't forget
that
we will
basically be focusing on
decidable languages
after a language being decidable we then
discuss how much time you need to decide
that
language okay so we don't discuss
uh how much time we need to
recognize
atm we don't do that because you know it
it is very likely that a input string
will cause you
doing the computation forever so we
don't discuss those cases
we only
we will be only uh we will be facing
only languages in the region of
decidable
okay
again that is uh
basically
because
in practice when you do the computation
you need
to you need some resources the resource
resource are resources including
the computational time
or the memory or space you need to
finish the job
or other resources
and you can do all complexity on every
you know aspect for example there are
there may be networking algorithms you
need to consider bandwidth
right
in practice
so anyway
in reality when you want to do
computation
you will be
uh bounded by
the resources you need
so after
a language being decidable in theory
then we discuss how much resources we
need
again we
shrink our focus here we only focus on
time
okay we only we focus only on time in
this chapter and talking about how much
time
how much time you need to decide a
language
that's why we have time complexity for
this chapter
okay
so we're focusing on time
and then
in order to
talk about time like in order to talk
about computation we defined two
machines
so in order to talk about time we need
to define time
well some may ask
why we want to define time isn't time of
you know fee uh a quant a
property or a quantity of physics or
something you can see the wall clock you
have
physical time like real time here or
clock time
but
since our
computational model computational
machine is
abstract right turing machines or other
machines anyway
we
will
be talking about time
uh
respect to two machines instead of our
physical real world
okay so the time will be defined on
the uh in terms of turing machines
okay
then
let's define time like this
if you have a turing machine that's m
the deterministic theory machine okay
vitamin c2 machine let's talk about dtm
first
determines the turing machine
that
holds on o input
that means m is a decider
right so m will decide
the language l of n
okay so that's our
turing machine
so
if you have a turn machine that might
not be hold
might not be hold on some input then
it's outside of definition
all right so for let's say for the rig
for a recognizer of atn
a recognizer of atm may hold may hold on
some input that
those inputs are in atm
but it might not
hold on some input that outside atm
right so the definition does not include
those
two machines we own we only define
we only define running time
or time complexity
of
the two machine holds on or input
okay that is
deciders
okay so then we use the term rung mean
time okay
wrong in time
and
time complexity
equivalently okay so
don't think about running time is a time
okay let's define the whole term first
then i will go back to explain it
because many
previous students
have confusions here
okay
running time or time complexity of n
okay is a function
okay it's a function that's it is very
important it is a function
mapping from
natural numbers to nature numbers
okay
and f of m
is the
maximum number
okay
this is important maximum number of
steps
that
and uses on any input of length
n
okay
so what does this mean this is basically
the definition of our running time or
time complexity of
a turing machine
which holds on all input
okay
let's say
you can think of a concrete example to
help you to understand the deformation
so let's say you have a turing machine
the alphabet is
zero and one
okay the input alphabet or
uh
the
type alphabet is like visual and one and
blank something like that anyway
so the input
alphabet is zeroing one
so
for example
for length 3
for input string of length 3 so you will
have 8 possibilities right so you might
have 0 0 0 zero zero one zero one zero
etc
one one one
so
you will have
the cardinality of your input stream
sorry input alphabet to the power of m
for any input
of length n
you will have so many
possible for that particular length of
input strings
and of course
when you run that two machine on all
these input
you might need
different numbers of steps
right
let's say
you know it's very weird but let's say
we designed a
language
on alphabet zero one
and our language contains
all strings begin with one
end with one
okay can i have a language like that yes
i can right
then how do you design your tune machine
you will check the first
the first symbol is one then go to the
end of the string and check if the last
one is one then if yes accept if no
reject right
of course such a
language is decidable because we can
easily write the turing machine doing
the decision
then in this case you will find that for
lens three
the machine c0
reject right
so that takes step one one step one over
two okay
and one
reject
sorry are zero reject and for the
uh
zero one one
reject right it's that it takes many uh
sorry very few steps to reject such
string because
it
the first symbol is zero not one
and then
for this
other four strings you will need to go
to the last one to see if it is
one right
so you will take more steps
for all these probably you know three or
five steps doesn't matter
then
our f of n
mapped to the maximum
steps
okay
so for this example you have a uh you
have eight impossible input stream for
length three
then
for each possible input string the
machine may
act differently and the tag
take different numbers
of steps
our f of n
mapped to the maximum number
so for this example probably f of three
map to
for i just you know
make up some example like six step so f3
so maximum and for these parts we ignore
them because
it takes very few steps to finish these
cases and we ignore them first here
so in here a run in time and time
complexity is a function
mapping from natural numbers to natural
numbers
and the input of the function is the
length of the input string to
that
to the machine
and the output of the function
is the
maximum number of steps that that turing
machine use
on any input of length m
okay so that's our running time or time
complexity
so
i would suggest
you use time complexity for the concept
here
because if you use rung mean time
you will get stuck
oh okay not not all of you but some of
you may get stuck with the concept
concept of time
you tend to think that okay this machine
needs like seven hours to finish the job
or need three minutes to finish the job
no we are not talking about
any machine running on any specific
input stream no we are not talking about
that
we are talking about
a growth ratio
of that two machine
we are talking about the behavior of
natural machine what behavior
how the machine responds
to
the input stream not particular input
stream but
the
length of the input string
when
for example you have a two machine when
you input
this long attack this time
and you input this long
attack this time when you input this
long you take it take this time
we are talking about
the increase
in the input string length
corresponds to
the variation of
the number of steps need to be taken by
that two machine
that is
the running time we are defining here
over time complicity
okay
so don't think running time is a
length of you know one o'clock time like
three minutes
five minutes no it's not
it it it is even not
the a turing machine
exactly
needs
uh this
it is even not the exact number of steps
taken by a two machine to process the
input stream a particular input stream
no we are not talking about any
particular case here we are talking
about
a behavior of a turing machine
by
using
a function to reflect the relationship
between
the length of the input string and the
maximum number of steps needed by that
two mission
okay so you have to
understand it
clearly then you will know
what we will be talking about in this
chapter that's very important okay
then
let's go on with the definition here
if f of n is the running time of n we
say that m wrongs in time
f of n
okay
we say m runs in time f of n
also we say that n
is an f of n time turing machine
f of n time to machine
okay so that means
we use f of n to describe
the behavior of transmission
that's our purpose
okay
very similar to we use two machine to
say computation you know it's kind of
you need to un uh
to uh
comprehend
the connection between the uh
terminology here and the concepts we are
going to introduce
here and of course
we from now on we usually use n
to represent the length of the input
well it is not you know necessary but
it's a custom so
we we see n in this chapter we know that
that's a that's the input of two machine
okay
so
we compute the rounding time of an
algorithm
purely as a function
of the length
of the string
representing the input
it is very important to
length
of
the string representing the input
okay
it is a important concept connected back
to the check back to the end of chapter
3 we are talking about
you need a representation for your
tuning machine to process
well
uh
you might think that
for example
you have a
algorithm processing
songs
processing audios
or videos
and
when you see
let's say a video you see
uh moving pictures and or you know
object in motion
and
how and here you
you can consider that anyway
the video or the audio file is a file on
disk
they are anywhere encoded
as
data
binary data and the binary data is
actually the string
we are talking about here the string is
not ascii code or utf-8 udf 16 code you
are familiar with as you know readable
by human no the string here
is basically the data you fit into
the two machine
okay so you have to uh
familiar
with this kind of concept okay
then
here we define time complexity as
maximum number of steps
okay
so that can connect to the concept of
worst case analysis
okay worst case analysis
and in worst case analysis we consider
the longest running time of all inputs
of a particular length which is n here
right
so
we are doing this in this chapter or in
this course
but of course there are other ways we
will not be introduced here
and
one of them is like average
case analysis okay average case analysis
so instead of defining
running time as the maximum number of
steps you can of course you can define
that it's a average number okay like
like the uh example i
uh gave
previously
you might average all the eight
steps
you have an average
number here then you define that is the
output
that's okay
then we call that
average case analysis okay
but we don't do that here we do
worst case analysis of course there are
bad uh best case analysis but
all these are uh you will employ those
uh definition when you need them okay so
we do worst case analysis here
okay
then
the problem is
the definition here
the definition here is okay right you
know that are given uh uh given a two
machine you can define that the turing
machine responds to
uh
input of a particular lens
how
in the worst case how many steps it
needs it needed
it needs to finish the computation
but that's not enough for
uh
for our purpose because it is
basically it is very very very difficult
to come up with
the exact function
as the running time of a particular two
machine
it is very difficult
if possible actually
you can uh i will not go back in the
slide but you can go back to chapter
three four and five you'd end
probably three actually
you
just select one or two three machines
and
think about how you can come up with the
function
defined here it is you know very
difficult
if possible
so we need other
mathematics construction mathematical
construction to
help us
to help us to uh
continue the
analysis here so we
use a sympathetic analysis terminology
here
to
further
abstract the behavior of a function
then
we can talk about
the abstract behavior of that particular
two emission
okay so the notation here we adopt
is uh basically big o notation
and we will introduce big o and a small
notation here
and what is those
uh for example if you have a turing
machine if you have a turing machine
of which the running time is
like this
okay it's like this
of course we don't you know we don't
we we usually cannot come up with a uh
exact function like this but
assume we have a function like this
then for
bigger notation
we can describe
we can describe this function
we describe this function
as
big o of
and cubic
okay
let's see what did it what what is the
definition okay
let's say
we have
function f and g
which are from natural number to
positive real numbers
we say that
f of n
which
is the function u want to describe
can be written as
big o of
g of n
if
positive integers c
and n 0 exist
such that
for every integer
n
larger or equal to n 0
the function you want to describe f of n
always equal to or um
less than
the constant c
times g of x
okay
so if you have uh you can use some
example to help you to understand the
concept here for example
you have a function like
let me
oops
like this
assume that this function is the one you
want to describe
okay
then
you use a function
that's bad that's here
you use a function like this
uh assume not from
these
do it again
so you have a function one uh like
this is the function you want to
describe
and you use a function like this one
assuming that after
after
this
g of n
always bigger than f of n
okay assuming
after this one
then in this case
c let's say c is one and the n zero is
here
then we use g of n
to describe f of n
maybe g of a
maybe usually we we are using
a sim
a simple function
for g like n square
then
we use
the simple function
to
describe the behavior of
f of f of n the function you want to
describe okay so that that is the usage
that is the purpose of big o notation
okay
you can consider big o notation is
something like a
sketch of a photo
you have a photo here that is pretty you
know uh complicated
and you use
a sketch
to extract
something you want to look at and ignore
others
okay
and since it's it is a sketch it is a
abstraction
we use big o
the notation here to
represent
to tell others that
we are using
this kind of
this kind of definition
to describe
the target
by using such a notation we describe
these targets as g of n
so
when we and g of n is usually a simpler
form
then you can we can get the idea of the
behavior of f of n
of f of n
and you can
then we can discuss
more complicated concepts
later
so
that's why
for this
function
we can find
c
maybe let's say seven
and then
n zero i don't know you can cut it's a
pretty
easy to calculate you just need to
calculate
when
7 n cubic bigger than or equal to
the function here right probably i don't
know 10 20 or something anyway there
will be n 0 here
because c and n 0 exist
we can say that
f of n can be described as big o of
g of n where g of n is n cubic
so you can see that we can use
n cubic
to describe a more complicated function
forms
right
so that's an example
and let's see another example
like this
f1 of n be the function
pretty complicated right
then
we know that
for well we know that from the previous
example we know that uh just let's
selecting the highest order
and cubic here and discuss the
coefficients we know that
we can describe f of
one of n as
big o of
n cubic
right
and but we we cannot just do that we
need to verify it because the definition
is
is newbie uh need to be satisfied
so let's say
we
let
c
to be six
and
after actually every calculation or
you can just guess that and n should be
10 and 0 to be 10
then we know that the function f
1 of n
for every
n bigger than
n0
greater than n0
it's always equal to or less than
g of n here
sorry not given c times g of n here
here's c6 right
so that's why according to the
definition we describe f1 of n as big o
of n cubic
so the idea is that we are using a
simpler function forms to describe
the asymptotic behavior of the target
function
okay
so that's the point here
then
according to the definition yes you can
always
have
a higher order
function to describe the function you
want to you want to describe
for this particular example
we of course we can
say that f1 of n
can be described by big o of n to the
fourth power
to the power of four
right because the growth rate of n
to the fourth power
always
larger than cubic
right of course according to a
definition you can say that
but you will never be able to say
f1 of n
can be described by n square it's
impossible
because
you will
not be able to find c
and 0
2 to fulfill
this
it's impossible so we cannot describe
f1 of n
as big o of n square
right
so
usually we are interested in a lowest
order
that is able to describe the target
function by definition you can use
higher but
the lower is the better because you can
know pretty closely the behavior of the
target function
okay
then for another example
regarding
logarithms
okay that's very uh you know the
interactive we speak all in a particular
way as the text here
why because you can change the base of a
log
okay
you can change your base
change the base of load
usually when you want to use logarithms
you must
specify the base
right you must specify the base
for example
you say and
with
base 2 log is x
so that means
2 to the power of x is m
okay
that means
it but
in big o
we ignore
constant
right we ignore the constant coefficient
constant factor and
for lo for log
you can
easily change you can easily change
the
face
by using for example
let's say
log
2 of n
is x
right as this one
and we know that
log
either
another base log b of n
is equal to
log
base 2 log of n
divided by this term
log
2 base b
and if b is a constant the whole thing
is a constant right
then in a way you can always change to
any other base
by multiply a constant
sometimes some constant corresponding to
the base you want to change to
okay
and that's why
for
big o notation
for big o notation
we write only
log
n
that's why we don't really specify the
base for the log for the log function
because the base for the log function
doesn't play a particular role here
because we can always
change
the base by multiplying some
constant factor
and constant vector is ignored
in bigger notation
okay
so then you can
more actually
more precisely understand
the common behavior of log function
it doesn't matter
where which
basis we are using because the
we are we just want to describe the
target function
has
the behavior of
log functions
okay
so we usually
don't write
base here
okay
and so here is the note that
many of you might uh read some paper
later and lay
may
write
like uh 10
and
something like this
and there are two possible cases here
one
the authors
don't really understand
the bigger notation
that's one possibility
and the other possibility is that
they understand
big old notation but
they have to write like this
because
the algorithm they propose
may improve on the base here
okay
so they improve the improvement they are
they are uh
they they want to
emphasize on
is not
a
uh
it's not on a label on the level of
you know you can see the difference in
the big o notation no probably not
but they have a constant
improvement
which will be
which will disappear
in bitcoin notation so they have to
put and emphasize on the contribution
they are making that's the other
possibility
but anyway we have to know that
usually we don't write base of the log
when you use the bigger notation
okay
so here's another example
if you have a function like this one
see
it is a concrete
function instance so you have to specify
okay this term is
the log
for this term is base the base of the
log is 2
and then we use
big o of n log n
to describe this function
we don't need to specify the base
because it doesn't make difference in
bigger notation
and also that we
we are sure
n log n can be
used to describe f of 2
f 2 of n because log n dominates log log
n
okay logo log log n is
pretty close to constant anyway so
that's the
definition of bigger notation
okay
so
when you when we are able to describe a
function
with bigger notation we say that
g of n here
is an upper bound
of
f of n
or more precisely because we do it
through
o notation through the asymptotic
analysis so we say that g
g of n is n
a symmetric upper bound
for f of n
so that means
the growth rate
of g of n
is
equal to
or greater than the growth rate of
f of n
okay and
we are
suppressing constant factors
so in the previous case i draw
i say that c
is one right
but you can say that
for example
you have a f of n here
and you have a g of n here
and
probably
after some factor
you can change the n like this one
and after n0
c of g of n c times g of n always larger
than f of n then you can use
big o of g of n
to describe
f
okay
so that is the idea here
and
since we are using a simpler function
to
describe
usually a more complicated function
the simpler function we are using
should give us some pretty clear idea
regarding the behavior
of the function you want to describe
right
so we are you we usually use
one polynomial
as the g of n here
if a function f
can be found on
with a polynomial
for some c bigger than zero
then we say that we have the polynomial
bound of that function f
and the other family we are usually use
uh usually using is exponential forms
okay
that means
you have some
constant
you have some constant
and
to the power of n
that is the polynomial
sorry uh exponential forms so polynomial
is that
you have
constant angular power here
and the exponential is like you have a
constant base
and the n don't forget that n what is n
and is the input string length of the
turing machine
on the exponential here
of course you can always rewrite this
quantity into this form
and remember that 2 here is not
important
because you can change to any base
okay
and for big o notation base doesn't
matter but
for the log
for the log notation you can
ignore
base here
but you you always need some base to
write this form so we choose two
two here is not really two it's just a
placeholder there is some
you you we want to emphasize that
the
n is
n is in the part of exponentials okay so
uh
we usually use two family function
families as our balance one is
polynomial bounds the other is
exponential bounds because
they can provide us pretty clear ideas
regarding the behavior of the target
function
okay
and finally we since we have introduced
big o we introduce small small o
notation uh together okay
so for a small
notation it's pretty
similar to bigger notation we say that
f of f of n can be described
as
small of g of n
if
when n approach infinity
the ratio of
of
f over n and g of n is zero
okay that means
that means
uh
the growth rate of g of n
is faster
is faster than of
f of n the growth rate okay that not the
not the absolute value
a growth rate
so
in other words if we use the definition
we use for
uh big o
we can say that for any real number c
larger than zero
there is a number exists
uh and zero exists
for all n
larger than
or
equal to n zero
f of n is smaller than c times g of n
okay
and for big o it's like you have one
more
equal here but for small o there's no
equal here
so in this for this definition we can
say that
we can check that
we can describe
square root of n as
small of n
right because
you can divide it
something like this
and
you will know that when n
approach to infinite that's zero
okay
and you can describe n
as n log log n because
although it is
it grows very slowly but
it grows
okay so
when n approaches uh
infinity
the ratio will be zero
but you will not be able to describe n
as small
o
right it's
it's not
doable because
they the growth rate of the
true
function is the same so it's not uh it's
not
the form here does not satisfy
the definition
okay
oh that's uh
f of n is never
small all of f of n because the grocery
gross uh growth rate ratio is the same
okay so small o
here
is
uh
indicate that the g of n here
grows faster than f of n but big o here
you have the possibility that g of n and
f of n grows with the stem ratio i
usually want that because we want to
describe f of n as
as precise as possible as possible
okay
so now
we will have
a sympathetic
uh
form to describe f of n which
is usually unavailable for some given
two emissions
so now we are ready to do the analysis
and we will do that
next time