okay
uh after defining polynomial time
reducibility and proofed
theorem 7.31
let's go on with an example okay
okay
uh let's define
a normal phone which is called
a conjunctive normal form for boolean
formula okay
so for boolean formula actually we
usually consider boolean variables like
x
y or z
they are called boolean variables
because they have
two possible values usually zero
and one or
true and false okay
and here we call
here we call
a boolean variable and it's
negation like x bar
the negation means that if x is is false
x bar is true and if x is true x bar is
fourth okay
and we call
a boolean variable and it's negation
literal okay literal and then
literals connected
by or like this one x1 or x2 bar or x3
bar or x4 okay
so leader rows
connected by
or
operator
forms
a clause
from circles
so conjunctive normal phone
always uh
or
uh
cnf formula
or cna formula
is
clauses
connected
by using
and
okay
so we usually call it conjunction and
it's conjunction and or is this
disjunction
so
boolean formula in this form
we call this form
cnf
formula so conjunctive normal form
and is there disjunctive normal phone
yes there is okay and
we call it
normal form like
we explained in
uh
what chapter three uh chapter two i
guess
um
chomsky normal phone okay like we
explain that
when we when we uh
set some form to be normal phone that
means
all the stuff
like for context free grammar we say
that
uh
we call the
normal phone we introduced
uh chomsky normal phone
and we call that kind of form normal
form because all
basically
all
context-free grammar can be represented
by that
can be represented
in such a form
so conjunct
conjunctive uh conjunctive normal phone
here is the same
that means
all boolean formula
can be
represented
in this form that's why we call it
conjunctive normal form and why and how
we
is are not uh problems here are not
questions here we want to answer
here we just need to know that
boolean formula can be represented by c
and f okay so any boolean formula can be
represented by
clauses
connected
with
and
okay so also disjunctive normal phone
but we don't uh use that here
and if
if
okay again so since all
boolean formulas can be represented in
conjunctive normal form so uh if you
have any boolean formula you can
you know convert it to
c and f
and so
it is possible to
find equivalent not possibly
it should we surely can find equivalent
c and f for any
boolean formula okay
so we think
we think cnf
that's defined as a spatial type
spatial form of
cnf we call it three cnf formula okay
so for free cnn formula
uh
each class
has exactly
three
literals
okay
we don't know how many clauses that uh
it
you can have as many as
possible clauses you want but each
clause has exactly three cnf formula
oh sorry has three literals
if you have a cnf
of such property
of such a property we call it
three cnf formula
then we define
a special
problem or a language here we call three
set
for three sets
that means
it contains all boolean formulas
what kind of formulas
satisfiable three cnf formula
okay
so three set
three set contains
all
satisfiable
three cnf formula
okay so this uh language or problem is
well defined right
now we want to show it as an example for
polynomial time reduction
okay
so
here it uh
it is theorem
7.32 we want to prove that three set
is polynomial time reducible to
click okay polynomial time reducible to
click
then
don't forget what we need to do to prove
this uh
theorem we want to have a function
we want to have a function the function
is polynomial time computable
and
the function provides
the
capability uh
function provides such
a property that if you have a
w
if you have an input string w
in
three set
if and only if
f of w
in
click
okay
okay that's uh
c l i q u
e in click
so we want to
design a function like this
and say that it is com uh the function
is computable and
also polynomial time computable
and then the function has such a
property provides such a functionality
for us to convert and any input string
in
three sets if and only if
the output string is in click
okay
so
how
let's describe how the function works
okay we don't we don't want to write the
details but
the ideas is straightforward like this
one so assume that
remember that we want to have a function
again
let's use phi here so phi is in preset
if and only if
f of phi
in
click
and what is
apple right here that would be uh
instance for click right
so we will output a graph
and a number
right if you don't remember what's the
definition of
uh of click then you can go back to
check it so
for a five
sorry for fine for putting formula for
putting formula in 3c and f we want to
output
a graph and a number
the graph
and the number
is in click if and only if
the given
three cnn formula
is in three set
okay
so
let's do it
so assume that we have
this
formula
then what should we do
firstly
our turing machine go through the whole
string
once and you will know that
how many
clauses
of uh in this formula right in this case
there are three for three clauses
but the three is a coincidence of one
two three
one two three right that's coincidence
if there are four then you may have like
something a or b
or c something like that okay
anyway
so
we know
how many closes here
so for each clause
for each clause we produce
three notes
in the graph okay three notes in a graph
so if you have one more clause you have
one more three notes
okay then
we mark the notes with the leader role
so
the first clause we have x1 x1 and x2 so
we mark x1
x1
x2
mark the node
label the node okay or take the node
whatever
then
for the second clause we mark
x1 bar x2 bar x2 bar
and for the
third clause we have x1 bar x2 and x2
so if you have the fourth clause you
mark them a b c
okay so according to what you have in 3c
and f you output
these vertex
then to
compose a graph
in addition to verdicts we need h
right we need edges
so how do we uh
connect these
how do we connect these
vertex
the rule
is simple
the rule is simple
all vertex
basically are connected
except for two conditions
first
there is no age
of the same
between the nodes of the same group
okay
there is no h
between the
note between the vertex of the same
group
okay so that's the first exception the
other one is
there is
no age
between
a boolean variable
and its
negation
that's it
so you will see that
in this graph there is no edge between
x1 and x1 bar
x2 and x2 bar x2 and x2 but there's no
edge between
a boolean variable and its negation
so that's it
that's the two exceptions so you will
see that
when going through
the boolean formula here
you can construct the graph
right
you just output each literal as a node
and you know
there are
if you have l closes then you will have
l
group of
three nodes
then you connect the nodes
and how do you connect the nodes
basically every node
every pair of those are connected uh is
connected
except for
nodes of the same group and
boolean variable and its own
negation
okay
then
we specify
since we already have the
g here right where it is an h then we
need to specify a k
how many should we specify in this case
since we have 1 2 3
clauses so we specify 3 here
so
this input stream
this input string
is what we need to output
after computing
the computer uh computable function
the computer function is basically our
program right so our program reads
in the boolean formula and output
the graph and three in this case
okay the three is not three c and f the
three is three clauses
in this case
so
firstly we want to prove that the
procedure
really satisfies
if
the given
formula in
three set
if and only if
the output
in
click
right we need to establish the
uh making new disability first here
so why
that's quite easy because
if
the boolean formula is satisfiable
you just
need
to
mark
okay so if the boolean formula is
satisfiable
at
least each in each clause in each clause
at least one literal
is true
right because the clauses are connected
by end
so each close must be true
and for each clause to be true
as long as you have one literal to be
true then the clause is true because
they are connected by or
right
then you just need to
mark
for each close
the leader row
the true the literal of which
the value is true on the graph you will
get a click
why
because
since each leader each clause has
you you pick one if you have two two or
more it doesn't matter you just pick one
okay
so for
since the
whole pulling formula is true then each
clause must have has at least one
literal to be true and you peak
from each
close
one true literal and a mark on the graph
when you mark on the graph
firstly how many nodes you will mark on
the graph you will mark exactly the
number of clause
verdicts right
and then remember how we draw the graph
basically all nodes are connected
except for
two conditions right the first one is
vertex of the same group
not connected
but
since the node you mark are from each
clause so
those notes are not
limited
by this rule by this condition right
and secondly
since
the node you pick represents
a boolean
value assignment to the boolean
variables
you won't have like
x1 is true
and x1 bar is true you won't have such
conditions you will have a consistent
boolean assignment
because
you already know
the
the formula is satisfiable we want to
prove this way okay now
so you know that file is satisfiable so
according to the choose assignment you
won't have such conditions
you will have consistent assignment and
that assignment lets you pick
the notes on graph and you won't pick x1
x and x1 bar
at the same time
our x2 and x2 bar at the same time no
you will pick you know consistent stuff
then in this way
since you will not pick
you will not select a boolean variable
and it's negation
then you are you are
you can be sure that
all the notes you pick on the graph are
connected
because
that's all how we draw the graph right
so if
as long as the boolean formula is
satisfiable
exactly that boolean assignment that you
have
k click
undergrad okay so that's the one
direction
on the other hand
if someone gives you this graph
and three
if such a graph can you if you can find
three click on such a graph how do we
prove that the original boolean formula
is satisfiable
the same reason because when you p
when
you can successfully get a k click on
such a graph that means
that means
firstly
from each group
you exactly pick one note
right
it's enough it's not possible for you to
pick two notes from the same group
because
same notes in one group
sorry
nodes in the same group
are not connected so
if you you if you do have a k click
from the
graph since there are k groups on the
graph
you must
select one note from each group
that's the first thing
and the other thing is we don't have
connection between
a boolean variable and its negation for
the nodes
so since
the nodes you peak forms
a complete graph on the graph
you won't pick
a boolean
variable and its negation
so
that will form
a consistent boolean assignment
so for this example let's say we pick uh
that okay see
it is a three click
right
so you will see
to form a three p a three
click
firstly you must have
note from each group secondly you will
not
pick
boolean variable and its negation so we
pick what
x1 bar
right this one is x1 bar and this one 61
bar
and x2
that means x1 bar should be true and x2
should be true
so x y bar should be true that means x y
is false okay
so these
will satisfy
will make this
will satisfy this uh boolean formula so
let's check it
so x one bar is true so x one is four
right so false false x two is true right
true so this clause is true
and the true false false this clause is
true
and
true true true so this so this course is
true so see
if you can
find a three click on this graph
that
selection
makes the original
booting formula satisfiable
okay
so now we have a
conversion process which is the f the
computable function
converts
boolean formula
to
an instance
in
click and
such that
phi in three sets if and only if
the output
proper instance in
click
and the whole process can be
finished in polynomial time because
when you read
once right then go back
and
output
output the node
i'll put a note
right
and connect the edges and don't forget
that
you how many nodes you have it's linear
to the length
right linear to the length and how many
edges
at most
vertical
vertical square of vertex right
then after you collect the uh the
number of clauses you know that
you need to specify
k in this case s3
so all the process is apparent
the process the whole process is
apparently
doable within
linear to the uh
length of the input string so
within the polynomial time
okay so that's a
example for
uh for normal time reduction
from three sets to click
after
equipped with uh
after equipped with
the polynomial time reduction
that's formally define empty complete
okay mp complete
and actually
something
complete
is a general definition
something
complete okay so here we talk about np
complete
so for np complete
there are
two conditions
we say that a language b is mp complete
if language b satisfies
the following two conditions first
b itself is in mp
okay b itself
is in mp
then otherwise we don't talk about
complete
complete means that the whole mp
for some criteria can be
can become
the whole ante the instant all the
instance in np can become b
okay for some criteria
so firstly b itself massing mp to talk
about and be complete
then
for every language in mp
there is a polynomial reduction
to the language b
okay
there is a
polynomial reduction to language b
so again why we call it np complete that
means the language b itself is in mp and
all the language in mp can be polynomial
time reducible to b
so you can think of b as a
representative
of the class and p
okay
so
let's
introduce another
clause
we say that
if every language in mp is polynomial
reducible to b
and
if we don't have this criteria
we call b
mp
heart okay you might seen this term in
many literatures because people love it
and behave seems you know
harder than mp complete
but
mp heart has no such
conditions that means
the language we the language b
may be
harder than mp
okay although we don't introduce
you know bigger classes here but there
are some of them so
mp hard means
language b is
hard at least as np something like that
anyway
so
since b itself b here itself is in np
and every language a
in mp is polynomial time reducible to b
by defining this term now
we can prove that
if a language b is nb complete
and
b is in p somehow you can prove that if
then we know
p
equals to np
okay p equals to mp
and actually we don't need to prove that
right
because firstly
p
is a subset of mp
right
we know that
that's by definition we already
explained it
then
if there is a language
is
if there exists a language to be mp
complete
like b here
if you have mp complete
b
and you can prove that
this language is in p
if you can prove that a mp complete
language in p
then according to a definition you see
every language in np
is polynomial time reducible to b
and b is in p
so
every language in np is in p
right
why we already uh prove that right
because we have a
theorem here
if a language a has a polynomial time
reduce a b are reducible to his
polynomial reducible to e3 sorry is for
normal time reducible to b and the b is
in p then a is in p right
and you know that for b
for b
here
b is mp complete
then every
language in mp is pronoun time reducible
to b
and by using that theorem we know
a
in p
so every a in mp
is in p that means
mp
is a subset of p
and we know already know p is a subset
of mp
right
so
it makes
p equal to mp
okay so
if you can prove a an
mp complete language to be in p
you effectively proved
p and the mp are the same cost that's
why i said
defining empty complete
help us to study the relationship
between p and mp because
if you really had
if you really have some np complete
language you can just
you just need to study those languages
you don't need to study every language
in np or p
doesn't matter now
we have a theorem here then we only need
to study the mp-complete language if we
can prove
any one of the np-complete language to
be in p we proved p equals to mp or
if we proved
and if we want to prove p and mp are
different
class
those np complete languages are most
likely candidates to be not in p
right so
then
uh the second theorem we want to prove
is
if b
is mp complete
if there is a mp complete language
and you know this
mp company language
has
a polynomial reduction to another
and b sorry another language
and you know that
that other language is in mp
then
see here
is also empty complete
okay
it's also np complete
why because we can easily prove that
right
so
since c is in mp
c
satisfied satisfies the first condition
then
b is mp complete
that means every language in mp
is polynomial reducible to b
right and you know
b is polynomial time reducible to c
so we can every language
in mp
we have a
computable function polynomial time
computable function
and to c we have another polynomial time
right
so every language a and p can go through
f and go through g to c
and how much time you need
for the conversion
polynomial time
because
polynomials
sorry not this way
polynomials polynomial
still polynomial so the total computer
computation time
spends on f and g to do the composition
of the two function
must be bounded by polynomial
so
c satisfies the second condition so of
course c is complete uh mp complete
okay
so
let's say
uh
this block is what i said okay
so
now we what we have we have defined
and be complete
okay
and we know that mp complete can
help us to study the relationship of p
and np
and now we know that if we have an mp
complete language
we can easily
prove
other language to be mp complete
by reduce
the non-mp company language to
the one you want to prove
okay
so the problem is
where is
the first and the complete language
what is the first np-completed language
right that's the problem
we can define
anything but
find an example for that thing that's
another problem
so
here we want to prove cook's lemon
theorem which is
sat
is mp complete
all right
satisfied
satisfiability problem is mp complete
problem
so
if you think about it it is kind of
difficult
why because you need to
prove
every language in mp that's very
difficult
is polynomial time reducible to
sat here
right
how do we handle that
so the key point is
since
a
any language a in is in mp
there is
a non-deterministic undetermined
non-deterministic machine
decide that language
right
we don't know what
machine that
is that but we know since the language a
is an in mp
there must be
non-deterministic
turing machine as decider for that
language
that's the key part of this proof okay
so let's go through it so we want to
prove sat is com mp complete
firstly we need to show that
sat is in mp sad itself is emp right
that's the first condition
and how do we show that how do we do
that
you can easily say that we have we can
construct a non-deterministic polynomial
time
to a machine
things we can guess
actually we can try all possible
boolean assignments
again you see you will see that uh
there if you have n boolean variables
okay let's say
if uh if the boolean formula
is like
n
okay the total length
and you have a lot of x or y and
something another something like that
but anyway
you
can collect the number
the number of boolean variables within
the formula right for example you have l
variables which is less than n
because n is the length
then you have you can construct a
machine to guess
all possible
choose assignment
to try all possible truth assignments
of course of course the width here
is exponential probably exponential to n
but it doesn't matter because we don't
count with
what we care about is height
right
and how many steps
you can guess one
you can
try one two assignment
about l steps which is less than n
so
then you verify
each choose assignment if it can be can
satisfy the formula
if any one of them
returns true you accept it and the whole
machine accepted
and the formula is in set otherwise if
all
computational branches reject then we
reject that string
okay
so apparently
sat itself is in np
then
any language a
in mp
we want to show any language a in np
there is a polynomial time reduction to
sat
okay so the key concept comes in here
since a is in mp
there is
a non-deterministic machine besides a
let's call it
n
okay
that's the definition of mp actually
then
since it is a non-deterministic turing
machine besides a
in polynomial time there must be
a constant a oh sorry k here a constant
k
and n here what is n here the input
length
so
the non-deterministic machine need
so much time
to decide a that's worst case okay worst
case scenario
so
let's do the reduction this way
for any language a
we get n which is the non-deterministic
decider for a
and then we know that
there must be some constant k for the
machine to run its worst case
okay
then we construct
on any input string for n
on any input string w for n we construct
nk
by nk
and to the kth power okay
nk by nk
table
then
what will this table do
we want to fill the table
with valid
computational history
of n
r w
okay that's the key concept
and how to
fill the blank here
how to fill the blank here
we define a lot of boolean variables
x
i
j
s
i is the row number okay and the j is
the column number
and s is all possible symbols
and what is all about all possible
symbols
from the turing machine you know
it states
and from w our two machines
alphabet you know
those
type symbols actually we want we want
this right and the blank
and the separator we added for our
purpose
okay
so all possible symbols include
state of the tuning machine
type alphabet of the turing machine and
you know you can add some finite extra
symbols for
convenience
so for each tape
for each blank here
we possibly
fill
these symbols
then we've defined
boolean variables this way
to represent
what symbol we want to field in for
example i and j
let's say if x i j
s let's say uh
blank
is true
that means we want to feel blank here
or x i j
um
[Music]
q 0
is true that means we want to fill q 0
here ok so it's pretty straightforward
we define a lot of boolean variables
the boolean variable to be false that
means we don't want to fill that symbol
into x i j
if that boolean variable x i j s is true
then that means we want to fill s into
rho i
column j
okay
then firstly
we want to
write a formula
boolean formula
so that
each blank exactly be written into
one symbol exactly one symbol
not
no symbol and not more than
one symbol
to make the table a table otherwise it's
not really a table right it's a
a mess actually
so
we define a boolean formula here
and for all possible
symbols
we or
these
boolean variables together
and
so for
row i
column j okay
for row i column j
imagine that
if
this formula to be true
okay
the other way if this formula is false
if this formula is false
that means we don't want to fill any
symbol into i j
right
that's not what we want we want to fill
symbols into i j so we have the formula
here
and if the formula evaluates true that
means at least the one symbol
will be filled into i j right
and of course two simple three symbol
doesn't matter all true
so we need another formula
to
make
the symbol i the blank i j exactly be
filled with
one symbol so we add this one
okay
it's kind of uh
complicated but it's
really really simple you see
for all possible
symbols
and as long as they are different
we
or
negation of x i
j s and x i j t
and then end them together
that means we pair each symbols
and then
we do the not
over and the end
then you you may probably
be confused with this but it's pretty
simple to understand
imagine that
for all the boolean variables
for all the boolean variables for i and
j for all possible symbols
if you have all fours
then what will happen
if all the boolean variables for i j
are false
that means
all these negations are true
right
and since all these negations are true
then you do or they are still true and
all the pair
are true so you do end still true
okay
so
if none of
the boolean variables for
i j
is true
then
if
none of the boolean variables are true
then this formula will be true
okay
then if one of the formula sorry one of
the variable is true others are false
let's say
if
a pair of two fours then it's true
and all the symbols there is one true
right
so let's say
x i oh sorry let's say
i
j
q 0
let's say it's true
others are false
so
x i j q 0 is true then x i j q 0 bar is
false
right so
but it doesn't matter
because
it will pair with
a true
literal because all other variables are
false right after negation they are true
and
only this one is true
so
it will be negated as force
so for all possible pairs they are all
true
now we know that if all the boolean
variables are false
then
this one is true and if one of the
variables
is true others are false this formula is
still
true
but
if for
all the variables there are two
true
the two variables are true others are
false
then the whole boolean formula will be
they evaluate force
why
because when the two
when the two variable
assigned true
pair together
and
be negated as false
and then
this one will be false
and exactly that pair
will make everything
false
okay
so that's why we write it this way
we use
this
formula
to ensure
there are
less or equal to one
boolean variable
be set to
true
and we use
this formula
to ensure
more
than one or equal to one
variable
to be set to
true then
we do an end
so
if you've got a formula here
if you are putting the assignment
satisfies this formula that means
for
i
row i
column j
only one symbol
is true others are all false
that will make us
feel in exactly one symbol
two
row i colon j on the table
okay
then
you just need a you know
double loop
from i
sorry i from 1 to
n to the k's power and j from 1 to the n
to the k power
then
you will have
a boolean
uh
formula a boolean formula
for cell
and you will know that you can know that
if
you have a boolean
assignment
satisfied
satisfied by sale
that assignment can be translated into a
table
in which
each blank is filled
exactly
with one symbol
okay
not no symbol not more than one symbol
exactly one symbol that's why we call
this formula by cell
and
understanding
how fine cells work
will help you a lot in understanding how
the whole proof work
because
we want to use the manipulation and
boolean variables actually put in truth
assignment
to
ensure
what we
filled in the whole in the whole table
okay
so
i guess time's up for this
for this part
so
we will continue
in next lecture