now let's trace the example of 3.7 m2
to
get ourselves familiar rice riced with
our two machines
let's see
with configurations and we can with
configurations and the diagram we can
trace
how the machine operates while
processing
string
for example
zero zero zero zero four
zeros
okay
so
the string
as usual starts
from the store state which is q1 of this
machine right
so
from and the uh assume that the
input string
is 0 0 0 0
which is supposed to be 1 of the
language a right because language a is 2
[Music]
sorry 0
2 to the nth power
and n equal to zero
something like that
right
so
that's our star
start conv uh
that's our
start configuration
and we see that
when
q1
with zero you will go
this direction
right
so
it will become
it will uh firstly the zero the first
zero here will be
changed to blank okay
and
q1 will be q2 and go
right
go right next time it will read
uh q
it will read zero the second zero right
and this blank here is the original zero
becomes blank
right goes to q2
so that's one step
okay
and interestingly uh
see that's also it's very uh the
this exactly transition here this
particular transition here is very
similar to
what we put dollar sign onto the stack
as the first step in pda it's a
programming skill
why because firstly we know that
blank
is not in
the input alphabet right that means
blank
is not a part of in you know that blank
is not a part of input string
and you change the first symbol to be
blank
basically you mark you try to mark the
start of the tape
if you go back to see the definition of
our turing machine you will know that
you
you will not know
when you were when the tape had
tap head is located
at the first
tab space
just like we don't know
the bottom of the stack
is the same it's not in the formal
description of the definition
okay
so as a programmer
we use some skills to you know to do
that so firstly we read the first zero
in this case and we change that to the
blank and we know that blank is not a
part of
input string so we can safely use blank
as a separator
or as
a boundary of the tape
and now
this machine reads the first
zero right it knows
it is the
uh it is a 0 1 0.
so that's a let's uh assume that
the input
the input has only one zero
let's assume that okay
so there will be no
this zero right
so if the input string is exactly
one zero
then there will be
okay let's go back a bit further that
if our input string is the empty string
right nothing
so the start configuration would be q1
blank right because there's nothing on
the
there's no
string of input symbols on the tape
right so that would be our
star configuration
so by this
what would we have we have this one
right
and
reject
right so the machine will
empty string
right
so
no problem in this case then
let's say
if our input string is 1 0
then after going to q 2 and change that
0 to blank
q 2 will encounter what blank right
because only 1 0
and when q2 encountered
blank
it will accept
right so this machine will accept
a string of one
zero
so
let's say
now
if we have two zeros okay let's go one
by one if we have two zeros
then it will be like this and here are
blank
and q2
will
read 0 which transition this one
right
so q2 reads 0 it becomes q3 so that's
why we have q3 here
and
the head
that's 0 will be marked read
marks red actually
then this x is the original zero here
and
q2 become q3 and the move
right
move right
and don't forget that we are assuming
that there are only two zeros so here
blank
right so the next step
q3 read blank
then we'll go left and on and
not change anything
and
so we will have
q3 becomes q channel c to q5 and the
position will be
[Music]
before x because we want to read x next
time
so for the machine states at q5 it will
read x and go to zero without changing
anything
so next time still q5
but position will be blank
right
and q5
blank
it will go
right
and it becomes q2
okay
so it will become
q2
sorry
it will
q5
blank right
and
it will become q2
and the q2 what will read
this x right
and
q to read x and the state
at q 2 and it goes right so we'll
go right again and here i'll blank
right then
blank
accept
so it will accept
zero
and two zeros
right
then let's
go further
so we if we have three zeros
okay
then
q1 read the first zero change to blank
and translate to q2
and the queue to read 0
marked 0x and change it to q3
right and the q3 read 0s
and three z read zeros is this one
right
then it becomes q a change transit to q
four
and not change zero to anything
and as soon as we have only three
0s here then q4 will encounters blank
when q4 encounters blank
it will reject
so see what we have now is
empty string reject one accept one as a
read one zero except two zeros accept
three zeros reject
right that's what we have now
then if we have five sorry four zeros
like this then we already goes here
right and when this step
q4 encounters zero
it will go back to
q3 okay go back to q3
go back to q3 then
mark the read
sorry mark the red 0 to x so this
this zero becomes x
that would be this one
okay
and
the head goes to
right so that's q3d here because q4
becomes q3
and see this blank that's our
uh special cases because you have
infinite blank
you just don't write it
now we have to write it because we want
to know that what is the next symbol
read by
uh what's the next symbol read by
the machine right so that would be blank
so q q 3 read blank
will go left without changing anything
so it will go to here
head will go to here and it becomes q5
so next time that will be
state q5 and x will be red
okay
so
as you can see q5 here it will skip any
zero and x and go keep going to
left
so you will go here
and then go here
and then
go
here
until this step
right
and
this step
at state q5
symbol blank symbol is red
so blank symbol is red it will become q2
and goes to right
so
goes to right that will be
in this position
and becomes q2
okay
so becomes q2 then
it will
skip every x
which is already processed
right skip x so
q 2 will go here
then
in this
state
in this configuration
when q 2 encounters 0 it will
mark the 0
right
and goes to q3
so mark the 0x
and
becomes q3 and the goal right
so will be this state
okay
then
q3 at q3
it will ignore any
processed symbol so
go this state become this one
and
when it's encounters blank it will go
left
when q3 encounters blank it knows we
know that it's the end of the tape okay
so go becomes q5 go
left and it becomes q5
and the q5 will do what skip o
x
and t o here
so that will be
this configuration
and then q5 read blank goes right and
change transit to q2 that would be this
blank at least configuration
right
and then q2 goes to
skip all process the symbol skip all
processes symbol
until here
and when q2 encounters
blank
it will
enter q accept
so
this machine will accept
a string of four
zeros
okay four zeros
okay so
compare the diagram here to
what we want to do
uh described by a bunch of text here
some major
steps include
sweep left to right across the tab
closing of every other zero
least
concept
is actually
implemented as
q3 and the q4 right
q3 and the q4 and the
initial step of q2
see
across a 0
that's we change 0 to x
and we change 0 to x
across
the tape and the change 0 to x
so that means that becomes q2 to q3
and close one x and the skip 1 0 cross 1
0 skip 1 0 cross 1 0
so
every other 0 is closed
during q3 q's 4 q3 q4
steps
and initi initiated by q2 goes to q3
so let's initiate q2
goes to q3 then
three four three four three four three
four three four imagine that you have a
lot of zeros
then somehow you got initiated by q2 and
goes to q3
and q3 will skip one zero
and q4 will cross one zero goes back to
q3
and let's keep one zero
close skip close
okay
and for any other for any
processed
zeros that will be
that will be uh skipped by q3 and q4
so when the symbols when the zeros on
the tab has been processed has been
processed by this these two one of these
two transition
it will never be
red again right you can see that
only
this transition and this transition
change 0 to x for all other transitions
on
our diagram there is no change of type
symbol right
and
for the major
uh state here
all processed the symbol
are
skipped
right
so any x on the type
they
are
seemingly
uh
this disappeared from the tape from the
scope of the machine
because
the machine never looked at x again
okay
so that's what
we have here
like
uh
sweep left to right across the tape
closing of every other zero that's what
it does it means
okay and
you can see that
for
the loop here closing zero and we
actually are
trying to
record uh
odd or even
of the number
of zeros
okay
uh we we we cannot uh use the state to
store to record the number
of zeros but we can use
state
to
count
the
identity of the number
we we know that uh it's
the uh
the number of residuals
is
even odd even art uh things like that
so you see uh after
marking the first zero
s blank
from
q1
to q2
okay
after this
we know that there's one zero here
right i mean initially initially
and then
we accept one zero right that's the one
zero part then if there are one more
zero
then
it will be marked x and goes to q3 and
you can think of q3 is
somewhat like a even
state okay we know there are even
numbers left on the tape
and then q4 is like odd state
you know not
odd but identity of the number of zeros
so even
uh
sorry
odds even
odd even odd even
that's why
if
at q4 you hit blank it will be rejected
because it knows it's even oh sorry it's
odd
and then so
more or less q3 represents like odd uh
zeros
so
if
when you hit
blank that's the end of the string
with q3 you know okay uh
now that the number of zeros left
remaining on the tab
is an even number then you go back
and doing over again
so you know even out even out this way
see that's the interesting part of
using
turing machine
to processing
strings
well
the design of this machine may be very
interesting and
usually we don't
directly design this level this
machine of this label okay that's just
uh
for
the purpose
of giving examples okay
okay uh let's see another example of 3.9
which is m1 you can see that it's
actually
uh
first example then the second one m2 we
just described and traced
okay for m1 which we use to
recognize okay actually deciding we will
see that again deciding a language b
as this one
that is you have some zero one string
and a separator here and a zero one
string and
string like this is in this language
like zero zero one 1 0
and separator
0 0 1 1 0.
and
as i uh
described it is very easy to prove that
this language
is
not even in context free language
because it's impossible for you to do
the same thing here okay you can do
things like this but not
this one because thick
you won't be able to do it via
using the
steak as the storage
okay anyway
so here is the example to
recognize in the uh for for this
language we have 16 16 states here
q1 q2 through q4 uh for 14 accept and
reject
and then the input input symbol you can
see that zero one and the separator so
three uh symbols for input symbols input
input alphabet and then
for uh type alphabet we have all
those in the input alphabet and then
one required by our theoretical
framework on
blank symbol and
something we want to use as
you know our own mark
so
we have uh states input symbol
input alphabet type alphabet star state
q accept q reject and the transition
function is
this one so
we
make the transition function index 116
state
but
so for the transition function
we didn't give
all state out right you see that
we have uh
according to the textbook we have some
for a state here but
not all of them shows on here
and
all for complete
uh for complete operations of the tuning
machine we need that but
to
accept all the strings
and
not accept
the string not in the language we only
need a transition like
what we have here
okay
so
let's trace the machine
with the input string we
had
in the beginning of the
chapter so when start with q1 right
with q1
and then
0 is read so you can see that
it will
go this way and
mark 0x right and goes right so next one
is like this and then
now we enter q2 so here we are in q1 and
at q1 and q2
and then
for q2 it will remain q2 and skip every
zero one okay skip every zero one
so it will
goes
here until here and then
goes to q4
so after
here is q2 but after this
after
going here will be q4 okay
and q4 will skip every x
that's that is uh
the symbol has been processed okay
and then
reach
it's originally
uh
reached 0 right so when q4 so so so this
one should be here okay
so not this one
when q4
match 0 and change to x change to x
and then goes to q6 and go back no
matter 0 or 1 or x
okay so you can see that 0 0
here
matched
so match the 0 with the 0
x and the then go back q6
go back until
the separator then goes to
goes
skip every
0 and 1
and then reach x so
when 7 reads
x
it goes back to q 1. okay so you can see
that
match 0
0 with
this path
and match 1 1 with
okay
so
finally
if
it goes through everything so
it will um
when q uh you when we when we enter q6
when you enter q6
will go
to the separator then
through everything
and the
cx go back to q1 right
so imagine that after
the x here
sum
this one or this one but
mark this one here then it will be q
going through this one until here and
change to q
7 right and q 7 will c x and go back
here to q 1
so that's why we have q1 read separator
then we change it
we change to q8
to check if there's anything wrong here
if no
q8 will reach the blank which is the end
of the string
right so accept
okay
so
as you can see
if
0 0
this way as i said and 1 1
this way
and if everything works out then here
here accept
okay
so imagine that
imagine that
if you have zero
here
and the skip through separator
what if at q4 you encounter one
right
okay let's see
actually we can uh
complete we can make the whole
uh turing machine complete with
everything
then you can go to reject and to reject
the string or something
okay but
for this
for the
partial machine here partial transition
function here you can find that
it is very interesting that
for this partial transition function
see
when as i said if you start with zero
and here you got one what happened
start from here then q4 you got one then
not defined right
and in
if
this is the whole if this uh
machine is the whole turing machine
then according to the acceptance
according to the acceptance
see this one
here
according to the definition
for two machine to accept
the input string
there
a sequence of configurations existing
the three conditions
must be must exist so we say that the
machine accept that string
and
for this for the
situation here
when
the machine is at q4 and encounter
one
then it's undefined okay
so we see that the machine
does not accept this string
however
for this state of the machine
we have to consider the machine is still
running
without accept the string and
without
reject the string it's just running and
running and running and with no answer
something like that
so it is important to see that uh
to see that the turing machine works
differently from final automata and
pda
for final automata
and pda we have accept
right
and we have
not accept
and for pda and the
final automata another accept is
basically reject no problem
because the machine anyway stops
when the input
input string is uh
the whole input string is processed so
we can also say that
the machine not a
pda nfa
dfa not accepting a string is rejecting
the string is no problem because the
machine stops
but for turing machine it doesn't work
that way
for tuning machine not accept
basically
is not reject because
if turing machine does not enter the
state of reject it doesn't reject the
machine
and if it doesn't enter
either reject or accept
we have to consider the machine
continues to operate
it is still running and we
cannot say that okay the stops no that's
why we call accepting configuration and
the rejecting configuration
holding configuration only
the machine enters
accept or reject state then we set the
machine holds
other than that we have to consider the
machine keep running keeps running
and never accept
you know have no answer for you
that's why
we need to
more precisely to describe the situation
here so
we firstly follow we firstly follow the
definition that
let's say
the collections of strings that's
turing machine accept
is the language of the machine m
or the language recognized by m denoted
l of m
okay so you can see that the definition
is exactly the same as we have for
final automata and the push down
automata
okay
so the language of some machine
is still the collection of strings that
machine
accepts
okay accept
then
if you can find a turing machine
recognize
some language
we call
that
turin recognizable
we call that language tune recognizable
okay so for this definition you can see
we defined that
if you can find some finite recognize
some language then we call that language
what
regular language
and for pda we call that context free
language of course we use that for
we we have to prove the equivalence
between context-free grammar and the pda
then we can do that but
it's quite straightforward to see
the
resemblance of the of these definitions
right
so
following the same definition
if there is a machine
and
l of m denotes the set
which said
the collection of strings that m accept
accept okay accept
so that's
accepts and we say that machine m
recognized this language and
any language recognized by turing
machine we say that the language is
tubulin recognizable
okay and for some ancient
pretty old
terminology we also call it
recursively innumerable
innumerable language sometimes you can
see r dot e dot
or r e
in other textbooks not a regular
language but recursively in your
innumerable language
right
and we just said that we just described
that for two machines there are actually
another situation that for a string
the machine
does not
reject that string
but the machine keep running and without
giving give give you any answers
you can consider the machine
as in an infinite loop or stuff like
that
and in that case
we have an other definition for
a more
for our concept it's more uh
restricted definition that
let's use the example
for alphabet it's all possible strings
sigma star right
and let's say
for the
give you a if there's a machine here
and then
the language accepted by this machine we
call fm and if a language can be found
recognized recognized by some two
machine we call alpha m2 recognizable
that's no problem here
the problem we want to
describe more precisely here is that for
strings outside of
l of m all right
for strings outside of l of m
for example this string
if you give m
you make n process it
and
it is possible that m rejected
okay that's possible
and also possible that n gives no answer
just keep looping and
no answer forever
so
for the string outside of
l of m
for turing machine there
are possibly two results
so here we give a more restricted
different definition that
if the language here
or if the turing machine you have
can accept all the string it accept
and
reject
all the string not in l of m
that means
for the for all the string outside of
error of m
and
reject
there is no if there is no
infinite loop situation here we call
that
the language is turing decidable or
simply decidable
and we call this action decide
okay decide
so again
if
there is a language
and you can find a tool machine to
recognize it
that means
lateral machine can accept
all the strings in that language
okay
and such a definition is identical to
those we have for
final automata and the pdas or yeah
context-free languages
we use recognize
for that purpose
but for two machines there are
slightly more
complicated
because for the you see for pdas or dfas
nfas
the string outside of l of n
those machine eventually stops and
always stops and
you know it's not accepted it does not
accept the string
means it rejects the string but for tool
machine
there is a possibility that the machine
goes into an infinite loop
and without giving answers
okay
so we
have one more definition for that uh to
describe a language more precisely that
we say that a language is turin
decidable or simply decidable
if we found we can we know some tuning
machine decides the language what means
decides the language
besides the language means the machine
will accept all the string in the
language
and
reject
all the strings outside of the language
for all possible strings for all
possible strings
there is no string
given
uh feeding into the machine and that you
don't get answer you don't get either
reject or accept there's no such string
okay so you can think of that if a
machine always
stops and give you
yes
we accept or no reject answer
then we say that the machine decides
that language
and if the machine is a tool machine we
say that that language is a
turin-decidable language or simply that
language is a decidable language
okay
so again recognize recognize means
a machine recognizer language means for
that language every string in that
language
will be accepted by the machine every
string in that language well
not accepted by that
machine
and again
there's no problem for pda and the dfa
because they always stop and if they
don't accept the string you can consider
they reject that string so there's no
problem for those two types of of
machines but for two machine there's a
slightly diff it's slightly different
because for two machine it is par it is
possible for
uh the machine goes into a you know
infinite loop if we consider it that way
and
that's why we need
a
more restricted definition
to clearly separate
recognize
and decides
okay so design means that every string
not
in
the
language will be rejected
but recognize
it's not necessary that
if you give the machine
a string in a language you will get
accept
accepted
if you give the machine a string outside
of the language you either get rejected
or
you will have no answer and the machine
will never
give you answer
okay
so that's the
uh that's different for the case of
turing
machine and
for also an ancient terminology
for decidable languages
and
it was called it was called
recursive language
okay recursive language because there
was a time
mathematicians use
recursive recursion to consider
computation so
they already identified similar
uh set
as we well introduced and they use
different
terminology terminologies for that
because
they are originated from different
you know
thinkings and the concepts
so sometimes
you will see recursive language that
means decidable or too indecidable
and you will find the tune machine
decides besides that language
okay
so
let's go back to the example so actually
this language
this
language
can be easily decidable right because
you can write a machine to you know just
check if not
if the string pass the check then
accept otherwise reject so that's why
the example described
we can have a two machine for deciding
the language okay
although
the partial machine displayed here
is not a decider
it this machine partial machine
is only a recognizer okay it can accept
all strings
in
this language
it can accept
i shouldn't say
all string in this language
but it will not reject any string
and also
that this partial machine has no uh
reject state it will never enter reject
so you must con we must consider by
definition the machine is always
running and without giving any
answers
it's quite easy to imagine for
you know using our common regular
computer
there are times that you don't know if
the app
is still calculating doing computation
or just you know going somewhere you
don't know and you will never have
answers
but you have no way to
determine
which situation it is something like
that
anyway so
this partial machine is merely a
recognizer because any string in that
language can be accepted and any string
not in that language will not be
accepted
and will not be rejected so
then for this example
we also describe that machine m2 decides
see
that's where
decides the the verb decides has been
used
besides a
the language here
because any string
in
0 star
right because
a is a substring of
0 star
right
and any string in 0 star
processed by this machine
you will get
like
reject right we have we have already
described that
and 1 0 accept 2 0 accept 3d row
reject 4 0
accept
and so on
of course we are not trying to prove
that the machine decides that language
but at least we have traced the machine
for these cases right
so you know that for every
string this machine will give a give an
answer either reject or
accept
so that's why
we describe that machine m2 besides
a instead of recognize a
okay instead of recognizing
and also by the definition here
let's say tune recognizable and
decidable
what is recognizable let's say a
language you can find a recognizer to
your machine recognizer right and the
decidable is that
a language you can find a tuning machine
as a decider
and by definition you'll know that
decider has
we have one more criteria criteria for
decider
right
decider have to reject strings outside
the language
so by the
way we define the whole thing we know
that
decidable language let's say decidable
languages that is
all the language in decidable language
uh this this class you can find too
machine to decide it
and a
language is decidable it is recognizable
right because you can discard the
answers from the reject part and that
machine is automatically by definition a
recognizer
so
decidable must be a subset of
recognizable
so there are two possibilities for
the two class
one is that
decidable
and recognizable
is the same class
and the other is that
decidable
and recognizable
are
like this decidable is a proper subset
of the site are recognizable
in this case in the
right
the in the case of on the right hand
side there must be some languages
here right so that's
so so that decidable
is
a proper subset of recognizable
otherwise it should be the same
okay
so
later we will try to know which one
is the uh is what we encountered
so uh
that uh that's the
from the definition we know
either this one or this one
okay