in chapter 3 we introduced and defined
two machines and then in chapter 4
we
mainly discussed
decidability of languages
right
and also we introduced the
relationship
among classes of languages
and as as shown
in figure
4.10 and that's probably about what we
were talking
in this semester will be covered by this
course
there are
actually more
uh classes of languages and their higher
hierarchy is more complicated but we
will not cover that in the semester
and in this chapter chapter 5 we will be
talking about
reducibility
and
let me put it first
when we talk about reducibility
we are not talking about
solving problems
we will not
propose solutions to problems
or in train machine terminology
we will not propose decider or
recognizer two languages
and what is reducibility reducibility is
about using a solution
to some problem
to solve
another problem
okay
so
let's see the description here
if problem a
reduces to problem b
we can use solution to b
to solve a
okay so imagine that you have a problem
a
and you have a problem b
and you already know some solution to b
that means you can solve b you have a
way
a procedure or something else to solve b
and
if you can use that solution to solve a
we said
we will say that
problem a reduces
to problem b
okay
and most importantly
reducibility says
nothing
about solving a or b alone
okay that's very important
because
if you
want to solve
let's say a or b alone
you'll miss the point of root of
reducibility
and also that
don't
don't consider the word reduce
make problem a
easier
no
it's not like that
okay if you look up in the dictionary
reduce may have some
you know make it smaller or some meaning
similar to that but
i suggest you
not to think about the word reduce
or reduction or deductible reducibility
in this chapter that way
you should consider reduce in this
chapter
just like
change to transform to
[Music]
another way to describe that or
something like that okay
there is nothing regarding making the
problem easier because we will never be
able to make a problem easier
that's the key point of the
in this room in this chapter
so
again
let's say
if problem a
reduces to problem b
that means we can use solution
to b
to solve a
and
we are not uh inventing
some way to solve a alone
and
the solution to be
is not is it's
it is not proposed
here either okay
so when a is reducible to b
okay that means a can be reduced to b
we know that
solving a
cannot be harder than solving b
because
solution to b
gives a solution to
a
right
so the difficulty imagine that the
difficulty
to
solving a
is is at most
the difficulty to solving b
because you can use the solution to b to
solve a right
so in this sense
we can say that
if
a is reducible to b
we know that
if you already know that b is decidable
since b is decidable and you can use the
solution to be to solve a
so
a is decidable
or
in the reverse direction
if you already know that a is
undecidable
and somehow solving b can solve a
you know that
b must be undecidable too
okay so a
is reducible to b you know solving a
cannot be harder than solving b
by this sense we can in
we can
say that if you already know a b is
decidable
then you know a is decidable on the
other hand if
a is already undecidable
then b must be undecidable
so
according to this kind of
according to this way of thinking
we can start to prove
other
undecidable languages now
see we have now
one oh well actually more than one
because unrecognizable languages are
undecidable because they are harder than
design undecidable right
but for recognizable
decidable we have only one atm
so
if you can find
some
language
which is which
of which
the solution to which the solution can
be used to solve atn
then we already know atm is undecidable
so that's language is undecidable
again
if you find
some language
to which the solution
can be used to solve atm
and we already know atm is undecidable
we can prove that
the language we are talking about right
now is undecidable too
okay so that's what we want to do
okay
so
the first language you want to prove is
that
hot tm is
hot tm is undecidable
okay so what is whole tm here by the
definition used in the textbook we can
say that hot tm
is that you have a tool machine and the
input for that turing machine
and the tuning machine holds on the
input
okay
then what is the holding configuration
it
holding con
configurations include
accepting configuration and rejecting
configuration right
so
m either
accepts
w or rejects w
we both we call the uh we call both the
situation hot
and hot here means
if
if a turing machine holds um
input w
all these kind of string is in the
language
and we want to prove that whole tien is
undecidable
means
there can be no decider for hot tm
okay
so according to what we are talking
about uh
here
if a is revisible to b
and you know a is undecidable b is
undecidable
so we want to prove that
we want to prove that
whole tn is undecidable
since we want to prove pro tm is
undecidable
we want we want to use the solution to
hold tn to construct the solution to atm
right
so
assume that there is a decider r
for hot tn exist
that is the solution to hot tm
okay
so solution oh sorry solution to hot tn
we use solution to
hot tien which is the
assumed to be exist to exist
decider r besides otn
so based on the solution here we
construct turing machine s
and what are we doing
on input mw
where
m is a turing machine and a w is a
string
for the two machine as input
we run r
because r exists right we arm we run r
on input mw
if r rejects
that means
and
wrong on w
will
what enters some
uh some
some condition in which
and runs forever
right maybe loops
uh maybe infinite loop or you know going
somewhere not repeatedly but
never ends never stops
so
we know
m on w will never stops
so
hold tn the decider r for whole t n
tells us this
so
s just need to reject
so what x what our s reject
s reject
the input here
because
m will not accept w
and also we know that m will run forever
right
if r accepts
then we know that eventually m on w will
hold
will hold right so we
can
[Music]
simulate m on w safely because we know
it will stop
until it holds
and
since m on w will hold
if m accept w
s accept its own input which is the pair
here
or and reject
s reject its input
mw pair as a string
right
so for the turing machine here you can
know that as
the true machine s we just constructed
here
can decide atm
it's atm's decider okay so we
successfully use the solution to b which
is r
as whole tm decider
to construct solution to a
and clearly if
clearly
we know that
atm's decider
cannot exist
right
so
the construction comes from assuming r
exists which is whole tm decider
so hot tm
must be undecidable
okay
so in the concept
we previous we we just described that we
use
the
solution to hold tn to solve
atn
and we know that atn cannot be solved so
otm is undecidable
but for the proof here what we use is
proved by contradiction
and the constructive contradiction
raised in the assumption
of the existence of whole tm's decider
okay
so if whole tms decider exists then we
can construct atm decider but we already
proved that atm cannot have a decider so
host hold decider for whole tm cannot
exist
so we proved that
hot tm
is undecidable
okay
so the concept is
here
although the proof technique we
we were using is proof by contradiction
okay let's practice more
so
we can also prove that e t n is
undecidable
okay
so the whole thing repeat again just
different construction
we assume that
etn decider r exists
so we use the solution to etn which is
the decider r
for etn
to solve
atn
so we reduce atm to etn
and we already know atm is undecidable
so
etm must be
undecidable that's the
concept okay so
again
assuming that
etm
decider
r
exists
okay that's the solution
to etn
now we use that solution to to solve atm
okay
how do we do that firstly
we
design a turing machine m1
okay
so m1 input x
and we put
a blank
here
a blank here
and also a blank here
so m1 and here sorry and the m1 is a
is a is an
incomplete
program
it's a program with
some
blank for you to fill in after fill in
you will you will get
a complete program
but before that it's not a complete
program it cannot run along okay and
we've seen this construction before
for
proving every
context free language to be decidable
right we have some
uh
some incomplete program for you to fill
in some blank
okay
so anyway
for the input of
m1
it will be
it will compare the input string with
with some particular string let's say w
if they are not then reject
they are not identical then reject
so
you can see that for all possible
strings
for all possible strings
as long as x is not some particular
string that will be filled in
will be rejected so the only string that
may be accepted by m1 is some
input is some string w which hasn't been
written into the program okay anyway
so if x is w
then we will run m which will be filled
in
on w
since in this case uh condition m and x
and w is the same string so it doesn't
matter to write which one
and if x if accept
sorry
if m
accept w
then m1 accepts its input
which is also w here
right
but
m and w
are
blank for now
we don't know what they are right now
okay
then we construct
tuning machine s here
okay
so as here it it is
supposed to be the decider for atm
so on
mw where m is a turing machine program
as w is a input string
we
put m
and w
into
m1 okay
so
after we have m and w
we filled in m and w into m1 so now m1
is a complete program
right
then
we use m1 as the input to
r
okay we use that m1
as the input and fit it into r and we
draw
r
and
what is r r is the decider for etn
okay
since r is the decider for etn and what
is m1
so let's say now we have m and w
so what will m1
do
m1 will reject
all strings
m1 will reject all strings
not equal to w
right
and you see
if w is
m1's input
m1 will simulate m on w
so
when you do
wrong and on input w you will get three
possible
right
one
runs forever
right
or infinite loop if you will
two
and
accept
w
three
and reject
sorry
w
now
if
m runs forever
m1 runs forever then m1 will not accept
w right
or
in that case
x because x is w in this case so you see
m1 definitely rejects
all strings except for w
and
if the input is exactly w then m1 will
run m on input w
and when
m1 run m on input w and it runs forever
and one will run forever and will not we
accept w
so in this case l of m1
is empty set
right because it already rejects any
string
other than w
and for w it will run n
and if m
on the input w runs forever then of
course m1 will not accept any string so
the language recognized by m1 is empty
set
or
m reject w
and since our description does not
contain
a
you know
halt situation it does not reject
so and uh we also it does not accept
that string
so in this case
l of m1 is still
empty
empty set why because m1 does not
accept stop
accept any string in this case
it's undefined here right
only that
if m does accepts w then m1 accepts its
input string which is w2 right
so in this case
ll of m
is
a language contains only one string
which is w
and therefore it's not empty set
right
so back to the step two here when we run
r
on input m input m1
r will let us know
it's
this case over this case
right
so if r accepts
and
don't forget that what is r
r is the h etm decider
so when r accepts m1 that means
l of
m1
is mt set
right
and we know that
either this case
or this case
means and
will not
accept
w
right
we as a atm designer we need to reject
our input here
on the other hand if r
rejects
that means and l of m one
is not
empty set
then we know
c
m accepts w
so as
the atm designer
s
accepts its own
input which is mw pair
so
with help
of m1
we
construct atm decider as
this to machine
so for the reduction
we use
the solution to etm
to solve
atn
since we know atm is undecidable
etm is undecidable
and we actually finish the proof by
contradiction
how to
obtain the contradiction
because we assume that
etm's decider r exists
and then
we
by using r we construct
atm decider s
and the construction of
s here
has no
particular technical difficulty right
everything we can do
within the capability of turing machine
so
that means
we successfully construct
atms decider
but
we already know that
a decider for atn cannot
exist so we know that the contradiction
comes from the assumption of the
existence of
decider for etn
so etm decider cannot
exist
so we know that etm must be undecidable
okay
so
we proved this theorem
we proved that etm is undecidable
okay
next one
we want to prove that a regular tm is
undecided undecidable too
with the same proof
structure so what is regular tm as the
naming convention
regular
tn means that all the turing machine
of which the language
is a regular language
okay
since we have introduced the
relationship among classes of languages
we know that a regular is
within
the capability of turing machine right
so there must be turing machines
recognizing
regular languages
so if we define that all the turing
machines that recognize regular
languages is in the set
is it possible for us to write to design
a turing machine
for the input as a turing machine to
determine
whether or not the given to a machine
recognizing a regular language
okay so now we want to prove that
it is impossible
it is impossible for us to write
to design artillery machine to determine
whether or not a given turing machine
recognizing a regular language okay
so
we want to uh use the same
proof structure so
uh
assume that
there is a decider r for regular tn
we want to use
r the solution to problem b
to solve problem a
and we already know that atm is
undecidable therefore
regular tm is undecidable that's what we
want to do
and the whole proof
is much like the one for etn so let's
just
prove it
so we assume that r is the
solution to regular tm which is the
decider for this language
and then
we construct
s
as atm's decider so the input for s is
a turing machine and
a string
as the input of that turing machine
and we construct
m2 here
the row of m2 is like the row of m1 in
the proof of etn
this undesirability of edm
so
m2 on its own input
it firstly check
if the input
if the input has the form of
this
if so accept
okay
so let's see
for step one
no matter what
m or w is
no matter what the pair is
n2 always
out of all possible strings
and to always
accept
accept string
like this one
okay
this language
the strings in this language will always
be accepted by m2 okay
then
outside the language outside of the
language
m2 will run m
on w
then to see
if m accepts w
m2 will accept its own input what is its
own input we don't know we just know
that here
the input may be any string outside of
that language right
now
you can find
we
actually use
n on w
as a switch
okay
if m
accept w
then what will our m2 recognize what
language will our m2 recognize
no matter
m
accept w or
or not
m2 always accepts all strings
in
this
language right
if and
accept w
and to well
accept string from
will also accept string from outside of
the language that is l of m2
is all possible strings
right
because it will
also accept string outside of the
language
if n
does not
does not accept w
then m2 recognize
this language
then m2
recognized only the strings in this
language
that is it recognize this language
right
so
it becomes a switch
to switch the behavior of m2 as
this language recognizing this or this
language
so
if
m
accept w
and to well
when m2 will recognize
will recognize a regular language which
is sigma star
if m does not
accept w either rejects or runs forever
m2 will recognize this language which is
not
a regular language
so we just need to put the source code
m2 as the input of the decider for
regular tm which
we assume
its existence
right
so if
regular tms decider accept that means
it is
this case
then we know m accept w so
atm decider accept accept what
the
machine string pair
if r rejects
then we reject
okay
so s here
is the
atms decider
and we use solution to regular tm to
solve
atm
however we know that
atm's decider cannot exist so regular
tms decider cannot exist
so we conclude that
regular tn is undecidable because
if the decider of regular tm exists
there will be definitely a contradiction
okay
then
did you see
or
do you see
the similarity of these two proof
that is
we use a machine
and we design a switch
to switch the machine's behavior
then we assume
some language
is decidable
then that's decider can help us
to decide atm
okay
so by abstracting such
this kind of proof we can
prove
rice theorem
that is we can prove
all together a lot of languages to be
undecidable at the same time
we want to prove that
the previous proof structure can also be
used to do
similar things
to prove the undecidability of many
languages
okay
so
let's define the first so that p
be any non-trivial property of the
language of a turing machine
okay
and the property just
you know just uh it's just a language
property is just a language
consisting of turing machine
descriptions
and you can see that etn
or regular tm
this kind of language
the string of
in the language
is turing machine descriptions or you
can consider them as you know programs
like java programs the program doesn't
matter
so property is just a set of programs
you can think of consider it as that
and
if such a language
fulfills satisfies two conditions
first non-trivial
what is non-trivial
it is very easy that
as long as it contains
it contains some but not all turing
machine descriptions that's what we call
con uh noun trivial so if you have a
property
contains no machines which is empty set
right then that's trivial
it's trivial tribute right
and the other cases of trivial is that
you define
a set of two machine description
contains
all possible turing machines then that's
also trivial because you have all two
machines there's no
problem to decide whether or not a given
tier machine is in the set because it is
right and the previous case is that is
the machine it not said no it's not
because
your set is empty so either empty or
contains all possible two machines they
are trivial otherwise
as long as
the property we are talking about
is non-empty
and also
not all two machines then it's
non-trivial okay so that contains uh
there will be a lot of
uh properties non-trivial right
and the second one is that the property
must be determined by
the language recognized
of that turing machine
okay
and as long as
as long as two
turing machine recognizing the same
language
they must be
in
the property together
or out of the property together
okay in the property together out or out
of property together so let's look at
the previous example so regular tm
does the language of regular tm that's
regular tn fulfill the two condition
yes
it is
why because firstly
firstly
there is
actually there are
turing machines
recognizing regular languages right
that's no problem so it contains
two machines it it is non-empty
on the other hand
thus regular tn contains all possible
two machines
of course not
right there are two machines recognizing
non-regular language
even non-context-free language right
so
regular tm is non-trivial because
it contains some but not all
to machines
and
for the second
condition
if a regular language that say a regular
language a
and we can
surely know that if there is a machine
m1
recognizing a
and
also an other turing machine m2
recognizing the same language
they are both in
regular tn
right
or you have a
regular uh turing machine m a
recognizing let's say
a noun regular language
and all the machines
recognizing the same language they are
out they are not in regular tn
right so
regular tn fulfill that
uh that two con those two conditions
and
then the same situation goes to etn
right there are two machines
recognizing empty set
and also two machines not recognizing
empty set so it's non-trivial
and
all
actually all turing machines in the set
recognizing exactly the same language
which is empty set as long as your
machine
that's
as long as a machine does not
recognize empty set they are not in etm
so it fulfills the
second conditions too
right
and
you may ask okay so what kind of
property
uh
or what kind of turing machine
set
does not
fulfill the
second
condition it's quite easy if you define
a turing machine
set
let's say a turing machine set
and m is a tn
okay
and n has
uh let's say 100
states
okay can we do that yes we can we can
say that okay i have a set of two
machine description of which
all the two machines has
exactly 100
okay so that's a tuning machine set
however this two machine set does not
fulfill the second condition because if
you have an
m1
in the
set and you know the language
recognizing by m1 then you add one
more useless
state
which will never be going to and out of
the states so you create m2
since that state
is useless
so the language of these two machine
will be identical however since m2 has
101 states it's not in a okay
so
this kind of
definition
of turing machines that it does not
fulfill the second condition
okay so
if we have a property
fulfills the true condition
then we can prove that
such
a such set of turing machines
is an
undecidable language
okay
all
properties satisfying the two conditions
here
are
undecidable we can prove them all
together
okay
and the proof is
straightforward if you
consider what we already have for etm
and regular tm
let's say
firstly we assume that p is a decidable
language okay
because we want to do
the proof by contradiction so we uh
assume that p is undecided sorry
decidable so there will be a decider rp
decides p decides p
right
and then we construct
atms decider by using rp here as what we
did for etm and regular tn
okay firstly
with that a regular artery machine t
uh
empty set
be a turing machine that always rejects
that means
l of t
l of t empty is empty set
now we assume that
this turing machine
is not in p
okay without loss of generality
why can we do that
because if language
is decidable
the complement of that language is
decidable too
right because
if a language is decidable then you have
a decider for the language
then you just need to
change
the accept state and reject state to
create
the decider for
the complement of that language
that's why
if you have a language which is
decidable the complement of that
language is also decidable
okay
so
now
if we want we since we assume p is
decidable
then p bar is assumed to be decidable
too right
so let's see
the machine recognizing empty set
in p
over p bar if it is in p
then
we consider
p-bar
that means we consider
the language we consider the language
which contains
no
turing machine recognizing empty set
okay
so if you want to apply
rice theorem which we are going to prove
to regular tn and etn
we
actually are proving
e t m bar
or
regular tm bar
undecidable
okay if you directly use rice tea rice
theorem to prove
regular tm or etm we are actually
proving etm bar undecidable and regular
tm bar undecidable
since etm bar is undecidable so etm is
undecidable and the same goes to regular
tier
okay so
you have to be uh
we have to be clear about that so some
of you may think of it's weird because
uh
turing machine recognizing empty set is
in etn it's actually etm right and in
regular tm so how can you apply rice
theorem actually we if you apply rice
theorem we are talking about etm bar
undecidable and regular t and bar
undecidable
okay
so we assume that
the lang the machine recognizing empty
set not in p
okay because you you can proceed p bar
with p bar instead of p
because p is non-trivial
then
we can
get
one
turing machine out of p because there
are two machines in p right we just get
one out of it any one and you know that
the one recognizing empty set is not in
p so any machine you get from p
will
not
be recognizing
empty set that's important okay
then we construct
atm decider
to distinguish
between the machine recognizing empty
set or the machine recognizing
some
[Music]
language
for the property
defined by that property
okay which will definitely be not empty
that's what we want to do here
so the construction process is easy you
have already uh
look at etm and regular tm just reverse
okay not reverse
very similar to that
so
the decider for atn
on the input
of the machine input pair
we construct a turing machine mw
like
this one
so for its own input string
no matter what
mw will simulate m on w
okay
so as long as we do n on w there are
three possibilities right
first one
runs forever
right first one runs forever so if mw
gets stuck on
this step
and w
will be
recognizing empty set right because
no matter which string is the input
string
the first step of m on w of m w
is to simulate m on w and get stuck
so it will never accept any string so
it's recognizing empty set
okay so that's the first situation
the second situation is that
m reject w
it holds and reject
so if it holds and reject
then we do reject
and remember that this reject reject
any
input string of nw so
for the second okay this is the first
one this is the second one for the
second situation
also recognizing empty sets
okay
then the third
situation is n accept w so if accept
we do the
second step here
then mw simulates t
which we get from p right
which we get from p on its own input
then we just see what
t
will do and mw will do what t will do so
three
well what
language of mw will be language of t
will be
not
empty there
right
then we just need to
use rp
and
let's mw
be
the input of rp
since
empty set is not in p
if rp say yes
rp say yes that means
lo of mw
is lo of t
is
not empty set and we know m
accept w
since n accept w
s as a decider for atm s do
accept
okay
otherwise if
says no
that means
m
error of mw is empty set
and empty set is not in p so
we do a reject
we don't know
it is situation one or two we don't know
we don't know if m on w runs forever or
every jw we know that
mw recognizing empty set and we know
that m does not accept w
and
as atm's decider we reject
our input
okay
so the key point is also that we use
whether or not and access w as a switch
to change the behavior to determine the
behavior of
the machine here the machine mw here
and
that's the
decider for that
language
assume to be existence the decider
to
to determine whether or not the mw
in or out of the property
so
this one is wrong here so that would be
m w
okay
therefore if m uh therefore m w is in p
if and only if
m accept w
okay
so
we know that atm decider cannot be
cannot exist right
so
as long as the decider flow
p
exists
atm designer can be constructed so
you know p must be undecidable
so that's right theorem
you can also see that we modulize the
proof
and you just need to
change some
let's say module like this one then you
can prove all
properties all turing machine
description sets
having uh fulfilling the two conditions
these are undecidable okay so that's
right there
so you can
easily
define that let's say
since
since we know that every context free
language is a decidable language so if
you
uh if you uh define a turing machine
description set like cfl to machine set
is that
all turing machine
m is a tn
and recognizing context free language
then you know that by using rice theorem
it is decidable why because firstly it
is non-trivial
there are two machines recognizing
context free language and there there
are
material machines that
not recognizing contextual language
firstly and secondly
recognizing same language will be both
in all o2 machine recognizing a language
will be
in the in
this language or out of this language so
the second conditions are fulfilled
then we know it is
this this is undecidable
and
for this particular instance we actually
use
uh
rice theoren to prove
cfltm bar on undecidable
okay
that's why because
empty set is a
context free language
okay
and we can do that
we can
uh prove a lot of languages regarding
turing machine
descriptions or programs
together so that means
in practice it may be very difficult for
you to write a program to determine
other programs behavior something like
that
and
but there are still other
languages that cannot be
proven
either decidable or undecidable by rice
theorem for example
if we do eqtm here
what is eqtn
as our naming convention we got two
machines they are turing machines and
their language
is the same
okay their language
so apparently we cannot apply
rice theorem on this language because
it's not fulfill the requirements of
rice theorem okay so now we want to
prove it
directly but with the similar technique
for
etm and regular tn
we assume a decider for eqtn
exists
so eqtm is now b
right problem b
we use the solution to problem b
and construct solution to problem a
the problem a now is etm
okay
if we can do the reduction like this
then
since we already know etm is undecidable
eqtn is undecidable
okay so what we do the same by
contradiction
we
assume that etm's decider r
exists
then we construct decider for etn
okay
so
until machine m
we firstly
build a turing machine m1
and error of m1
is empty set okay
it's described as rejects all inputs
which is recognizing empty set
so we can write down m1
our hard code m1 in
our
program and then we copy the input into
here and
use the whole thing as input to ask the
decider of
eqtn right and as long as equity n tells
us accept
what does that mean the amine error of m
and l of m1
are identical
and we already know of m1 is you know
empty set so we know and
recognizing empty set so we
accept
because as now
here
is the decider for etm
otherwise if the decider for eqtm
rejects that means error of m
and fm1 recognizing different languages
and we know that error of m1 recognizing
empty set so that would be not
empty the language here is not empty so
we reject
and it's not in
etm
see so that the behavior of s here is
definitely
a decider for etm
since we know that
etm's decider cannot
exist
and so we got a contradiction and the
contradiction here is
caused by the existence of eqtms decider
so eqtm must be undecidable
okay so the same
we use the solution to be to solve a and
we know a is undecidable then b is
undecidable because a contradiction
can be obtained
okay