okay let's give some examples of
problems in p
we want to describe aggregates with
numbered stages for analysis
if we can establish that
a polynomial upper bound under
on the number of stages
exist
and
we know that
the
individual stages can be run in
polynomial time
since
the polynomial of a polynomial is still
a polynomial we can conclude that that
algorithm runs in
time of point uh
runs in
polynomial time okay
then we prove that that problem the
algorithm handles
is in p
okay
and here we have to
note that we need to use reasonable
encoding method
for the input
we put on the tape of two machines such
as that we use
base k
for any k
equal to or greater than 2 for integers
if you if you use base 1 that means to
represent like
five
you need to have one symbol let's say a
a
two represent five right it is an
unreasonable representation because we
have much better
uh representation much shorter
representation right as long as you use
a base
greater or equal to 2 for example 2
you only need to use log 2
of 5 plus 1 bit
or symbols or
spaces of tapes
to represent 5
that's much shorter than use base 1
representation
so remember that we need to use
reasonable encodings reasonable
representation for the input of uh two
machine uh sorry for the input that we
want to put on the three machine type
okay so that's very important for the
uh
for the computation for the calculation
here
so the first example we want to give is
the
is path okay past
so what is path
we have
a directed graph
which is g
and
we specify
the starting point s and the endpoint t
so that's how we represent it on the uh
as the turing machine input on the tape
you encode
a graph and specify the starting point
and also the ending endpoint
okay
to prove
to prove that
the language or the problem path is in p
we need to have an algorithm which can
correctly handle
the problem
or
decide the language right as in the
turing machine terminology we want to
have an algorithm to decide that
language
and we want to say that
the algorithm which is represented by a
tuning machine
runs in polynomial time
okay that's our purpose
so
here
uh
for visualization of a problem graph we
can say that given a graph g you have uh
you have some
verdicts and also edges and since it's
since the graph we are talking about is
a direct graph
the h is directed h right over arc and
you specify some
starting point and
end point so
if the given directive graph and the
specified snt
there is a
path directly to pass from s to t on
g
then
such input string is in path otherwise
it's not
okay otherwise it's not
so
firstly can we have a turing machine to
decide this language
okay
and apparently we can right and let's
let's see how the high level description
of the turing machine handle the problem
okay so
on input graph
s and t
where
the graph is at the vector graph and
s is the starting node and the key is
the end node right
so that the first
uh
that's
imagine that
on the two machine type you have
but what do you have here
you will have uh
at least some
verdicts here like uh
vertex 1
vertex 2
vertex 3
etc right
and then let's say we use comma to
separate the vertex and h then you have
some
uh
notation for
representing the uh directed edge here
for example we use
may we
we can probably use like
uh v1
v2 means you have h from v1 to v2 okay
then
v1
v4 for example
and you have a lot of h here
then
let's say it's a
it's the graph okay
okay
one more for something like that then
you specify s
let's say v4
and
t
like v
one something like this
okay so
that's the tape
so
you have two machine you have tape on
the type is your input you input
consists of a directed graph and a node
snt
okay
so first
first stage of the turing machine is
that we place a mark on node s
and you will say what is a mark well you
can prepare two versions of the symbols
right
so the mark may just think that you have
another version of like v4 here but i
shouldn't say ah okay that's b4 here
okay
so you change e4 to e for
that something like that okay that's
just a uh turing machine programming
skill
we mark d4 here then
we repeat
we repeat uh
the stage two three
okay
we scan all ages of g so we scan o h
of g
and as long as
an h a b
is found going from a marked node a
to n unmarked note b
we mark b
okay
so for example we scan b1 b2 and then we
scan okay
b1 and go back
to scan v1 v1
is not marked so we skip v1 v2
and we scan v1 b4 and etc for example if
we scan v4
v2
and
b4
is marked right
then we change
v2
as a marked
node
then we do we repeat the whole thing for
every ages in g
okay
then we repeat
again until
no additional notes
okay
so every if we scan
the h once
and the sum nodes
are marked during the process we need to
do the skin again
if some nodes are marked then we will do
that again until
first
for
a complete scan
after a complete scan we don't have
new
marked node then we stop
okay
after we stop we check if t
is marked
if it is marked then accept
reject
okay
so for the description you can know that
what does the algorithm do
it actually doing the something like
this
we mark s first
right
then we check all the notes sorry all
the edges okay we check this edge okay
uh i don't know what that is and we
check this edge we check this age we
check this age we check this edge and we
check this edge oh it
from s and s is marked then we mark this
node
for the same reason we mark this node
right
for so for this run we actually mark two
more nodes
it's s is marked as stage one
and for the first round of ages we
mark one more and two more
right
then you scan all the edges again right
and when you after you scan all the
edges again
in this case we will mark this
this node
a new node after scanning and then a new
node and then a new node and then a new
node
and finally
we start when
after a complete scan there is no new
marked node
generated
right
so
in that case after the whole thing stops
we check if t
is marked
that means there is a directed path
going from s
to t
right
otherwise if t is not marked
it is apparently that from s there is no
directed path
to t
that's why
the algorithm here
is correct
okay it is a desire for path
no matter how you input the string
it can distinguish if the string the
given string is in
pass
or not
okay and remember remember that there is
always a stage 0 here
reject all the invalid formatted strings
okay so
that's
that's what you know
and then
after proving the correctness of the
algorithm we need to analyze the
argument to show that it runs
in polynomial time okay
so as we just described
to show that firstly we need to say that
there is a
polynomial upper bound on the number of
stages
and then
individual stages can be wrong in
polynomial time
and don't we don't forget that the
polynomial here is relative to
the input
the length of the input string okay
that's very important okay
so here we say that
we obviously obviously we know that for
stage one and four
they only
uh the two
stages are executed only once
right
only once
and
how many times will stage three runs
at most m times what is m m here is the
number of vertex okay so
m here is
number of vertex
because every time you mark a new node
right
so
if
you mark all the node
it will stop
if you
if you if we haven't
mark all the nodes and stop that means
some node cannot be
reached from s
right
but eventually it will stop it will not
run forever
so at most m times that means all the
nodes
all the nodes in the graph are marked
okay
so the number of total number of stages
at most
is 1 plus 1 plus n which is stage 1
stage 4 and stage 3
okay or you can say 2 and 3 doesn't
matter
okay
then
we know that for each individual state a
stage for each individual stage one and
four
are easily implemented in polynomial
time
and reason on any reasonable
deterministic model because see for
one you just need to find node in g and
mark the node right
and
the whole type you have v you have e
and of course two vertex here
and
here
is m right and how long is here
at the most
about
m square
right at most
and we consider the whole thing n
right
so apparently to finish stage one you
just need to go through a small portion
okay actually you need to go over
the whole tape
and know that okay you need to mark v3
and you go back to mark b3
okay so that's about linear to the input
length
right
and then for stage four you just need to
check
within this part to see if t is marked
okay but anyway stage 4
stage 1 and 4
are easily implemented in polynomial
time on any
actually any reasonable deterministic
model
and stage 3 involves
a scan of the input and a test whether
certain nodes are marked
and let's say
when you do the scan
you
you will go the
you will go through this part
this part once
but every time you get a
directed directed age
you get a
starting point of the direct sorry uh
the head of the the directed edge here
you go
to
the node the vertex part of the graph to
see
if that is
marked
if no
you go
back here to see next
h
if yes you mark you mark this no sorry
then you mark
the tail of the directed edge
by the whole
operation here you can easily
uh you can imagine that it it
it is it can be easily implemented
within polynomial time
as to the whole length of the input as
within the polynomial time you can
finish the
operation of stage 3.
if there is no problem here then we know
that
the
overall the total number of stages is 1
plus 1 plus n that's no problem and for
each stage for each stage
the implementation can
the operation can be implemented
in polynomial time of the length of the
input
string
okay
so
m here
is a polynomial time algorithm for path
since the polynomial time algorithm for
path
exists language path
by definition is in p
okay
so that's what we are talking about
to prove
a problem or a language
in class b
so next is relative point
uh so relative prime
so for relative prime it's uh we we use
the famous famous euclidean algorithm
for
a chinese speaking student
it is
all right it should be known for
everybody i guess
be known to everybody
so
uh
we have two integers x y x and y here we
want to check if x and y are relative
are relatively prime what does that mean
that means
the
gcd the
greatest the common divisor
of x and y is 1.
except for one there is no other common
divisor for the two
uh integers okay
so
what is the euclidean algorithm if we
implement in
uh the terminology of turing machine in
the in as a we implement the algorithm
as a turing machine we can write it this
way
okay so firstly we have a
subroutine called here
okay we have a sub wrinkle here we call
that
uh e
and for e you get
uh e the input of e are two
natural numbers in binary let's assume
that okay in binary
we will repeat
the two
uh stages here until y
is zero okay until y is zero
so firstly we assign x mod y two x
that means
x will be assigned as the remainder
of x divided by y
okay
then we exchange
x and y
okay
if until y
equal to 0
we output x
okay so if you think it's very you know
difficult to understand you give some
example here
so let's say
we have
17 here
okay and eight here
okay so
we assign
what is uh
mod
that would be
17 divided three
17 divided by a
which is two
the remainder is one
right
okay
so
next time x
is one
and the y
is still eight right
then we exchange x y so x is eight y is
one
right then we again we assign x mod y
so what is
eight divided by 1 that will be
8 and the remainder is 0 right so we
assign x 0
and y still 1
and we exchange
x and y so
x is one
y is zero
and then
y is zero right so we output x that
would be one
okay so 17
and eight
are relatively prime because the
greatest common divisor of them is one
otherwise let's say if we do 16 here
okay
so
the same thing 16
mod 8
right so that will be
2 remainders 0
then x will be 0
y is 8.
right then we exchange x and y
x 8
y 0.
since y is 0 we report
8.
so 16 and 8 the greatest common divisor
is eight so they are not
relatively point
okay
so
this part is actually
the turing machine representation of
euclidean
algorithm
okay
so then we can build
a turing machine based on e
okay
so because uh
euclidean algorithm here
is not directly for checking relative
point
the usage of it is to
obtain the gcd the greatest
common divisor of two
integers
okay so we
design a tree machine
decider based on euclidean horizon
so for the input here
we run
e
under
the input directory okay
so
after running
the euclidean algorithm if the result is
one
that mean
that means
there is no other integers
can be the
common divisor for the two integers so
the two given integers x and y
are relatively prime
so we accept
and uh the divide the decider accept
otherwise
otherwise reject right if you uh if
there are any
other integers any integers other than
one
can be the common divisor of the two
integers then the two
integers are not
relatively prime
okay
so uh
so i guess the
the correctness of the algorithm here
the r here and e here
are uh
there's no problem with
correctness here so we can just
skip that
then
what we are interested here is the
running time
right the running time
and how
how uh
how fast
uh
in terms of the
length of the input string
okay
okay we can
can we uh finish the
algorithm execution okay
so
to analyze the time complexity of
euclidean algorithm
there's nothing to analyze for r here
right because the r here just
uh run e and the theta
check the results and report the
decision okay so
the uh the main algorithm here is the
euphemism
so to analyze the time complexity of e
we first show that
every
execution of stage 2
cuts the value of x by at least half
okay
so
there actually there are some
assumptions uh regarding the analysis
here
if you are doing the programming contest
you know that uh
the time complexity analysis is far
complicated then we will be
talking about we will be discussed here
okay so here we
present a highly
simplified version of uh time complexity
analysis
okay
so now here
we can see that
for the
simplified
viewpoint
every stage
repeat until y 0
can be
implemented can be run in polynomial
time
right
and
here we do a division here
and assign the result which is a
reminder of the
remainder of the division to x
so such a operation can be
implemented in polynomial time of
the length of the input right and
exchange x and y can also be implemented
in polynomial time and of course output
x doesn't matter
right you know it
it does doesn't read any real operation
here so it can be implemented in within
polynomial time
so the problem here is how many stages
the number of stages we want we need to
finish the calculation to finish the
computation
right
so each stage no doubt they are they can
be run
in
paranormal time
so how many stages
so that depends on how many loop you
need to finish the calculation right to
the
computation that's why we first one we
want to show that every execution of
stage two
probably accepts popular first okay
cuts the value of x by at least half
okay
so
stage two here
okay
and what what's interesting here is that
for x and y
two integers
that's enough let's analyze
two possible situations
actually only two possible situations
okay so first situation is that
let's say
first the situation
x
divided by two which is half x
okay
greater or equal to one
and the second
situation is that
half x
smaller
than y
less than one okay
well there is no other
possible situation here right only the
two let's classify the situation here
into these two situations two scenarios
okay
okay so
if half x
is equal to or greater than y
what is
x
mod
y
what is
the value here
that's a problem okay
then what is x mod y
the value of x y is x divided by y
the remainder of x divided by y
right
since it is the remainder
the value of x mod y
must
be less than y
right
it cannot be y because if it can be y
the ratio plus 1 right
so it cannot
be
greater or equal to y because it's the
remainder
okay
then since
the value here is less than y
see that
y
is less than or equal to what
f of x
right
and then we assign
this value
to our next x
right so
let's use x prime
here so we assign this value to next x
so next x
equal to or less than
half of the
current x
okay so that's the first situation
for the second situation here
what is
x
mark
y
the same question here
what is x my y
see
now x oh sorry now y
of
y
is greater than
half of x
y is greater than half of x
okay that that let's give an concrete
example so that you will uh
understand it easily
so if
you have a number 15
and the y is 8
a 8 is greater than half of 15 right
so what is
15 mod
it will be 15 minus 8
which is 7 right
because
y
is greater than half of
x
there is no other
integers
can be
multiplier
to multiply y
and
still smaller than
x
that's why x mod y
in under the condition that y
is greater than half of x
the remainder
become
the remainder becomes x minus one
okay because how large is y okay
so that will be
x
minus y
in this situation the remainder
is x minus y
again since y is larger is greater than
half of x
x minus y
must be less than half of x
right
because y here
larger than half of x
so x minus y
will be smaller
will be less than
half of x
so
our next
x
is less than
half of x
half of the current x
right
so
these two scenario covers all possible
scenarios all
possibilities and within
all possibilities
we know that
next x
is
greater than or sorry less than or equal
to curve half of current x
okay
so that's why we say that
no matter this situation the first
duration or the second situation
x drops by at least half
that's why we say so
okay
okay then for stage three
we just exchange x and y
okay we change x and y
and so that we
may we make y the next x and
x prime
the next y
okay
and how many times
how many times
uh well stage two and three executed
you will find that
the execute the number of the maximum
number of
times
that stage 3 and 2 are executed is the
lesser
the lesser
of
2 log base 2 x or 2 log base 2 y
okay
why
firstly the 2 here the 2 here is
because stages 2 and 3 there are two
stages here so the 2 there it means 2
stage 2 and stage 3.
and since we cut
at least half every time
how
many times you can cut
x
to
one
and the y to 1
that would be
log
base 2 x
and the log
base 2 1
right
because every time you cut cutting half
of x or next time you cut y and next
time you cut half uh sorry x and next
time y
and why the lesser not the
not the greater
because
as long as you cut one two uh
sorry as long as you cut one of them
to one
then the process
terminates right
no matter how large the other one is
for example if you have a very very
large x but y now is one then the
divisor
sorry the remainder will be zero so it
doesn't matter
how large the other one is
we only need to take care about the
laser right
so as long as one
big uh one of them x or y becomes one
then the process terminates
that's the key point okay so why the
lesser of the two because
as long as one
of them becomes one then the whole
process terminates
okay
so
we know that
we know that we need so many
or this one okay it doesn't matter so
many
stages to finish the calculation
then
probably you will think okay uh it is a
big o of log
and
already
right
actually wrong why because
the end here
we talk about
is actually
the length of the input string
and what is the length of the input
string here
as we just
uh discussed in the beginning of this
this hour
x
or y
are in db uh integers are integers
so if we consider binary representation
of x and y
how long
how many
spaces
on the tape will be occupied by
the string in representing x or y
for x we need
so many
and the plus one actually
right and for y we need
this many
types right
so
the tape the input
the length of the input string
is actually proportionate
okay
proportional
to
the quantity
here linear to the quantity here
so actually
relative prime
solved by euclidean horizon
the execution time for euclidean horizon
is linear time
okay it's linear time of course it's a
polynomial right because linear is the
is a polynomial but
more specifically is linear because the
running time we need
to finish the exclusion of
euclidean algorithm
is proportional to is linear to
the length of the representation
on the input of the input string on the
tape
okay
so
it's kind of important that to know that
euclidean algorithm
is in polynomial
actually in linear not in log time
logarithm time okay
so
if you uh
that uh
let's
elaborate this uh a little bit further
and uh let's say
sometimes we need to check if uh
if uh uh if a integer is composite
right so for example 10
you say that 10 is 2.5 that's composite
right it's not a prime okay so you check
let's say um
100 then you can say oh 100 is 10 times
10 or
2 times 50 or something so it's not a
prime
okay
and if you check something
uh some and
you want to check it's a point or
composite
what the naive way to do
is to check if n can be divided by one
okay one you don't need to check that
okay so two
three four
until which number of course n minus one
would do but you don't want to do that
right
usually we can check until
square root of n
right that's a theorem i guess
and square root of n is like
n
to um
0.5
power right
and
you might think that
okay it's a polynomial time algorithm
but no it's not it's a it's an
exponential time algorithm
why
don't be confused by n here
and
okay and the n we use in here
the n we use in the big o notation
usually
means the length of the input string
right but n here is actually the value
so how
many tape spaces you need to
represent the value here let's change it
to m okay
you need log
base 2 if you use binary okay then you
need so many
tape space
and
you need
so many iterations
this value is
an exponential value of this
term
so such a naive algorithm
is an exponential time algorithm it's
not the point of no time everything so
don't be confused by
the value
the power of the value the polynomial of
that value
with
what we are talking about regarding the
input uh the length of the input string
and the lens the input string on the
tape
okay
so we you need to be
uh you need to uh
make clear of all these things okay
so uh next
example is that
we know that uh
every context free language is a member
of p
okay
if you remember that
we have a
theorem that every context free language
is decidable
right it's decidable
and how do we prove that
we prove that theorem by
given any
context free language
we design
a decider for that language right
now we use the same thing actually we we
actually use cyk algorithm right so for
any given counter speed language we have
a cyk
algorithm here
since the algorithm can uh
the algorithm here
given
a context-free grammar
the tutoring machine here
plays as the decider of that context
free language
then we need to analyze
the running time of
the turing machine here
and for running time of the training
machine here we do the same thing as we
say
as as we said in the previous analysis
firstly we need to know how
many
total uh
we need to know the total numbers of the
stages
and then we need to know
that individual stages can be executed
in polynomial time
okay
so let's check uh
the format uh not format let's check the
attribution here
so i'll input
w1 to wn which is which means the uh w
here
the length of w here is n right so you
have uh the the input string contents
and symbols
and you will find that we have
we have the
loop here
and also
here
and
it's easy to see that for every
uh
we can ignore the loop part right
so the
up operation part here
and operation part here
apparently they can be implemented they
can be implemented
within polynomial time okay that's no
problem with that
and
we need
if we use what we have for
uh
our
first and first midterm examination
right
you need
about
and
by
and you need to feel
and by end
place of course half but
for the uh big o notation half of
any terms half is a
constant right so we have n by n square
sorry n uh n squared uh blanks to fill
and for every for example this one
you need to check about
n
about n possibilities
right
so for this one you you need to check
one the whole thing two
three
five
four five right
so
the order here is like n by n
and times n because
to fill each blank
you need to go through
all possible split of the input string
right if you remember how you finish the
question in our first examination you
know that
you need to you firstly you need to fill
and
big o of n square
yeah big o of n square blanks then for
for uh to fill each of the big o of n
square blanks you need to check
separate like this and separate like
this and separate like this
about n possibilities
right so you will need so many stages
for that so that will become the goal of
and cubic
so
cyc arizon
can be
executed in
the goal of
n squared sorry n cubic time so that so
it is a polynomial time everything
okay
so that's another example of uh problems
in p that means
our language is in p right so that means
each context free language
is a member
of p
more specific more specifically big o of
n cubic but doesn't matter we want to uh
eliminate the boundary of n square and
cubic
even log n we make them
class of p
okay so that's our
examples
so we have
all context-free languages we have a
relative prime here and we have
path
have pessi
so that's the example
examples of problems in p we want to
introduce you