let's go back to the goal of this course
we talked about that the goal of this
course
is to discuss the limitations
the capability of computations and
the analogy we draw on
the models is that we use
languages we consider languages as
problems and the strings
in the language as problem instance
in some problem and we use the
computational model
to handle or to solve the problem
by accepting or not
accepting strings that means
if you have a problem and
of which the answer is yes or no you can
use
you can directly connect to such a model
so for example
as i gave that
if there is a dfa
which can appropriately
answer all the valid
addition strings equations and we will
think
okay this kind of model can do addition
or for that matter multiplication
subtraction division same uh
something like that so
we already know that we just proved
the equivalence of the four basic
conditional models dfa and fa gnfa and
regular expression
if just if
regular languages are all possible
languages
then we are we and we will be very happy
about it but
right because our dfa can solve all
possible problems
under such assumption or under the
analogy we draw between problems and the
languages
right in this case you might think
that's not possible because dfa
determines the finite automata are
obviously
too simple
so regular languages cannot be all
possible languages
well that's not wrong because we are
as the title of this section non-regular
languages
implies that there are languages outside
of regular languages right
but the problem is how do you prove that
such language exists
right let's consider the example here
for example there is a language b here
which
is defined as
the same number of 0 and 1 and the 0
is before ones okay
so what are all the strings in the
language
is they are like epsilon when
n equals 0 right then
0 1 0 0
1 1 0 0 0
1 1 1 etc etc
okay it's pretty easy to
figure out or what what what kind of
strings
in this language let's consider this
language that
if you want to prove this language
to be regular by definition we need to
design a dfa to accept
all the strings all the strings in the
language
and not accept all other strings
right so
what will will you do you might think
okay i use some
state
and when it reads zero
and it goes to more states so we use the
states to count
basically to count how many zeros
and doing one bag right
something like that
but the problem is that how many states
you need
obviously you will quickly find that
you will never have enough states for
this
right for example you say okay i have 1
million state here
i use 1 million state here fine
but what if you have 0 like
2 million and the 1 2 million
such string you cannot handle by
using only 1 million states even though
it's
the amount is huge but and of course
it's finite
and you will find that
finite state
don't seem to be able to handle such
language
and after a while you might think
okay it might not be possible to desire
a dfa to recognize this language
so the language probably is not
a regular language
well that's correct but the arguments
cannot
cannot we cannot use such
arguments to prove the existence of
non-regular language or to prove the
language
b here is not regular
because it it may be a you know
a way of thinking but it's not
valid mathematical argument
over this proof we need something
stronger
we need something valid in logic
so here we
introduce pumping lemma
we can use pumping lemma to prove
some language to be non-regular
okay we firstly we will uh
introduce uh what is pompilema and
present well close to a proof
to prove that pumping nema is correct
then we will use the pump element
to prove some language to be non-regular
and don't rem don't forget that pumping
lemma is a
necessary condition that means every
regular language has such property
so if some language does not have such a
property
it's not regular but
the reverse is not valid that means
if you can prove some language has the
property
described by the pumping lima
that doesn't mean such a language
is regular okay so
it's a single direction criteria
don't forget that that's very important
okay so what is pumping lima
hominema describes if a
language a is a regular language
then there is a number p
we call it pumping length
and the piece is basically a p is not
unique
okay but you got the number p
and
for the strings in a
any strings
in a longer
or equal to p
then such a string as long as it's
long enough may be divided
into three pieces okay keyword here
is maybe divided so you
don't know how to divide it but you know
there is at least a way to divide
s here into
three pieces let's say x
y z satisfying the three conditions here
let's see second condition first
the middle part the second part
of the piece cannot be empty string
and the first
two parts together shorter
or equal to p and
under these conditions we
know that
you can either pull
out the middle part or
repeat the middle part
for any possible
times the resultant string
will always be
in a will always be in
a2 okay so it's kind of
complicated complicated statement but
it's not that complicated actually so
let's do it again
so you have a language you have a
regular language then
if there must be a number p
we call it pumping length where
any string in a
at least longer than p or
equal the dense is equal to p
such a string may be divided into three
pieces
satisfying these three conditions
and according to the condition here you
can understand
why the middle piece cannot be empty
string
right because if the middle string can
be empty string
then there's it's nonsense to describe
such a
lemma because if y is empty
string then it doesn't really matter
right
so y cannot be empty
and pampilema tells us that any regular
language
have such properties
okay have such properties so
that means any regular languages you
know there is a
number p and any strings
any strings in this language
as long as it's long enough how long it
is
longer than or equal to p then
the string there is a way to
there is at least a way to divide such a
string
into p three pieces satisfying the three
conditions
okay so why regular language has
why any regular language has such a
property
it's actually quite easy if you think of
the definition of regular languages
okay how do we define regular language
we use dfa
right and don't forget that the most one
of the most important
property of dfa is that there is only
a finite number of states
okay so imagine that
for dfan here
there is that's a
uh
end state okay there is totally
n state then
if you try to process a string
for example length n right
this string sorry
this string s has
length n then how many states
will be stepped upon
totally n plus one right
so you have only end state
and processing this string
you need n plus one state
so it's pretty straightforward that
there must be duplicate
states during the processing of the
string
right
so the most straightforward thinking
regarding
pumping lemma is that
given a dfa which
represents a regular language right
and for that dfa
it has only a finite number
of states
and if there are strings
longer or equal to
the number of states in that
language for that dfa to process
such strings it requires
duplicate states
during the pro string processing
so to visualize such a relationship
you can think of a processing
a string processing maybe like this
start from
q1 and after process
the string the first part of string it
reaches
some state and then
after processing the second part of the
string it reach
the duplicate states for example then
final part of the string
go to the state accepted
okay so if a string
is accepted in this fashion
then you know that string
xz must be accepted by
exactly the same dfa right
and the string x y
y z must be
accepted too right because you just
go through this past again
then you can go through this page
indefinitely
indefinite times so that's why
for x
y i z
it must be in the language
for i for each possible i
right
so that's why we have
these conditions and
that's why it is called pumping lemma
because you pump
you pump the second part
you pump white into the string you pump
the second wire
third y fourth y you pump y
into the string and the resultant string
is still in that language
it must be in because you just
go back to the same states and for dfa
don't forget that's
dfa deterministic final automata
so every state every step
goes to some deterministic deterministic
step
step okay
and why we have the third condition
because the as long as the string is
long enough
the duplicate states must
there are as long as the string is
longer
or equal to the number of the states
there must be a duplicate state there it
might be
you know other place elsewhere
but for the first duplication
it must happen within
the length of p
which might be your the number of the
states of that dfa
okay so that's why we have
that's exactly why we have uh pumping
lemma
we have pumping lemma for regular
languages because any any regular
language
you can find some dfa and you just pick
one dfa
and the number of the states of that dfa
becomes the pumping becomes the pumping
length
and you can know that
any string
equal the length of that string equal to
p or
greater than p such a string may be
divided into three pieces
which three sorry which three pieces
from start state to the duplicate states
from duplicate states back to the
duplicate states
and goes to the accept state
okay so if the start state
is the duplicate state then you don't
have the first part
if thus if the
duplicate state is the accept state you
don't have the
third part
but you you always need to have
the second part otherwise it doesn't
make sense
okay so
regular language has such a property
okay
and we can only use this
lemma to prove some languages to be
non-regular
because if you prove that okay i have a
language
i let such a language have this property
we cannot conclude that that language is
regular
because non-regular probably have
have this property too
so we can only use to disprove
the regularity of a language okay
then how to use it how to use it
we need to do a contradiction because we
want to prove a language
has no such property
we usually assume that language for
example
b here to be regular
since b is regular right since b is
regular
we need to go back to the pump element
we need to say that b has no
such properties and how
so we we need to prove that not
every string in that language
of length at least p
has these property
since the lemma describes any string in
the language of length at least
p has the following property we need to
pick some special case
okay because any string is a for
all relationship we need
to give a counter example
but the difficult part is that the
string
may be divided into three pieces
so there exists some way to divide it
and how do you
how do you contradict such
situation you must prove that
there is no way
to divide the string into three pieces
with the following conditions you must
prove that
that's you know slightly well actually
sometimes
quite difficult you have to prove
there is no way to divide that string
satisfying the three conditions
okay so what we usually do
is to
assume that one
or two conditions are satisfied
in that case there is no way to satisfy
this condition okay
and if you want to prove something
if you want to prove there is no way to
satisfy the first condition well
first condition is for all
stuff for each i
for all so you need to pick some
counter example here to prove that
there's no way okay
so let's
uh see the example of the language b
in the beginning of this section okay
so let me be the language we just
talked about okay here
we want to use pumping lemma to prove b
here is not regular
by contradiction so firstly we assume
b is regular okay we assume b is like
regular and since b is regular
there is a pumping pumping length here
that say p we don't know what p is
but you know there is a number p playing
such a row
then by pumping them up
any languages longer than or equal to p
has that property now we need to choose
a counter example say that this
string doesn't satisfy those properties
those conditions
okay so
which string should we pick here
select here as the contour example
choose zero p
one p what is zero p one p
that means the string is
zero you have zero
and you have p zeros
and then p ones okay
so we choose this string and how long it
is
so one zero p 1 p the length will be 2p
and of course 2p
greater than or equal to p because
without the loss of generality p is not
0 and also not
negative right it must be greater than 1
or something because
you know basically it's the number of
states
so if
b is really regular such
such string s must be divided by
uh in some way to satisfy the three
conditions
right so by pumping they might guarantee
that
there is a way to divide
s into three pieces
but we want to show it's not possible
there is no
way to do that so we need to
how do we prove that
firstly
we can we know that the length
of y the second part right
cannot be zero
that means y cannot be empty string
so consider string as here
where can y go if you if there is
some way to divide it s
and the middle pieces the second pieces
is not empty so there is only
three possibilities right we don't know
how long
y is but we know it's not zero
and given that
situation we know that y is
either in this region
or in this region
or in this region right
there is no other possibilities the
three possibilities
are everything
you have a noun empty y so either y
contains only zero
or y contains only one
or y contains both
zero and ones
right all possibilities are here
let's say if y contains only zeros
then apparently let's say
string x z
we make i we make i here
zero xd is not
in the language right because you have
more
one more ones than zeros
or let's say this result
x y y z
not in b either because
you have more zeros than ones then the
resultant string
is not in b okay so it's not
possible that y contains only
zeros and the same
argument goes to content only containing
only once
right saying exactly same arguments
because
if you get rid of y then you have fewer
ones
if you duplicate y then you have more
then either way the resultant string is
not
in the original language
so it leaves the final possibility that
you have y sorry the y have
the symbols y have only
uh not only zero or one it both contain
both
so both zeros and ones
so in this case you know that
it is possible xz is still in b
right if y has same number of
zeros and ones but the string
x y y z here
is not in b although it may contain the
same number of
zeros and ones the four the form
the format is invalid
why because you will have 0 0
0 sum 0 1 1
and then what 0 0 0
and then 1
because you repeat y and y is something
like
0 0 1 1 1.
so you repeat this part of the string
again
and 0 here one here you have something
like
x y y z
will be like this and this string
is not in b
okay then we know that
there is no way absolutely no way
to divide
zero p one p this counter example we
choose
satisfying the three required conditions
by the pumping lemma so
that's a contradiction and
what's wrong with it the
error source comes from we assume that
b is regular okay
so the conclusion is that b is not
regular
because if b is regular
we will have contradiction
okay as long as long as we assume that
b is regular the contradiction
is unavoidable so b is not regular
so that's how we use pumping lemma and
you can go through
you can go through the process
like here that's like described here
we assume some language is regular
and we know by pumping lemma there is a
p here
and for any string
as long as it's long enough it will be
it can be must be pumped
so we found we try to find a particular
string
as the counter example
and the only requirement for this
counter example is that
it's long enough and
usually it's you know kind of difficult
to
think of figure out a good counter
example for you to
finish the whole proof it's the
difficult part one of the difficult
parts
anyway after you pick an appropriate
counter example we need to
describe that such
string cannot be pumped as described
then we know the contradiction is
obtained
then that language is not regular
okay so let's go back
to this example
and remember that there are three
conditions
okay so by
appropriately use the conditions we can
make the proof
slightly simpler
so let's assume b
is regular here let's assume b is
regular here
we choose the
counter example candidate zero p one p
so it's the same that we have p zeros
and the p ones right
and we know that the third condition
would be x y
shorter or equal to p because we explain
that
in the first duplicate states must be
happened you know when
the string the length of the string is
close to p
since we
need to satisfy the third condition here
that means y can
only in our example here
y can only exist
in this part right
y can only exist in this part
we don't even need to analyze the
three the three possibilities
we just need to use y
noun zero sorry non-empty
and x y within
the first p simple symbols so y must be
here and then you know that
y contains only zeros if
we need to satisfy the three condition
the second one
the third one
under the
condition that three
the second and third condition are
satisfied
there is no way to divide
s into three pieces also satisfying
the first condition because
given that y is within
the part of zeros
any string
for i on equal to
1 is not in b
right
so we have proof that
b here
b here is not
a regular language okay
since b
is not a regular language
that means well it uh
it indicates that uh
the the existence of non-regular
language
simply tells us that
let's say if you have alphabet
right then we use
sigma star to represent
all possible strings composed
by sigma
so sigma star is a set
of strings and
it is the state set of all possible
strings
composed by sigma and what is language
all possible language are
all possible subset of
sigma star right so in a way
we can you know denote all possible
strings like
two to the sigma star or some
textbook use this notation or this
notation
okay then
we we was hope we were hoping that
regular languages are all possible
languages
because in that case we can use dfa to
do
any possible problems right but now we
know that's
okay at least this language
is not regular that means
if we have if we have all possible
language here regular language
is just some of them because
at least b is outside
of regular language
right so
it goes back to
uh the need to discuss
the closure property of regular
languages
we have discussed crucial property of
regular language
on three operations right
uh first one is union
we prove that the class of regular
languages
is closed under the union
operation and also concatenation
concatenation
and also the star operation
so now we know that sadly
regular languages are not all possible
languages
see if let's say if regular languages
are all possible languages
then you don't need to you know really
talk about
closure property because all possible
set operations all possible
string operations are closed
right regular languages will be closed
under all those common or specific
whatever
operations because all
languages are regular but
now we know that it's not indicate it's
not the case
because at least one language here
is outside of regular language so
regular language the class of like
the cause of regular language is not all
then we need to discuss okay so
what operations we all have
closure properties on regular languages
after knowing that we know we we can
more appropriately handle regular
languages
because we know that okay you have two
or three
regular languages and go through which
operations you still get regular
languages
you still get something that a dfa
or nfa can recognize
okay so
we will be discussing closure property
next time you