in order to
prove the equivalence between
context-free grammars and
push down automata
we need to prove that
a language is context-free if and only
if some push-down automata recognize it
and
for this direction
if a language is context-free
we can
uh construct
a push down automaton
according to the given contextual
grammar because a language is context
free by definition
there is a language l
there is a context free grammar
g
which language of which the language is
l
then we use g
to build
a push-down automata p
such that p
is
l
so that
uh that's what we have proven
uh the such a pda can be well basically
easily constructed
by using the given context free grammar
and then now we want to prove the other
way that
given
a push down automata
given a pushdown automata
the language
recognized by that automata we want to
prove that
that language is contextual
okay so that's the other direction
for
uh
theorem
so the idea here
is uh quite
similar to the previous one that given a
pda we
according to this pda
we convert the pda
into
an equivalent context-free grammar okay
and
firstly
given any pda
we modify the given pda
to fit the framework
then we can easily do the conversion
okay
so how
do we modify the given any given pda
firstly
we want to modify a given pda into that
the modified pda has
a single accept state
okay
a single accept state because for any
given pda there might be
well several
or a lot of accept states right as long
as it's
and sub is a subset of the states of
that pda
and we require that there is only one
accept state
and such modification is quite easy
because our pda
is intrinsically non-deterministic right
so you just need to
for example you have a pda you are given
a pda and there is
some accept state
and then you cut
basically copy everything of that pda
and add one more
state one more new state
and
make it accept state and cancel all
original accept state
right and
make
transition from those states at one
epsilon
abstrom absorb transition to
the new accept state then it's easy to
see that
if the
if the process
stop by for example
this state
then it will go through here
so that will make
a equivalent make an equivalent
pda but with only a single state
uh sorry a single accept state okay
then
we also require that
the pda empty its stack before accepting
okay
so
we don't need to let's say
how do we do that
it's also a
known skill
used
it's already used by the example
we introduced
firstly we
the the given pdf has a
star state right and firstly we add one
new star state
and
make it a new the new star state and we
add initially some special character
onto the stack for example
we do let's say dollar sign right assume
that
dollar sign
is not used by the given pda okay assume
that dollar sign is a whole new symbol
to the whole
model here
and then
we make it we make the pda here
only one
accepts it but not yet we make it a
single uh
middle state then
we do
maybe do in this way or we make another
middle state and the pop
pop every stack symbol doing the loop
here
then
when we see
the spatial character here
we pop it out then accept
okay
so by doing this
at one more accept date at like three or
maybe two uh maybe two here so totally
three or four new states we can we can
achieve the modification required
right
so for any given pda it's very easy to
do it then the third
criteria is here
we need each
transition
either pushes a symbol or pops a symbol
okay
either pushes a symbol or a public
symbol
it's it's even easy
it's even easier than the previous two
because we can
we use it as an example okay
so for a given pda
then
this one is a
push only push only push operation
so there's no problem and only push
operation no problem only power
operation no problem right so pop pop
pop
and
push push
push
right
so
there are three transitions here
simultaneously push and pop
well not simultaneously
tenuously they have push and pop right
so we just need to add one more
state
so make it
pop
strong
as
pop right then
push
right so that's it so we also make it
one more here and
one more here sorry
go back here
okay
then you may ask that
uh if you have a
apps on app strong like that's you know
actually
to
if there is a
something like this
then you can do the same thing you add
one more state
and arbitrarily push something and then
pop out right so
arbitrary push let's say
c
then
pop out
right so simply put if
the transition is already push only or
pop only then there's no problem
then you might have both push and pop up
operation like
something like this
then you change it
to
pop first push next
right
or you have nothing
no push no pop let's say
like
no push no pop
then you change it to
push arbitrary symbol and pop it out
next
okay
so it's quite easy to
have an
equivalent pdh
and with the
three
criteria here
okay
so
if we have a pda has such properties
then we can
generate we can convert the pda
to a context free grammar
okay
and
remember that what we want what we want
to have
is that given a pda
and
writing a grammar
such that
the language recognized by the pda
is the language generated by the grammar
that's that's actually what we want to
do
but
the conversion here from pda to grammar
actually more
give us more than this relation
okay
because this relation requires that
from the start variable of this grammar
all the
string
or the terminal string
generated
is
the terminal string recognized uh
accepted by the pda right
but actually the grammar we we will be
generate we will be constructed
constructed here has a even closer
relation with the pda
we will
use one variable
for
each pair of states
for each pair of states
and
that variable can generate
all the strings
that are processed by the pda for the
transitions from the first state to the
second state
okay
so the grammar would we will be gen we
will be constructed
actually has a even closer relationship
with the pda not only you know globally
the their languages are identical
but
for
at a more fundamental level
they are equivalent
okay
so let's see how do we construct such
grammar given a pda
so
for pda for the given pda we say that it
is a sixth purple right so you have
state you have
input alphabet you have stake alphabet
you have transition function
you have star state and
since we have only a single
accept state so
the accept states here is a single
accept state but you know definition is
a stat so it's still a set
we want to construct a context free
grammar here pontius county free grammar
is a full tuple so variables
alphabet terminals
so you can see that the terminals is
exactly the input alphabet so there's no
problem there
and
inside the variable there is a starch
variable and
rules okay
then how do we construct it the
construction is easy so
for
air uh for
every pair
in
the state of the pda not say pq
we have we have a variable for that
okay
we have a variable for that
so for every pair in q we have a p q a
verbal and all possible
all such possible variables
is our variable
is our variable set of the grammar
then since
the start variable
is q0 and there is only one except
accept variable
sorry starts
the star star the star state is q0 and
there's only one
accept state
so
we have a variable
a q 0 q accept right and that variable
is our start
variable is our star variable
see that's what that's why we want to
have only single accept states and we
want to write a grammar
use one variable for each pair of states
and generate all the strings processed
by the pda
so you see
from the start state to
the accept states those string
can be generated
so
that's why start variable of the grammar
is this variable
okay
then
the sigma is the same so we don't need
to discuss that so we want to discuss
the rules the productions right
so there are three kinds of rules three
sets of rules let's see the last one
first
so
for each
state
we have rule
app may become epsom
okay so that's easy right so if you have
q
states
you will have so many
rules for the third kind
right
then
for the second kind of rules for the
second set
for every pqr
three
states for every pqr
in q
we write a rule
apq
may become
a p r and arq
okay
so there will be so
many
rules
for the second one second kind
okay so you see the third kind and the
second kind there's nothing to do with
the operation of the pda exactly right
because the transition of pda
has no role for the two
kinds of rules
so
the first kind of rules here
for pqrs in queue
and
some symbol in stack variable
for some input symbol or epsilon
if
the
machine at p
read input
a
becomes
r the state becomes r and push t
and you find another entry that the
machine adds s
reading b
and the part t
and the s
goes to q
and pop
t right
so the key point is the stacks in both t
stacks in both t
see
so you see initially the stack will be
empty right but initially the stack is
empty so everything in the stack
is pushed at some steps
and the pop
popped
in the later state right
so
we see where
some stack symbol may be
pushed and where
the symbol may be popped then we connect
we connect these two transition
and then write down the rules like
you see
at p
goes to
r
at
s
goes to q right
so
when the machine at the p
goes to r
and
and push t right
push t
and
from
s
goes to q
pop t
right
and
the step here we don't know
okay
but we know that
at this step a
of the input symbol is consumed
and b of the input symbol is consumed
right
and we know
this part of string can be generated by
a r s
right so from p to q
that is the mission of the variable apq
so we write
write down a rule that apq may become
what
may become a
a r s
b
okay
that's why we have the rule here
because
when
the states from p to r
a symbol of
a stack symbol
for example t here
is pushed onto the stack
and somehow from s to q
that symbol that stack symbol t
is popped from stack
okay
and for the first step a is consumed and
for the last step b is consumed
and for the
step in the middle we don't know what
happened but we know
what we want to have is that ars
can generate the string from r to s
okay
then that's our
conversion
procedure for a given pda to
the equivalent cfg
okay
so
let's have a example
with
this one
okay
it is not the original one we have
because
originally
for the previous example we have this
and
this
right
but now we use another pda
like this why we want to use this why
don't we use the previous one
well you can use the previous one
because
you can do the modification to make it
you know symbol accept states or other
things
but
it's easier for us to use the pda
this pda
as example because we don't need to do
any
multiplications that's it for simple uh
for simplicity
and you see that
for the second kind of
rule
we will have
cubic of the number of states right
then
for four states here
we will have 64 rules
if you have one more
like five states that'll be 125 so many
of them so for simplicity we use the
pda here as our example
now let's check it again if this pda has
all the three
well properties
firstly
it has only one single
accept state right it's uh state four
then
this pda
pops
everything in the stack before accepting
right before acceptance
then let's check
this pda
the transition of this pda
is either
push
or pop pop pop
there is no nothing or push and pop
right so we don't need to do any
modification to this pda
and we can convert to the grammar we
want to have
so let's construct a grammar
variable what is the variable
every pair of the states
so we will have
so many variables
right that would be
in this example so that those variables
are a 1 1 a 1 2 a 1 3 a 1 4 a 2 1 a a22
estrada 2 a44
okay
and we know that
our start variable will be
q0q
accept right
so the curio now is one except this four
so a14 here is our
start variable for grammar g
okay then
the sigma here is apparently zero and
one
remember the zero here is symbol the
zero here is integer okay
then
now we have need to write rules and for
rules it's easy that
firstly we will have third kind of rules
that would be
a one one may become epsilon
a two two may become epsilon a three
three may become epsilon
a four four may become epsilon okay so
four rules like this
and then
cubic of number of states rules here so
a one one may become a one one a one one
okay so a lot of the rules like this and
a11 may become you know 2 inside this so
a 1 2 a 2 1
then 3 inside this so a 1 1 b may become
a 3 1
a sorry a one three a three one and then
a one four a four one right then
a one two a one two may become a one one
a one two because you stick one into
that
and then two
and then
three
and then four
and repeat all the process you have
uh this case 64 rules right for this
kind of rules
just write it write them down okay
finish them
finally the rules we want to have is
the first time first one first kind of
rules
so how to do that it's quite simple
because you just need to align
you
just need to find matched
stack symbol
okay
you try to check
try to examine where some stack symbol
is pushed and popped and write them
together
so
first thing
you see a dollar sign is pushed and a
dollar sign is popped right
so we
pair these two
transitions
okay
so what what is the first transition
here
the first transition here is
you go from state 1
to state 2
right and you consume
epsilon
right and push down the side of course
and so for the second transition here
it goes from three
states three to four and consumed
what
epsilon
and the pop dollar sign right
so
we don't know what happened in here but
we know
in here is the responsibility of a
two
three
okay
and start from one finally four so we
write the rule a14
may become
epsilon here
epsom here
that's it
so it's the first one of the
first kinds of rules
then download sign there's no pair other
pairs right so let's see
check stack symbol zero okay there is a
push here so we find okay two pop here
so you make them two pairs
first pair
and second pair
okay
so
so first pair that use uh well
let's use a okay
so a is not
is a bad idea so let's use
small a and small b okay
so
let's say
for small a
for
folder
transition here that's
a1 okay
for trans transition a1
it
goes from 2
to state 2 right consumes 0
and of course push is 0
and then
for
transition a2 here
okay
so it goes to
it from goes from
to 3 state 2 to state 3 and consumed one
right one is here
one is here okay
and of course pop 0 that's why they are
paired
then
we don't know what happened here but we
know this part is the responsibility of
a22
and then
one sorry zero here
one here and
star front two ends with three so a
two three may become
zero a two two one
okay
so
for the second
pair here
for a
the the the first row is also a one
right
so that's same thing
two to two
constant 0
but
b2 here
is
3 consumes
and same thing this part
will be handled by a23
and the zero here
and the one here
and
first one last one a
two three
okay
so
no other pairs possible for the pdas
right
so
that's why we have
a three rules here
a1 4 to a 2 3
a 2 3 2
may become 0 a 2 2 1 and also may become
0 a 2 3 1.
okay
so
that's it we have
uh return the
equivalent context free grammar
for
this
okay
so
the problem
here
may be that
how
how can we be sure
such a grammar
is really equivalent
to
this pda
right why
it's not so intuitive it's it's not so
straightforward
everybody needs to think about that a
lot and
may not be sure of the equivalence
so we need to
prove it
okay we need to do a
do a further step to prove that they are
really equivalent
like what we did for the equivalence
between dfa and nfa they are not so
straightforward so we need to prove it
okay
so what we want to do is that
we want to prove
given a pda
with the three
uh satisfying the three criteria here
and according to
according to the construction rule here
we will get
we will obtain
a contextual grammar
and
for that context free grammar we have we
can prove two things
first one here
if apq
of that context free grammar generates x
some terminal string
then
this terminal string can bring p
from
state p
with empty stack
to q
also with empty stack
okay so there are two notes here
first
why do we want to say that with empty
stack and with empty stack
because
first one
means we don't
make assumption
to the content of steak
okay we don't rely on that okay your
stack must have like a symbol t first
then it works no
we don't make assumption
okay and then
we don't leave every anything on the
stick
if you
leave anything on the stack it might
affect the later the future operations
so
we don't make assumption
of the contents of mistake and we don't
leave
something behind us
okay so that's why we describe it this
way so that's the first note
the second note is that
what we want to prove is that
the variable apq the variable of grammar
apq generate x
then s can bring
you know
this one
so
if
our grammar apq
generates
nothing
let's say
it can generate
no
not empty string okay not m md string
if
apq
can
generate
no
terminal strings okay absolutely no
terminal strings
then
the sentence here
is trivially true
okay
so of course we want to prove it prove
it that this claim right now but
it must be
noted that
if apq
eventually generates nothing then the
statement is true
okay
so
let's see the proof first and we need to
do this combined with the next proof
so how do we prove this statement
firstly we use the
induction
on the number of steps in the derivation
okay because apu generates x
okay
so
since we want to derive from
a variable
we need to check
how many steps we
need to derive from apq to a terminal
string
so the induction basis is
the derivation has only one step
okay
so is there any
uh derivation from apq
to
a terminal swing with breathing only one
step
for the grammar there is only
the third kind of rules can do that
right
because you check this
this will be a p q may become a a r s b
so you still have an uh you still have
variable you need other durations it
won't be
a terminal string within one step
right
and
for this kind of rules
one variable becomes two variable you
only will have more derivations
derivation steps okay so only these kind
rules you have one step and become
terminal string
and let's check
app
with one step
get epsilon
and we check epsilon
is this empty string can bring p
from
p
to p the same state with empty stack and
empty stack
of course because there's nothing
happened
right so our induction basis is true
okay so let's assume that let's assume
that
for
derivation of length at most k
where k
is equal to one or greater than 1
we assume that
remember its assumption
we assume that it's true
for the claim here
then based on
the assumption here we will be trying to
prove
if the terminal string requires k plus
one steps to the right
okay
so
since apq
can derive
yields uh this terminal string with k
plus one steps okay
we check
what is the first step
okay we check what is the first step
since k
is equal to or greater than 1 k plus 1
equal to or greater
than
2. right
and
you see
from the three kinds of rules
if
the first step is this kind of rules
then there's no next step so you won't
have two steps
so
for for derivation
equal to or greater than two steps the
first step must be
this kind of rules or this kind of rules
right you have no other choices
so let's say
if the first step
is the first kind of rules
then apq
derives actually eos
a
ars
b
right
and we know that apq eventually becomes
x
so we know that ars
becomes y
and the x here
should can be rewritten as a y b
and
a p q becomes x with what plus one k
plus one steps that means a r s
yields y
with k steps right because the first
step is here
since ars
derived y with k steps
it is true that
we assume
the clan
is true
right well assume that is true
within
derivation of
length at most k
so this part connects to
the true
of the hypothesis hypothesis assumed to
be true
then we know that
y here
can make
can bring
p
go from r
on empty stack
to s
right
and we also know that
why can we have
the first derivation here why
because there is a rule in the grammar
and then why there is such a rule in the
grammar
because
the p
has a transition
contains
something like this
right
p
r
and also a transition like this
as
q
and a here
a b here
and they
and the
stack simple t is pushed
for the first step and the popped into
the last step
okay
so
it's similar to the
can be represented as a graph here that
apr
the whole string here
generates apq sorry generate by apq
right
and the first symbol is a last symbol is
b
and this part generated by rs
and which is y
previously
and
the machine from r
to s
there is the
the stack here because we don't make
assumption
on empty stick right we don't make
assumption here so the machine can go
from r
2s
go from r to
s
and leave nothing on the stack
and since the machine has a
transition
from p consume a
and
push
so i should write this way
and r
push t
here
t
is pushed onto the stack
and then finally at the the last step
the machine from
s
consume b
pop the
key here
and goes to q
and
nothing
right
the transition
of this machine is the
reason why we have a p q may become a a
r s b
why we have a rule here
that's why for the grammar
we know that
this
statement
is true
you can see that you can think of that
as
the some terminal string generated by
apq
and the first step
the
you put that
you put this terminal string onto p
from
state q state p
and the first step is
the machine from p to r consume a
and push some stack symbol let's say
t
and somehow it goes to s
from r to s and the consume input symbol
y
and leave nothing on the stick
in this case what is on the top of the
thick
exactly t right
so the machine
can come from can go from s consume the
last the symbol b
and the top t
then go to state q
then
it is proof that the claim is true for
the first situation
so the second situation is that the
first step of the derivation
is that apq
becomes apr and arq
right
and this is your this situation is even
easier why because
now
[Music]
you consume one step
so
for apr
and arq
let's say you need
u steps for apr
to become some string
u-steps
and for aiq
b steps and you know that u plus b
equal to k and
both of both of them is less than
k
right
u
less than k
not even equal to
and v also less than k
so they are both
within
the induction step
since
for the machine
to go from p to r with empty stack and
from r to q with empty stack
then the clan
is proved
okay
so now we prove that
for the grammar we constructed for each
variable apq as known as apq generates a
terminal string x
that x can bring
p from
can bring
p
can bring p from state p
with empty stack that means we don't do
assumption on stack contents and go to q
with empty stack leave no
stack symbol leave nothing on the stack
okay
again i want to stress that
we proved this claim is not enough
because
for this claim to be true if your apq
generates nothing then
this claim is truly true so we we need
another
claim here we need to say that
all strings
which can bring
pdap
from the states p with empty stack
to q with empty stack the ap q the
grammar we constructed each variable apq
can generate such x
okay
we also need to prove it
again if we do not have
proven
claim
if we only
prove clan 231
then
231 can also be trivially true
if apq
can generate
all possible strings
right
it says
the string
can bring p from p to q
apq can generate it doesn't say fpq
cannot generate other stuff
so if you have your apq can generate all
possible strings
claim
231 alone is also trivially true
that that's why we need both of them 230
and 231 so we can ensure
if there is a terminal string
bring p
bring pdap from state p with empty stack
to
state q with empty stack apq can
generate that string and apq can only
generate those string and
nothing else
okay that's why we need both of them
anyway
so how to prove it
since we are not talking about the
string print
pdap
from state
p to q
we
need to do the induction on the number
of steps in computation okay the number
of steps in computation
so our
induction basis is that if the
computation has only
zero steps okay
actually nothing happened
since nothing happened
the episode here can only be
sorry the x here can only be absorbed
and nothing happened right that states
on the stem state
so
of course the clan
of course claimed
231 is true because
for all state
in p we have rule app may become epsilon
and therefore
app
can generate epsilon
right
so the state the statement is
true then again we do the hypothesis
assume that it is true
for computations of length at most k
and k
is
greater than or equal to zero
its assumption then based on this
assumption we want to prove that
computation of length k plus one also
true
then by
induction we can prove the whole thing
okay so assume that
there is a string brings
pdap
from p to q with empty stacks in
k plus one steps
okay since we already
assumed that
k steps at most k steps is
true so we want to prove with k plus one
step
and
you can see that there are only two
conditions during the whole computation
okay whole computation from small p
states p to state q
let's say
let's observe the height of the
so first condition is that the stack is
empty only at the beginning and end
okay
it must be beginning and end at least
beginning and end right because we say
that with empty stack
so begin with empty stack and end with
empty stack so of course
you have begin and end
but the first condition we say that only
at beginning and end
right
so
for this condition it's like
this one
only begin
and end
and you can see that for the first step
see our transition has only
two
types one is push only the other is pop
only so you you you either push or pop
and since you start with an empty stack
the first
transition must be a
push transition so let's say it pushes
some stack symbol onto the stack
okay
and you know that
at the end
at the end only at the end
the stack is empty again
so
the last step must involve
popping
tea
right last that must involve popping t
okay so now we know that
the total computation is k plus one
so when you go from p to q you need k
plus one and
first one you spent here and the last
one here
so how many computation steps during
from r to s
that will be k minus one right
k minus minus one step and we know it it
falls into the hypothesis right we
assume that to be true
so
we know
that
we know that
this part
these parts let's say y
can bring the pda p here from r
from r to s with empty stack
but the stack of course there's a t
there but we assume nothing on the stack
so it starts from r
and it doesn't look at the stack and
doing the computation okay
so we know that
a r s
can generate y
why because we assume to be true because
it takes k minus one steps so ais really
can generate y
based on this
we know that
x
is a y b
right x is a y b
then
we have a rule
we have rule
here
so
we know that
and we know that
a
y
b which is x
can bring
the pdf p from p
to q with empty stack
and we have a rule here so
our variable apq can really
derived
a a r
s b and we know
this one can derive to y
which is x so we prove that
if the fir if the first condition that
the stake only empty at the beginning
and end
is true
the other condition is that
the stack empty
elsewhere
somewhere anywhere
more than once doesn't matter
only once or more than once doesn't
matter as long as the stack is empty
elsewhere we know that
we know that
from p to somewhere right so let's say
state r
we know that
how many steps computational step
of this one and this one
let's say u steps b steps so
u plus b will exactly be k plus 1
right
and
and we know that
they are
respectively
equal to or smaller than
k
right
then
we know that
this part of string can be generated
by a
sorry ap
r
and this part of the string can be
generated
by a rq
and of course we
do have a rule like this remember our
second
kind of rules we add all possible rules
like this into the grammar
so we have a p q
may
become apr arq
so
let's say
a b
a p q
derive yields a p r
a r q
and finally
y
z which is x
so
for the second condition we prove that
we prove that
if x can bring
pdfp from p with empty stack and to q
with md stack our variable apq can
really generate
x
okay
so
combine clean 2 30 and the 231 you will
have that
any string
can bring the
pda from p
to q with empty stack can be generated
by apq and vice versa
so
by definition
what is the
language recognized by the pda
all the strings
goes from start state to
accept state right
and those lines can be generated by
a
star state of substance
okay
so we have proven that the constructed
grammar
is equivalent
to
the given pda
okay
so
let's go back to the
equivalence with contextual grammar then
we already proved that
a language is context free
if and only if
some push down
recognize it
okay because given a grammar we can get
a pda and given a pda we can convert it
into the equivalent grammar
okay