here comes uh chapter 3
the
church to win thesis
well uh in the beginning of our course
we are talk we were talking about
this course is about study
studying
the limitation and the capability of
computation
and
in order to do that we need to introduce
the definition of computation
and
also in order to to do that we
introduced computational models and then
we said that
since we
it is kind of difficult
to define computation directly
we
define
models because we can define models
pretty much
very precise precisely then
we can uh
consider that the
things these computational models do
is computation
okay the thing these
these computational models do is
computation
and
to
get ourselves familiar
familiar right with the concept and the
use of computational models
we introduced uh final automata in
chapter one and the context free grammar
in chapter two
as actually as practice and also as uh
foundations
for our
later
mathematical development okay
so now in chapter 3
we finally
enter the
real uh
and use the real thing
uh regarding computation which is tui
machine
okay turing machines
and we
we do all this based on the
concept of
here the church tyrion thesis okay what
is church during thesis
basically it is uh
it is a hypothesis that
we
think intuitive notions of algorithms
or actually
what the computation is
equals
turing machines okay or two machine
algorithms as described here okay that
is
all what
computation can do
can be done
by turing machines
and vice versa
what turing machines
can do is computation
that's what we
believe okay
and it is not a mathematical statement
so uh you can you cannot you cannot
treat
it as
a theorem or something it is a
hypothesis it is a thesis that
we think we consider we believe that
computation
is what two machines can do and
all turing machine
can do
is computation
okay
so we transfer
in a way we transfer the discussion
regarding computation on two turing
machines
and
by
discussing the capability and the
limitation of turing machines
we think the result we think the
conclusions
are
applicable to
computation
to what we want to
understand
okay
so
is there any other
computational models
equivalent to turn machines
of course there are
for example lambda calculus actually
proposed by church okay
see
the church to read theses
land of calculus it was proposed by
church
and later they proved that
lambda calculus and the framework of
london calculus and the two machines are
equivalent
then
currently
in computer science we
use
turing machines as our computational
models
uh
more often because
the operations of turin machines
are uh
closer to what we have
uh
to what we have
right now like uh desktop new notebook
computers or something like that or the
tablet even the mobile phone you have
the
underlying hardware the operations are
closer to
touring machines so that's why
in computer science
uh most of time we talk about
computational models we talk about
turing machines
okay
so again
church tuning thesis
into
intuitive notion of algorithms
turing machine algorithms
now think about
uh finite automata and
push down with time time first
uh
basically finite automata
has finite control right what is finite
control
finite control basically uh consists of
a finite
set of string a set of states and it can
process
uh
a set of finite symbols
since the state and the symbols are
finite the transition function the
entries of the number of entries of
transition function
is also finite
right
and
for
let's say deterministic finite automata
there is no
memory
of course you can
in a way you can think of states
as memory
but
you actually had
you actually have firstly finite state
and
when the machine
is defined
basically the
state
the states are not very similar to what
we think about uh storage or memory so
usually we
consider
finite automata a memory less machine
okay it has finite control but there is
no
let's say
programmers
do not have the
do not do not have a
convenient way to
write or read
on some storage so
they are
they have only finite controls
and for pda you can think of pda is
these pdas are interfaced with
stake with a stake right
and the stake is basically
unlimited
memory okay unlimited memory
because we say that okay you can
have infinite
space for on the state
so that's why
pda can recognize languages like uh 0 n
1 n and
greater than or equal to 0 right
why it can do that but dfa or nfa can't
because pdas have unlimited
stake unlimited uh memory but such a
memory is
restricted okay restricted because for
stake you can only
do push and pop
so that would be a
less in first out or you say first in
less out style it is restricted
okay so two machines
has
unrestricted memory that means
it has
some
storage and you can go
you can read any position
from the storage and write
data onto the storage so that's why it
is unrestricted memory you can go
anywhere you don't need to like stack
okay you you cannot directly access some
position of
the data you already stored okay
so imagine that
if we have uh
if we have some
property if we have a machine with the
following property like uh you can
you can write down
let's model the
memory or storage as a tape
okay that's a you know model
that's uh conceptualize the memory or
storage as a tape
then you have
a lot of
blank
space
each
box you can
put one symbol on it into it
and you can write down the tape and read
from it like you have a reading uh you
have a head okay you have a head
on the position of the head of the head
you can
write a symbol
or read a symbol okay and the head can
move
right and
left and right
the tape is infinite okay so you have
infinite uh spaces to prove to
save or to
uh to read from the memory
and
then
the machine well
the the
operation of the machine is
mostly like
dfa pdas it will accept or reject a
string but
it is slightly different when we are
talking about tuning machine because for
dfa nfa or pda you can think of you have
a input machine sorry input
input string somewhere
and every time
the machine gets one symbol out of the
input string
that symbol will be consumed
right and only
when the input strings are all
processed the symbols of input strings
are all processed
we then talk about
uh accept or or not accept
but that's different for from two
machines for two machines it
it works like
you put your input on the tape
before
booting the machine okay like this
so
each tape
space like this
okay
then
the head position is at the
start of the input string
and then you can
let's assume that we have a
we have a turing machine or we have a
machine which can do
the uh four
four
operations
listed here then
we can think of that
when we read zero
when we read the tape and we find that
the
symbol on the on this tape
on this
down on this
space
is zero then
we move the head
close the
line here
because
if we want to
accept strings like
this
you have some zero one string
and
you have a separator
here and
the same01 strings
you can easily prove that this language
is not
regular language
and this language
is not
context-free language either okay
but we can use
the model of turing machine to
recognize such a language easily because
when you read 0 like this example
you just move the head across the
separator
and
oh sorry when you read 0 you just
change it to something mark
some mark to indicate that you have
already processed this symbol and then
you when
you you can go across the separator and
read this symbol
okay
and if it is not a zero then you reject
you reject the string because it cannot
be
like this format right
if it is zero
then you change the symbol to
like x here that means this symbol has
been processed
then you go back
you move the head back to
less position
because you know
this symbol has been processed so you
when he you go here and check what the
symbol is so it is one
then
mark it processed then go
to go acro
across the separator then
read the first unprocessed symbol right
if it is not one you reject you say that
it okay this string is not what i want
it is one
then
you go back
sorry let's try this
it is one then you go back
here then reach next unprocessed
symbol one okay
across the separator and
and read this yes yes it is one
and
go back to this
final last process the symbol then read
next on process symbol
then go here
0 okay go back to here
then next on process symbol
you go back and forth go back and forth
then finally
you will meet blank
okay
this means
that uh
type space
there is no symbol stored on that type
space
okay then you know
there is no this uh
there's no unmatched symbol
on the left and the right of the
separator that means
this part and this part
are
identical so you accept
the string
okay so as long as we have a machine
which is capable of you know the four
operations here write down the tape and
reframe it move the head to the left and
to the right and you have infinite
memory which is conceptualized as a tape
and then
you
put the input string on the tape then
put the machine
and since
since the input string is on the tape
it's not somewhere and you consume the
symbol like
we were doing for
a final automata or a pda
too much the model to machine reject or
accept the string immediately
okay immediately so it's not
the same as we
have in
dfa or
peas
so
let's introduce the formal definition of
a tube machine first then we
start to
discuss something regarding two machines
so a tool machine is a seven tuple okay
looks like look looks like many
uh
components but it's actually the same
thing as pds or dfa okay so the uh first
component is a finite finite set of
states okay it's the same you have a
state state
and the second one is the input alphabet
okay so the language compo is composed
of input alphabet
then we
we require that
the input input alphabet
do not contain the blank symbol
okay
you can think of that there is a very
special symbol we reserved
for the use of
tape blank
okay so you don't have
blank
in your
alphabet in your
symbols to
your
symbols of your languages
there is a special symbol blank symbol
and then
the third one is the tape alphabet
okay what is table alphabet
type alphabet
type alphabet is the symbols which are
which are which will be stored
on the tape
so
like i said
the input strings
will be put onto the tape
then
the machine will be booted up right
so
you will see that
the input alphabet
is a subset of stack sorry type alphabet
okay
and
actually it's a proper subset because
there will
there must be at least one symbol
in tape alphabet
as the type blank symbol
which is not
in
input alphabet
okay
so
for and other than this you can have uh
your
you what you can have the
uh input alphabet you want and you can
have
more than one symbol in type alphabet
which is not in the input alphabet
that's no problem okay
at least you you need you need at least
one blank symbol as the special symbol
which is not in input alphabet but in
tape
above it indicating
the tape space
which is not
stored
there is no input symbol stored on that
type space
okay that's the usage of a blank symbol
and compared to
stack alphabet
of pds if you remember that uh for pds
we also have stake of alphabet it's very
similar because
stack alphabet uh indicates what you can
store on the stack
right
but you will you can
easily see that
for
stick alphabet
in pda
basically there is no restriction
for stack alphabet
we don't even say that or you must have
a dollar sign to indicate the end of
stake because
that part
that part is not
in it's not uh
is not
the
theoretical
is not part of the theoretical framework
it's just a
you know programming uh practice and the
skills
we usually do that because it's easier
for us to write a program for pda
to detect the end of stake but that's
not required by the theoretical
framework
but here
firstly
blank symbol
in
type alphabet
not in input alphabet is required by the
theoretical framework firstly
secondly you will find that
here we
explicitly know that
input alphabet must be a subset actually
a proper subset of
tab alphabet why because you need to put
your input string onto the tape right
and that is not true for pda because for
the first example of pda
our input alphabet is 0 1
right
and
our
stake alphabet what is that our stake
alphabet is actually zero
dollar sign
right as i said dollar sign is what we
want not required actually not required
by framework but you can see that
we have only zero
in
stack alphabet we don't have one and we
don't need one
why because input string is not
required to be stored on the stack for
that pda
if you want to write out another pda
with all the input alphabet that's
that's fine that's okay but for pda
there's no requirement for you to store
all input symbols
on the stack but
for tuning machine you have to do that
because your input string will be stored
on the tape before the booting of the
machine
okay
so that's a
slight difference
then
you have a
spatial state called
star state
which is in the
state of states and
you have
one
accept state
and the one reject state okay
so
there are seven components for turing
machine but of them you know are
there is no
new one here we we just separate all
states here like you have a star state
accept state and reject state okay
and for the turing machine the
transition of the turing machine
is that uh you
from uh
from a state from a state reading the
current symbol
and then you transit
from the state to
probably the other state and you change
you change
the symbol you
read at that exactly position
and
the head
the reading uh
the
head
the tape head
can go left or go right
okay go left and go right
so
it
it is like that for example
for example
uh
the location of the head is here then
you read let's say a
and currently
it's q
nine something like that
then if there is a transition entry says
that
q9
a
you change to q11 and write b
and go left
then
you will change you will read you
add q9 you read a
then you change the a to b
and then you becomes
q11 and the head go
left
okay so the operation just as simple as
this
and according to the transition function
the definition of the transition
function
you know that now
what we are defining
is a deterministic
two machine deterministic turing machine
because
when you see state and the symbol you
exactly
go to
this state and rewrite the symbol as
this one and go left or right
so that's a deterministic next
next step
okay so that's our uh
trim machine in this textbook
and
i have to say that there are many
fundamental
uh
type of two machines and uh what we are
using here is that
uh we assume that there is a single tape
okay
and
we have a left hand
yes the table is infinite but on the
right
so we have a left hand
so we have a left-handed
tape
and infinite
length of the length is infinite
then
for our turn machine the head starts at
the first
the first space and you
in you put input
string
w
on the tape before putting the machine
and all other
all other
tape space are
filled in
blank symbol here like this then you put
the machine so that that is the uh
tim machine described or defined as the
fundamental one in this textbook
in other textbooks there are other
variants okay
for example
there are
for example there is a
two machine
with
three
left-handed
tape
so
input string is
stored on the first one
and the last one used for output
and you have you can do
your your operation
on this
working tape as the second one
so that's that's one one
other fundamental
type of turing machine
or in other textbooks you have you know
open ended
tape you have uh left infinite right i'm
sorry right beneath left infinite and
your head is somewhere here and
that's the
input string
it's also an uh
a fundamental machine for some textbook
basically all these are equivalents so
we hear
the author of our textbook the author of
our textbook adopted
this
for simplicity okay actually they are
not far from each other they are
basically the same
so again
for the volatile machine we have right
now
have
have a
type of infinite length but left-handed
and you are the
initially the head is at let's say the
first
uh space
then you put your input
string on the tape
then put the machine
okay
then to describe
a tool machine or not describe after
define the two machine you use it uh in
action
we can define configuration
to
depict to describe
the two machine in action
okay
and if you look uh think back
regarding
the action machine actions
let's say
for dfa what do we need to know
regarding the machine operation
you need to know
the remaining input string and also the
state of the machine right for dfa as
long as the state is the same
you will get the same result for the
same input
right and for pda you know that
in addition to
state and input string you need to know
the current content of stack
because the content of deck
will have influence on the result of
computation
and
for turing machines we
define a configuration
to
more precisely describe the whole thing
that
a configuration of a turing machine is
considered
is composed of
current state
see you know you must know
the state the current state and then the
current tape content okay
well tab contents include the input
stream and also
anything you change you
add
along the process
and then current head location
okay
so that represents the configuration of
the tuning machine as q sorry uqv
for state q current state okay current
state and
u and v
together
u
and v together is
type contents okay then why do we
separate umv because we want to
represent location together so we put
q
onto
the location of the head that means
u
is somewhere before the head
and the v
is
somewhere
at the head and
you know the later part the right part
of the
head
so we can represent
a two machine
states
now okay the status of two machine like
the type content actually
is
one
zero one one
zero one one one one and don't forget
that you we actually have infinite blank
okay
we just you know
don't write it
we have infinite blank
but
everybody knows that so we
you know just
omit the part
so
if the head here
that means next step is reading 0
we put q7 which is the states
here
to indicate that
we will read zero
and that's
v
that's
u
so that's why we write
the configuration of a turing machine
like
u
q
seven
v
okay like this one
and you can see that we can
write q70
and
call the transition function
and you will get
you know for example if your machine
says okay that will be q9
one and right
then you know that
this one zero one uh one zero one one q
7 0 1 1 1 1
will become what
0 1 1
and
since
q 7
q q 7 will become q 9 and the 0 will be
1 right and go to right right is this
position
so
this 0 will be 1 then q 9
1 1 1 1
so
that's the
transition of the machine to be
expressed as the transition of
configurations
okay
so as a side note we can think of
configuration uh as
well as the
snapshot of your virtual machines
right
it's kind of relatively easy to
introduce the concepts these days
because
everybody has
a
twin machine to play you can have your
hands on two machines
and for tuning machine it's very
convenient that you can do
snapshot right
then
you can think of configuration is like a
snapshot
so
you snapshot the machine then you know
what is the next step and you do another
snapshot or something like that or you
have a notebook
the hibernation is like saving a
configuration so next time next time you
can put up the machine and
restore the configuration back to
the moment you do the hibernation
right
okay
so let's say
if a turing machine can legally go from
configuration c1
to configuration c2 we said that
c1 yields c2
okay
then if we describe the whole thing
formally let's say
for abc
in
[Music]
type alphabet and the uv as tape
the string
of tab alphabet
and qyq is the states of the machine
let's say
q a
u
sorry u a q i b v
and
u q j
a c v are two configurations we said
that
this configuration yields
this one
if
for that two machine there is a
transition function entry
says that if the machine is at qi and
reads b
qi will transit to qj
and change
b to c and the gold left the head goes
left
c
q i
b
q i will be qj okay
and goes left where is left that means
next time you will read a
and this b will be c
so
this configuration yields u and the q j
because your head goes left and next
time you will read a
and then the original b becomes c and
all tab contents
later
then this point will be the same
identical okay
or you have
right right direction
your head will go go right then
the same thing but head goes right so
you see qr will become qj but
head will go here that means next time
it it will read the first symbol of v
okay
and then these are identical and this c
is the b here
and
q y becomes q j
so we have
we have uh
these calculation as the
result of this configuration
after
the transition here
okay
so uh the notation of configurations
have
special cases or the definition of
turing machine in this textbook first
one is that for the left hand left hand
end of the tape
see
since we adopt since we adopt tape model
like this there is a left-handed
left hand left hand end
what if you
encountered a
transition ask you to go left
in this textbook we assume not the head
stay as the first
at the first
position okay
so
let's say uh
for dixie sample
okay if your configuration is like this
then you don't move your head
so that would be q
sorry
q
q j and there's no a here and u here
right
so b becomes c and the v
so q u
q i b v
went through this one becomes q j cv
because we have a left and left hand end
so for
models like this there is no end so it
can go left but in this textbook we
have a left hand
okay then the other special case is that
uh right hand end of the tape
since there is there is actually no
right hand end right because it's
infinite so what what does
what does this sentence the spatial case
mean that means
for example
if you
if this configuration is like this so
it's the last symbol
and don't don't forget that there are
infinite blank okay
so after this transition
they'll be like this
but they are actually infinite
blank right so in this case we will
write
the blank symbol out to indicate that
there are blank symbols so that's just
for
uh convenience so we will write the
configuration in this case u a
qj
blank
okay so you will find you will find that
blank out of nowhere but actually it
they are there
we just don't usually write them out
okay so that's a
well kind of special case
then
for
uh spatial configurations we said that
since the machine starts with start
state and input strings right
so we say that star configuration is the
start state of the machine and the input
string
called that start configuration
and
accepting configuration is that any
configuration of that machine
as long as the state is q accept then we
call it accepting configuration
if the state is reject
q reject we call it
rejecting configuration
okay
and
accepting or rejecting we call them
halting configuration
okay
so it actually uh connects to how the
machine operates like we just indicate
like we just indicate uh
turing machine is uh
two machine
operates differently from pda
dfa
for pda dfa or nfa they
after all the
transition all the input symbols are
consumed then you see the machine
whether the machine accept that string
but for turing machine it's not like
this for two machine you have your input
string on the tape
right
and
input string on the tape and then you
put up the machine
then
the machine
is considered
running and running and running unless
it decides
to accept the string or reject the
string
if it
it decides to accept string it
enters the accept state
that's why
the queue accepts
as long as the configuration has
the state of the configuration is q q
accept we call it accepting
configuration
accepting configuration
if it's reject then it enters
the reject state then we call it
rejecting configuration and only
when the machine enters either one of
the states
we consider the machine halt
okay the machine stopped
if the machine didn't
or
as long as the machine
does not enter either one of the two
states we don't consider the machine
stop
okay that's why we call
accepting or rejecting configuration
holding configuration
so that's basically
uh that's the
fundamental difference between two
machines and all the machines we
previously introduced
and we said that
a two machine accepts input w
if and
if a sequence of configurations okay
exist
where
again three conditions
c1 is the star configuration of m on
input w
and the ck is an accepting configuration
and the hci yields ci plus one
if you
take the definition here and the
compare to what we have for dfa and fa
or pda
it's quite easy to understand right
we say that the two machine accepts
input w if
a sequence of configurations c1 c2
to ck exists where c1 is the star
configuration of mnw
and
hci yields c i plus 1.
let's say for all i
equal 1 2
k minus 1 right
and the final
configuration ck is an accepting
configuration
so that's
what we said that machine accepted input
w
okay
so let's see an example here
so
we said that uh
artillery machine here
we want to decide the language
a
here
okay which means
when n
equals 0 that will be 0 right
when n equal to 1 now b 0 0
and then 0 0 0 0
and 8 0
16 0
32 0 stuff like this this language
okay
so
what we want to do
basically
like description here
we want to design a turing machine an
input string
okay
we sweep left to right across the tape
and
thinking
about crossing of every other zero
okay
after that
if
there is only one zero
except
okay
if more than one
and you know that the number of zeros
was odd
reject
because it is impossible to have
2 to the nth power
0s
right
and then
return the head to the left and
left hand end of the tape
and that's a loop
okay that's what we want to do
and thinking of the
well some kind of algorithm here we
design a tool machine like this
seven tuple right so we have state
and we have q one q two q
three five q except you reject seven
states
and then the alphabet is only zero okay
because the language you are talking
about have
is composed
composed of
only
a single zero
and the tab alphabet we want to have all
symbols in sigma right and
at least the blank
and for the
programming purpose we add one more
symbols here for convenience
then
uh
q1 is our start state and of course q
accept
q reject
right
and for convenience here
we have
we have a
diagram for the transition function it's
just for convenience but it actually you
can write write down all the entries
here right so for example we have
we have q1
reading
right and
sorry
will become what
q 2
let's mark this way okay so that's the
first one
we have the example here
oh i should sorry
the first here
uh i shouldn't do that i should do this
one
yes and q2 and also zero
sorry
blank
and goes right okay
so we use the notation like this here
q1
read zero
change zero to blank
and goes right
okay
so here
yeah
and goes right and also for the second
one here
second entry transition into here we
have
q1
reads blank
right
q reject let's use qr okay
and
we don't write symbol here means we
don't change the symbol so blank
and right
okay
so third one here
so 1 here
q1
x
qr
no change right x
r
okay
so that's the uh
no uh notification
that's the notion here o or
let's say
uh for q4 let's write the same thing
here so
that's
1 okay so delta q 4
reading 0
become
what q3
x
r
and the two
uh to do the blink okay
two
delta q for
blank
goes to q reject
blank no change okay
r
and the
third one here
third one
q4
x
go back to q4
no change
r
okay
so we use the
diagram like this to represent
the transition function for convenience
only
and why do we want to
use the diagram because it's easier for
us to trace
the operation on the input string
so we will do that next time