after introducing contextual grammar and
defining
context free languages as those
languages
which can be generated by context
requirements
remember that in chapter one we
introduced
uh
final automata and said that
regular languages are those languages
generate uh recognized by
finite automata and then we
introduced the definition of regular
expressions
trying to
specify more directly specified
languages recognized by dfa
here we want we also want to introduce
uh abstract machines
which is called push down automata or
pda
okay so uh
the formal definition of pdas
is
that a push down automaton
a sixth tuple
yes one more then uh finite automata dfa
or nfa one more so which six
so first one is the uh set finite set of
states we also denote
it as q and the second one is
the
input the input alphabet which is also a
finite set of symbols
then the third one is a new component
for our abstract machine which is called
stack alphabet which is also
also a
finite set of symbols
then let's say the fifth one is the
start state which is one of
our states then the final one the sixth
one
is a subset of our set
also the set of
accept states okay so the
the uh
the fourth one is the transition
function
which is basically
the transition function for
non-deterministic final automata
and here we add one more com
argument for that function which is the
stack alphabet
and also
probably epsilon string
empty string
mapped to the power set
of q
and
stack alphabet we use the transition
function to
do the
state transition
according to what according to input
and also
symbol on the stack
and
transit to
some state with
doing operations on
the stack
and
pdas
are
fundamentally
non-deterministic computational models
so we map to a power set of all part
actually we map to all possible uh next
moves and you can
chose you can choose the
combinations you want in here
so that's why
powerset is used here
okay so let's see an example and let's
talk about how pdas operate
so here is an example
of a pda
let's formally describe it first
so
there are four states
for this pda
and
the input alphabet is 0 1
the stack alphabet is 0 and dollar sign
okay
and the final accept accept states are
q1 and q4
okay so there'll be four components
already
and the q1
here is our
star state
then transition function here is given
by
the
table here and
blank entries
are all empty sets
that means going to
nowhere so let's say there's a
transition
when the machine is at q2 and the input
the input symbol is zero
then there is an
epstrom
for stake symbol two here
okay
so that's remember that our delta
function the type of our delta function
function is q
product with
sigma epsilon and also stack symbol
epsilon
okay
so
uh this entry is q2
epsilon
which map to the power set of
q
and sigma epsilon okay
so that will be
q 2
0 something like this
okay so there are five transitions for
the transition function
and you know that for any other
entries
that would be
empties
empty set empty set empty set empty set
empty set stuff like that okay
and when we
visualize
this
pda which is m1 here
we can have the diagram as figure 2 15.
so the m1
m1 diagram can be draw can be drawn as
the
the machine on the upper part
so
we have
machines here so how this machine
operate
let's
give an example okay
so you see if you have
a string
if you have a string
0 0
1 1 1
okay
and for this string
we start
from q1 right because q1 is our start
state
and we start from q1 so if your string
is
empty string let's
give a quick example here empty string
it is already accepted at q1 right
because string is empty and the q1 is
accept state and when your input string
is emptied
and you stopped at
stays at
one of the one of the accept states then
the machine accepts that's that string
right so
empty string okay
okay then let's say zero zero one one
and remember that it is an
uh non-deterministic machine so
there is a app there is a
abstract arrow here
but for pds you need to match
symbols on the stack too
so
you
imagine that there is a stack here okay
and initially it's empty
so
we are lucky that there is an also empty
string here so the empty string here
means that
you don't need to check
or you don't need to pop a symbol
the corresponding symbol on the stack
okay
so
because
the criteria are matched so we can go
this way okay we can do this transition
and when we do this transition
transition
the machine
starts at q1 right then when we do this
transition the machine goes to
q2
and in the process
epsilon
is consumed so nothing happened to the
input string
and
epsilon
this apps on the second epsilon from
stack
is popped
or removed
but it's empty string so
stack is unaffected right
and
we push
the other side
to the top of the stack
okay
so that'll become
this
situation
then
we are at q2 now with
zero zero one one one okay
and
this machine is non-deterministic
machine so you need to try every
possible uh transitions so let's try
this transition first but
this
transition asks for
one as the input symbol and now we have
first one is zero right it doesn't match
so
we won't go this transition
and for this one
let's try
input
zero
input zero checked
okay
we don't need to check
stack so okay okay then we go
this transition
so
q2
right and
no need
no need to operate on stack i mean uh
push up sorry pop from stack and when we
go this transition we go back to q2 and
push zero into the stack so the stack
will be
zero
okay
so again you can okay we consume this
one again you can see that the same
situation
all over again so
q2
right
and
consume zero
no pop from stack and push
to stack
right
then again
go back to q two
consume zero
push to uh sorry
no pop from the stack and push to the
stack
okay so let's try again but this time we
cannot go we cannot go
follow we cannot follow the same
transition again because this
transition need input symbol to be zero
but now we have one here
right
so
we have one here
okay let's say if your string on our uh
the if the input string is only zero
zero zero in this case the input string
uh
is processed but the machine
stops at q2 so the machine will not
accept string like zero zero zero
zero right so the machine will not
accept string like this
okay let's go back to our zero zero zero
one one
so
now the only way to go is follow this
path right because the input symbol is 1
now
so for input symbol 1 here
see
you need to match that on the top of the
stack it must be 0 if it's not you
cannot go this way
and luckily we have yes zero on the
stack on the top of the stick right so
when we when we go through this
transition
the machine goes to q3
and consume 1
for the input symbol and 0 popped 0
from the stack so that's 0
1 and 0 means okay then we push nothing
on the stack so only pop
okay
so after going through the transition
our stack content will be
zero
zero dollar sign like this
okay
then we are at q3
so
every time
uh
at q3 you have two possible two possible
transitions
one is
going to q4 and the other is go back to
q3 right let's check q4 although for
the transition here you don't need to
care about input string but you need to
match
dollar sign on the stack
and now since we have zero on the stack
on the top of the stack we cannot go
this way right
and let's try the other one so one
yes
that's uh
checked
okay
then zero on the table stack
checked
so we go
this way once
so
q3
okay and comes from this one
pop this one
then same situation happens again
q
comes from this one pop this one
then you cannot go
through the same transition again
because now you have no transition
same sorry no you have no input symbols
and
the top of the stack
is not
zero anymore right it's the dollar sign
so let's try
the one we previously cannot go through
it doesn't need input okay
then
stack top is data sign in this case yes
so we go to
q4
okay
then
epsilon so no problem and pop this one
so
no empty uh sorry no input
the input string is empty now and the
machine stops at q4
one of the accept
states so we say that
the machine accepts this string zero
zero zero one one one
okay
so when we have symbols here that is a
pop front stack so you have to match the
same symbol so you can pop that symbol
and if we have a symbol
here
that's a push
to
uh to the stack so you push the
corresponding symbol onto the stack
so via the
operation on the stack
the
size of the stack is assumed to be
infinite okay so you have an input
infinite memory only that it is a
memory with restricted access it can
only do first in less out or you said
less in first out that's level or fifo
le4 or
lifo for stack
and also you can see that this machine
doesn't accept
strings like 0 0 0 0 1 something like
this right and it doesn't accept
let's say 0 0 0 0
and 1 1
and
when
the 1
are fewer than zero
let's say
it will get stuck
at
q3 which is not an accept state right so
the machine will not accept this one the
machine will accept
zero and one n
and larger than or equal to zero okay so
that's like this
or if you have
more
let's say
more one
then you also get stuck at q3 right
because you don't see
the other side on the stack
oh sorry yeah
you if you have
more one
then
zero
you see dollar sign on the stick
yes you see dollar sign stick because
all the zero is popped out and you see
down the side when you see the other
side on a stack you cannot go
this transition again because
you have no zero on a stack
you can go through this transition
arrive q4 yes but
the machine doesn't accept the string
why because
the
criteria to accept the string is that
when you arrive when you
stop at
one of the accept states there must
there is no empty string anymore
but in this case in this case
your string will be n uh sorry 1
u
n minus n once the string looks like
this one so
you still have string but you arrived q4
so
and nothing
no transition out of q4 right no
transition out of q4 so the machine will
get stuck at q4 but not accept that
string
and if you have some string like 0 0
and 1 1 zero one something like that
the same thing happened when you have
you know on the first part of the
mixture of the zero one strings
it will not accept those kind of strings
so
we have m1 recognize
this language
and if you remember that this language
is the first example
not
a regular
language
okay
so if you have no problem with
this example let's go back to
check the form of this
formal definition and the acceptance for
a pda to accept a string
so the formal description is like this
one and if you compare this definition
with all those
definitions we have
for
finite
including deterministic final automata
and non-deterministic final automata you
will see
the similarity between these definitions
and
no more
regarding these
computational models
okay let's
see the formal description here sorry
definition here
so a push down automata is
as hours back
so six tuple
we said of push down automata
accept input
w if w can be returned as
n parts
m parts okay
where each part is
either a symbol or
epsilon
and there is a sequence sequence of
states
r 0 r 1 through r m
and
corresponding strings s 0 s 1 to sn
as
strings compare composed of stack
symbols
exists that
satisfy the following three conditions
the strings s i
represents the sequence of stack
contents
first
the machine starts at starts from its
start state
and initially
the stack contents
are
empty
okay empty string
and finally
the last
the last state here is one of the
one of the accept states okay
and
the
second condition is that
for corresponding
part part of part of the string and the
states
we have
ri
with
w i plus 1
and
at that time
the stick
the top of the top of the stick is a
and when you look at
the transition function here
you look up the entry
you will find that
next state
and b
which is
the next
state content
are connected through the whole process
okay
so that is the
definition for a pda to accept
a string
and let's go back to our example to
check that okay
so
we said that this machine accept zero
zero zero one one one
not because what we just described
informally it is because
it satisfies
the definition
okay
we say that this machine
we say that this machine accepts
accept zero zero one one because
zero uh zero zero zero one one one
can be set uh can be
written as
epsilon
zero zero zero one one one epsilon
okay so that would be w one
w 2
3 4 5 6 7
w 8
okay
and we have
r 0 here
r 1 here
2 3 4 5 6 7 8. so q the final one r8
is q4
okay
and what is the corresponding stack
content string
that will be epsilon right
and then
dollar sign
then zero dollar sign
then zero zero dollar sign
then zero zero zero dollar sign then
zero zero dollar sign
zero dollar sign
dollar sign
and
empty
right
so
s0 as 1
s2
3 4 5 6 7 8 this is 8
and you can easily check that
the
string as the
w1 through w8 and we have a sequence r0
through r8 like this
and we have
stack strings
like this
and
they
satisfy the three conditions first one
is r0 is the start state of the machine
right
and our stack
content string start from epsilon
and final one our r8 is one of the
accept string
sorry except uh states which q1 which
are q1 and q4
so
the first
condition the third condition
for the second condition you will find
for any pair
for example
for example when you check delta
r1
which is what q2
and
w3
oh sorry i shouldn't write that
0 and then you have 0 on the stack
it will go to
q 2 and the push 0
right
not not equal sorry it should be a
belong to because that is a set
okay
so for all i
you will have
you will the second conditions are
satisfied for
r0 through r8
so that's why we said
uh this machine
accepts zero zero zero one one one the
string
okay
so for pda m1 you see that
although it's it isn't a
non-deterministic
machine
in fact at any given moment you have
only one way to go if you can go
so
and
uh it is easy to see how this machine
operates you can see that this machine
push o zero when it's this level push o0
onto stack and match
one
with the input string
right so as long as
uh
the number of zeros and the number of
ones are identical the machine accept
that string basically it runs like that
so let's see another example slightly
more complicated
so
the same part
you can see the same parts here
and here okay
then
no matter you see
zero or one you push
on to the stick okay if you zero zero
you push zero if you see one you push
one okay
and
for any
steps
you can
go from q2 to q3
okay there there will be no change on
the input
and the node
no change no match for stack
and and there's no up and no push no pop
on
to and from the stack
so you can see that
for any steps
you always have one more new branch fork
from the process and it goes to q3
okay
and what
does this machine operate at q3 it
matches
input and the tub of stack input and the
top of the stack
right
so every time it
it will fork a new process and try
to think of
this moment
is a
is the split point which you can try to
match the reverse
of
the first part of the input string
so let's say you have a
a string like
0 1 1 0
then
let's make it longer okay so
one one zero something like this
then
you will push on the stack and try to
match this one and fail
and you
have another process going on try this
possibly this possibility and try this
possibility and try this possibility
okay
it will not accept this string so let's
say this one
so when you try
this split point
okay this is a bad example so we we may
should have
it should have this one
okay
and
one more zero here
so
when you try this possibility
you will see that on the stack it should
be 0 0 1 1 0
and
now b
when a process fork at this this moment
0 match 0 1 match 1 one match 1 zero
match zero zero mesh zero and
q four accepted so that is why this
machine m3
recognize the language
this one so first part of the string
first half of the string exactly
uh is
the exact reverse of the second part of
the string
okay and it is not so-called palendra
palindrome
okay
palendron is like uh
w and w are
identical
so they are different
it's this language is a subset of that
because
such
uh
link strings in such language
possible that it's
the length is odd okay
like zero zero one zero zero
it's it's this one but not this one
okay
so anyway
it is uh m3 is another example for the
pda
okay
then we need to have two uh
notes here
first one is that for the uh
for the definition of pdas initially the
stack is empty right
but
it is hard
according to the definition of
pda it is very difficult to detect
if
the stack is empty
we know that it is initially empty but
during the operation of the stack
sorry of the pda
you don't have a mechanism to
detect
the emptiness of the stick
you see
it is this this
this this is not
to detect
to detect if the stack is empty that
means the epsilon here just means we
don't need to refer to the content of
the stick
okay
so there is no way for the programmer
writing transition functions to detect
if currency the stack is empty
according to the definition of pda
so
we usually use a technique that
initially we insert some particular
symbol which is not in the input string
or whatever places we just use a new
artificial symbol
and we put that
into stack
initially
okay
so that's why you will see all the
examples basically in the textbook
we have a spatial symbol dollar sign
here for example and initially we push
that symbol
onto stack
then we know
whenever
we want to check if the stack is empty
we can use dollar sign like this
right like this
so that's one
mechanism here
and the other is that uh
when pushdown automata was proposed in
the literature firstly proposed it is
not it is not defined like we just
introduced
the accept of a string for push down
automata was defined as
when the stack is empty
okay when the stack is empty
but now we want to make all machines
in our course in our course
share the same way to determine if the
machine accepts a string
we use accept states
as
final automata
as in chapter one
so
now
we change to use
accept states
to the to
define
if a machine accept the string
so we can make the definition
for accepting a string very similar
through all the machines
including two machines later
but
in this case the change the change of
definition makes
the
previously proven theorems
no longer
working okay
so in order to solve that
we can make
the you know using accept states and
empty stack
you know somewhat uh
compatible so
you can
also see that
in for the examples in the textbook
when we try to accept
a string
we
pop all the
symbols out of stack of course for these
two examples they are naturally doing
that but
you can always you can always uh
have a pseudo
accept states knowing that now you want
to accept a string and before that you
pop all the symbols because now you have
the capability to detect of detecting
the end of
stack the empty emptiness of the stack
so you can do that
so
that's how we
make
the new definition compatible with the
old definition so that's all
all the
previously
proven theorem still works for the new
definition here
okay so
since we
since we introduced the new machine then
everybody knows that we want to prove
the equivalence between pdas and context
free grammars
right that is
we want to prove that
a language is context-free
if and only if some push-down automata
recognize it okay if and only if that's
a bi-directional
stuff
then
we can say that if we are proof the both
directions we know that for any context
free grammar
the language generated by the context
which is a context-free language by our
definition
you can find the pda
and
the language recognize the pda is
the context
language generated by that contextual
grammar also
if you have a pda
the language generated by the pda
can be written as a contextual grammar
and the language generate by that
contextual grammar is the language
recognized by the pda that's we want
what we
that's we want to prove here okay
so firstly one direction which one we do
if a
language is context free
then
we can find some push down automata
recognize it
okay
and let me note it first if we proved if
we prove this
theorem we know that we will know that
the computational capability of context
with grammar
will be
equal to our that's
then push down automata
that means
the language
of
context free grammar for all g
will be equal to our subset of
all possible
p
something like that
okay so that's one direction and
we will prove
these
later so
so
clearance 220 is proved when they both
are proofed
so that's what what we are going to do
okay so first first thing first
we want to prove that given a contextual
grammar you can find a pda
okay so
uh
it is pretty straightforward for this
direction because we just need to con
convert the given cfg into a pda
and you probably think uh how is that
possible but it's quite
simple if you understand what we are
going to do
we are going to
use pda's
capability of non-deterministic
computation
and try
all possible
derivations
okay try
try all possible derivations
whenever you get some
terminal string you match
with the input string
and when you try all possible duration
then if there is there exists
a derivation
from start variable
to that terminal string as the input
string
then that string
is recognized by the pda
otherwise
it's not
okay
that's what that's the idea we want to
use a pda to recognize a language
generated by a contextual grammar
okay
so idea is like this
you see
we want to
the derivation actually
left most derivation we always process
always try to change
the first
from left to right the first variable
okay
so
we want to expand
the derivation onto the stack
on the stack and the match
input string here
so we push
input string
oh sorry uh
input symbol
to the stack to the stack
uh and match
it with
input string and then when we see
uh sorry we will push variable onto we
push the
expansion of the rule of a rule which of
which the head is that variable and to
the string and the match that generated
terminal strings with the input string
okay
so all the different uh the
leftmost derivation process
are using
stack and you can try all possible then
so
whenever
the body has
remember that for example a becomes 0 1
a
a 0 something like that so
when you see a you push in this example
you push 0 a 1 a
1 0 then you match this one and this one
that's how it works
then you have this one then pop a
and push what a can become
and then doing the same loop all over
again okay
so that's introduced a shorthand it's
not a modification on the definition of
pda it's it is just a shorthand or for
easier to
describe what we want to do
so we say that
we allow
transition like this
or describe with this
simply
because we can
expand
this one into
we match a for the input
match s on the stack and firstly push z
then push y then push x
okay
so after
this this
this uh in fact three transitions
on the stack we see
the e
y
x
on the stack something like that
okay and you go from q to r
and you consume a for the input and
original s on the stack is popped
okay so that's only a shorthand a syntax
synthetic sugar not a change on the
change of the definition of pdas
then
we for a given for given
grammar
for given grammar
we have two kinds of rule firstly
for all symbols for all terminals
in
sigma
we have rules like this
okay
that that is that will be used to match
the symbol on the
stack and the symbol in the input string
and for all rules
for all rules
and for another oh sorry for variable a
we add
all
rules regarding the variable a
as the transition for our
pdas
then
for any possible
sorry this one
for any
given
context-free grammar
we have a pda look
look looks like
this one
start state
then
push
we don't we do nothing to the terminal
string and input string and we don't
need to refer to the content of the
stake we push
the other side as on to the stack which
actually two steps right then
when
the stack is m when we reach the end of
the stack it's not empty yet there is a
dollar sign on it but
when it reaches the
empty stack we don't need to check the
input string then we accept
that string
but remember that when you reach
accept state q accept
the input string must be empty to accept
the original input string okay
if there is any string left as input
string the machine doesn't accept it
okay so that's the
uh that that's uh that's that's
important
and we have transition back
to q loop for rule
and for turbido
okay
so that's the example for the
construction
let's say we have a context three
grammar
st a b
and this s is the star variable and we
have four rules s becomes s may become a
t b or b
t may become t a or
epsilon okay
and according to the construction we can
have
a
pda like this
there is a
middle state
anomalous state here so
we push down the sign push s
and then we pop down the sign
after q loop and for q loop there are
since we have four rules right so the
first rule s may become
a t
b
then this one is t
may become
t
a
right
and
s become b as may become f t may become
epsilon and
the last two rules
for all symbol
in sigma we have a
a epsilon
okay so
the last two is like this
then we have constructed
uh pda for the given grammar
okay
so let's see
a derivation
like
if you have
one star variable and it is possible
that
you become a t b
right
and for t you can become
t a
right
and then you can do that again but we
don't want to do that okay so t
become epsom then you have a a b
right so a b
is one of the string
in the language generated by that
grammar
and let's see if you put aab
into this
pda what will happen
so for pda
it will
push
firstly
uh push dollar sign
on the stack right and the start from
cues q start
then we'll push s
on the stack right
then
and reach q loop
then since
the
table of stack is s you have only
this path
and this path possible
but for the
s may become b it doesn't work
right
let's try it okay
it can you you don't need to consume
a
right
and
you
pop s from the stick let's assume that
we do that you pop s from the stack and
push b in onto the stack you will get
s
b
if you go this way let's say if you go
this way
and after you go this way
the language the string got reject got
rejected you will never have no chance
to accept the string why because
you don't have
a transition for a
for the input symbol and the b for the
stake top right top of the stack
so
there is a
process forked for this way but it will
end with not accepting the string right
you you you still need to go this way
one of the process will go this way okay
and the other process goes to
goes this way
so pop s
and the push what
push b
t
a and go back to the loop right
then since
input string a stack type a you go
these
transition once
back to q loop
and you will have
t b dot sign on the stack
then for t there are two possibilities
one is epsilon right
and the other is
ta
but if you go epson first you will get
data sign b epsilon right then go back
to q loop but
same thing you cannot match is one and
that's a that's n
that's a dead end
so the other way
you go
t become ta now
the you will
push
a
t
to the stack
right
then the same thing happen again this
time let's say we go t may become f zone
so we will have pop t
and
push epsilon onto the stack
right
then
comes soon a a
and comes to
bb
and
the other side shows up then we go
to q accept and we have no
input string anymore
so
this pda accepts
a a b as its input string and you can
see that why it accepts a b
because all possible
left most duration from stop starts
variable
have been
well simulated or been processed
on the stacks
within
our veer all
the possible
forked processes
okay many of them may uh
stop at an a dead end but
as long as one of
the computational paths goes through
stop at the
accept states then the machine accept
the
string
and as you can see that since the
operation of the machine
is based on the left most derivation
so
all the
strings generated by the given grammar
will be
accepted by the machine here and the
machine will not accept any other
strings because
as long as the leftmost derivation
cannot generate that string the machine
will not accept
so we can see that
for any given context free grammar we
can write uh this we can convert it into
a pda like this
so
we know that
if a language is a context tree it can
be described can be generated by a
continuous grammar and then we can
convert that context to grammar into a
pda like we just described and that pda
recognized
the language