next we will be talking about by hill
the road theorem
before uh introduce the this
theorem we need to
define some
uh
we need to define something first
so uh
let's define
a relation
by using a given language
uh
please note that
the language can be any given language
okay so when we talk about the relation
defined by a given language that means
uh
when you specify a language
and you can use
the definition we will be introducing
to
construct a relation
defined by that given language
okay
so
given a language
let's say l
still l can be any given language okay
given a language l
we say that
we can
distinguish
two strings x and y
okay
x and y here are strings
we use arrow to distinguish strings
and how to do that
we say x and y are
distinguishable by l
if
there is a
string
z
concatenate to x and y
exactly one
of the two strings
is a member of l
okay
that means
you have two strings
right and you have a language l
okay
x and y are any strings
and l is a given language
which can be any language but when it's
given
it's given okay
and x and y
have no particular relationship with l
so
when we have an l
to define a relation
which is used to distinguish x and y
and how do we do that
we try
all possible
strings
okay
we try all possible strings how to try
that we concatenate
z to x
and also z to y
if
okay
if there is any string z
makes
one exactly one of xz
and yz
a member of l
that means if there is some z here
max xz
max xz in l
but y z
not in l
or
x e
not in l
and y z in l
okay exactly
one of the strings xz and yz is a member
of l
if such z
exists
then we say that
x and y the two strings x and y can be
distinguishable
distinguished
by l
and also x and y are distinguishable by
l
if there is some z
making them
making them exactly one of them
a member of l
okay
otherwise
if all possible z
if o possible z
we have
xz in l if and only if
y z in l
okay
that's the situation here you have x and
y
and
here is your language l
and you try all possible z
and you'll find that
x z
and y z
are either both in l
or both outside of l
okay
then we said that
x and y
are
indistinguishable by l
okay
so let's repeat that again
so if you have x and y
and
you want to use l
as the relation to distinguish x and y
the process is that you try all possible
z
if
one of the resultant string
in l and the other out
out of l
then we say that these two strings
are distinguishable by l
otherwise they are indistinguishable by
all that means if
you count
for all possible strings the
you concatenate
you append it to x
and
y
the two strings
are either
both in l or both outside of l
then we say that x and y are
indistinguishable by l
okay
if x and y are indistinguishable by l
we write
we use this notation
to denote the relation
okay
in other words
for x and y
we denote x
and y are
indistinguishable by l
if and only if
for
each z
xz
in l if and only if yz in l
with
this construction
for any given language
we can make some relationship
like this
and we can use such a relationship
to distinguish
arbitrary strings
and this relation we just defined
is actually an equivalence relation
so
if two strings x and y are
indistinguishable by l
in a way you can consider
x and y
are equivalent
by using l
or according to the criteria
of l
something like that
okay
and why this relationship
why this relation defined by a language
is
an equivalence relation
because
it satisfied
three
conditions or we said it has the
following three
properties
first one
such a relation
is reflexive
what is reflective that means
every element in discussion
has such relationship
with
itself
okay
so
when you
look at the how we define a relation
obviously
x and the x
always
have
the property like this right
so
any string has
the relationship
the relation with itself
not
many uh sorry not every relation has the
property of reflexive
let's say
everybody knows that uh we have like
greater than
okay
greater than four let's say integers or
values
so
for integer five
it doesn't
such a relation
greater than
has no reflexive relation
uh property right
because
an integer is not greater than
itself okay
for the second property
this relation here
has symmetric
property
that means
if
two
elements
has the relation
x
has the relation with y
y also has the relation
with x
that's called symmetric
okay
so
for x for example
five
is greater than or equal to
three
and you know that
three is
not
greater than and equal to 5
right
so
not all relation
have such property of symmetric
and the third property is
transitive
okay
now the definition here is like
x and what has relation with y this
relation with y and y has this relation
with z then we have x has the relation
with z
so one of the example is like
greater than or equal to
three
and you know three greater than or equal
to one
then
you know that
five
greater than or equal to one
okay that's transitive
any relation
has
the three property
is an equivalence relation
the concept is pretty much the same as
equal
right
so if you check
greater than greater equal and
less than
and
like these operators or this
relationship
you know that only
equivalent
let's say
equal has such
has all the three properties
because you any member is
itself right
and it doesn't matter
if
x
the order doesn't matter okay
and also you have transitive
property
so you have
something like
the concept of equal so it's that's why
we also use the notation
like this one and define it by l
so we can use this way to define
an equivalence relation
okay
so let's give an example here
if the alphabet here is 0 1
as we usually have
and let's say
if there is a language here
defined as
0 string
but no
uh empty string
so
what are
uh
what are these strings in this language
that'll be
zero
zero zero
0 0 0
4 0's
and 5 etc etc right
so that will be our language l0 here
then use the
procedure checking procedure we just
introduced
we can define
a relation
by l0
okay
then we can start
to check the equivalence
based on l0
of any two strings
in sigma star
okay
so firstly we check
zero
and zero zero zero
right
so
let's say
we
for the given procedure actually we need
to check all possible strings
right so let's say what are all possible
string in sigma star
that will be
epsilon
1 0 0
0 1
1 0 1 1 and 0 0 0
etc right
that's all possible strings
then let's try uh some of them
so we can connect absorb
to
the tool string here
then you will find that
they are both in l right
they are both in uh sorry they are both
in l0
then we
try container one that's already zero
here then you got four zeros
they are both in l
both in l
and they're both in l
and then you show one that would be zero
1 there will be 0 0 0 1 they are both
out of l
okay then you try 0 0 they'll become
3 0
4 0
they are both
in air
sorry l0 here
okay
then you try zero one that will be zero
zero one
zero zero zero
1 3 0
2 here okay
they are both out of l uh l0
so
repeat all the process for all possible
string you will find that
as long as you append
a z
without one
without one like
epsilon zero zero zero
zero zero zero etc
the resultant strings are all
uh both in l uh l zero
otherwise as long as the z
has
one in the string
then
both
of the resultant string
are out of arrow
l zero
out of l
zero so
zero and zero zero zero
are
indistinguishable by
l zero here
so they can be constant they can be
considered equivalent
they can be considered equivalent
with the relation defined by l0
okay
so let's try the next one
one one and the one zero one
and you will find that no matter
which string
you select from
sigma star
no matter which string you select from
sigma star the resultant string always
out of l
right
sorry out of l0
so they are the
two strings here are also in
distinguishable by l
because
no matter which string you
append to the two string x and y here
there is no way
to get the situation that one of the
resultant string
is in l and the other is out of l
finally
let's try this example epsilon and zero
zero
okay
so when you append
epsilon to epsilon you get epsilon right
and epsilon is not
in l0
and you append epsilon 2 0 0 you get 0 0
which is in l0 so see that
one is in l the other is not
so they are
these two string empty string and the
zero zero
are
distinguishable by l
in other words they are not
equivalent
with the relation defined by l
l 0 sorry
okay
so you can
use the relationship
you can use the relation defined by some
given language to
distinguish
any
strings
okay so you you need to pay attention to
the definition here firstly
the language used to
define the relation
can be any possible language
second the string to be
checked to be examined if they are
distinguishable by that language
they have
they have no relation
they are they they don't need to be in
that language or not in that language
they are just
some strings in
the possible languages of the given
alphabet
okay
now we have an we have an equivalent
relation
okay
equivalent relation is
well
interesting because
when you use equivalent relation
you can use
when you have recovered an equivalent
relation you can use such relation to do
classification
what does that mean
okay consider that
we
look at
each other i mean all students id
okay our student id
then i said
let's see the last digit okay for
example if your student id is one two
three
four five
six seven
that's that let's see the
the final
the last digit
let's define an equivalent equivalent
relation here
i said okay
if
it's an odd number
then i consider then consider all odd
number equivalent
to each other and all even number
equivalent to each other
so
1 2 3 4 5 6 9
is equivalent to
the relation i just defined right and
not equivalent to like
eight here
but
if you end with
a
the num the student number will be
equivalent to something end with
and
is this using a oddity
odd or even
an equivalent relation yes it is why
because you can check that with these
properties
for r and even
all numbers
have such a relation because
let's say 5
and symmetric of course and transitive
yes right
so we can use add an even as an
equivalent relation
and after you have an equivalent
relation you can using that to classify
all the members you are discussing
so if i use add an event
how many class
i can
classify student id
2 right
all students are all student ids ending
with an odd number 1 3
5 7 9.
is a group
because any student id within this group
they are equivalent
and the other group will be ending with
0 2 4 6 8
and same
all members within
this group they are equivalent
and all members across group they are
not equivalent
okay
so using uh
oddity i can
classify all possible students id into
two groups
okay so that's slightly generalized the
concept here
if i
define
like
uh i check two persons
and if their blood type let's say
we don't want to go into the biology
detail or medicine detail but
if it does say the blood type
there are only four blood type okay
let's say there are only four blood type
then
if we consider
people of the same blood type as
equivalent then
such checking criteria
such judging criteria
can be considered an equivalent relation
and you can classify people into four
groups
right a group of blood type a a group of
blood type b and a b and o
okay
so for many
oh sorry so for any equivalent relation
you can use it to classify
said
okay
and also consider that
if
for all people
i want to
say okay
randomly pick one people
that people will be
a or b or o or a b right
then
if i want to i want to pick another
people
okay and other people
then
these the
the second people
are also one of
a b a b or o right
what if i said okay i want to uh
i want to have a group a group of people
but
all each of them
are
not equivalent according to
the judging criteria here
that means i want to have a group of
people
for example 1 from a and two from o
i don't want them to have to have the
same block type
and how large
can this group be
for
the for the blood type example
this group can
have at most
four
people right
it is clearly that
the largest group in this definition
will be each one
each uh each people for example you have
first people from a second people from o
third people from a b
and the fourth people
from b
and if you have one more people
it meant it must be it must be from one
of the four
possibilities right then
five people will not
make the group
what i want what i want i want a group
in
i want a group
and the people in this group
has no
uh same blood type
okay
so that's
uh do another other example
we again we use student id so ending
with 0
2 2
right
and we
directly use the last digit as the
checking criteria as the judging
criteria
in this way we can
classify the whole
student body into
categories 10 classes right
and how many
people can be in a group that within a
group there's no
students from two different
groups two different classes so the
answer is 10
in this case right because
you can have fewer people achieving
you know people from a different group
but if you have 11 there must be
duplication
okay
so let's go into the details of my heel
and the road theorem
what is my human raw theorem
the theorem describes
let
l be a language
okay
any language
and x be a set of strings
we said that
x
is
pairwise distinguishable by l
if every two distinct strings in s
are distinguishable by l
okay so that's why we explain that i
want to have a group of people
and
any two of them
are not equivalent
okay
so here
you have a language l
which is used as
the judging criteria of two strings to
be distinguishable or not
and you want to have a
string set of string that's called x
and within x
every
any pair for example this one and this
one
are distinguishable and also this one
and this one are distinguishable by all
this one and this one are
distinguishable by l
we call such
pairwise distinguishable by all
the set x
okay
then
how large can this x be
okay so we defined the maximum number
of
elements in any set that's that is pair
wise distinguishable by l
the index of l
okay the index of l
and
what uh
let's say the index of f of l may be
finite or infinite
what is the index of l or what is the
maximum number of elements
of x
according to i just described with
people of
classified with blood type of student id
you know that
how many can be in here
actually the number of classes
the number of possible groups
right
so that means if
given a language arrow
and use l as
a judging criteria
use l to define the relation the
equivalent relation we just introduced
it can
such a relation can classify
all possible string strings
into many different
classes
and how many classes
the number of classes will
be
the maximum number
of
x here
the maximum number of
pairwise set here
okay
then
my here on the road theorem describes
l is recognized
by a dfa with k states
if l is recognized
if l is recognized by a dfa with k-state
then
the index of l
is at most k
okay
that means
see
l is recognized by dfa
is our definition for regular language
right
so
the first thing is
if l is a regular language
then
l
has an index at the most some
dfa recognized l
the num the states uh now the number of
the states of that dfa
will be
else index
okay at most
that will be the upper bound of
else index
and second
if
somehow you know that
the index of l
is a finite number let's say
k
then
the language l is recognized
by a dfa with exactly k-state
okay so you see
if you know
the index of l is a finite number
that means
if you use l
to define the equivalent relation and
then
you use such a relation
to classify all possible strings
and you got
finite
groups binary clauses
let's say k classes
so
the x here is at most k you know that
and then you know that
l the language can be recognized by a
dfa with k states
that means l is a regular language
so
with this 2
we know that
l is regular if and only if it has
finite index
okay
l is regular
if and only if it is important
okay it is important
because for pumping nema
we
because pumping nema for regular
languages is only a
necessary condition
it's not
sufficient so we can only use pumping
lemma to prove some language is reg is
not regular you cannot
use paminema to prove a language to be
regular however
my here on the road theorem is an
is a sufficient and the necessary
conditions
so you can use it to
prove a language to be regular or to be
non-regular
you can use it both ways
then how to use
how to use my healing role to do the
proof
see
the language here is used to
define the equivalent relation
so you if you want to prove some
language
to be regular
you can do that by
using that language
to define an equivalent relation and
and find that
that equivalent relation
can only
classify all possible strings into
finite number
of classes
then that language
is regular
otherwise
if you have a language and you use that
language to
classify all possible strings and you'll
find that you have to classify all
possible strings
into
infinite
groups
into infinite
clauses
then that language
is not a regular language
okay
so
the proof of my human raw theorem is on
textbook page 19.
okay
the prop problem 1.48 page 19
and
facebook actually has
provides the proof to the theorem on 98
so we don't want to go through that but
uh it's
it's not that complicated it just you
can think of the
dfo of dfa operation
you see that
for dfa for language l
if
okay
if it is regular then by our definition
there is a dfa
recognizing l right
then
dfa has finite
states right
star state and sum
accept states
and imagine that for all possible
strings
in sigma star
when you process the
string after every symbol is processed
the machine
will stop
on some states right for example stops
on this state state one
or stop on state 2
or stop on stage 3
and
or step state 4
etc right
then
connect this situation back to our
definition of the equivalent relation
here you will find that
after
stop at
and exception accepts
acceptance straight state
then
if you process x
it stop on this state and the process y
stop on this state
and start again from this state
since x and y reach the same state
no matter what
string you go
next they will
always
reach the same state
right if that state is not
an exception accept states then they are
both not in l
they are both out of l
or
that state is n accept states
then they both are in l
so
for language for regular language you
can easily see
how the definition
connects to
the result
anyway here we want to introduce how do
we use this theorem to prove the
language
regular or non-regular
so here is how we use it
given a language b
that's construct at the relation
equivalence relation
here by using b
okay
then
you just prove
b is a
if you prove that
b has a finite index then b is regular
if b
has infinite
index then b is not a regular language
okay
let's go for an example of
of the one we are proved by using
palmileima for regular language
that is
b
0 and
1 n
right
and
[Music]
okay
because this language is our target
so we
use this language to define the
equivalence relation
okay
then the next step is we want to use
this equivalence relation
to check
all possible
strings
okay to check all possible string
but all possible strings are you know
slightly difficult
to discuss as a whole
so
the idea is
we
select a subset
a subset
from all possible strings
okay
and the idea is that
if
if the subset
of all possible strings
has already
classified into infinite numbers
infinite number of classes
then of course
the whole
sigma star has to be classified
into infinite clauses then b
has
an infinite an infinite index
right that's our goal
so which subset we should choose
let's say we choose
a subset
and
let's do it this way okay
we choose this subset
out of sigma star
okay again why do we want to choose this
subset
we choose this subset to discuss how
many class cars classes
whale
this
equivalence relation
generate
okay
if
using b as the definition for
equivalence relation
has
to classify the subset into infinite
classes
then
that equivalence relation must
class
classify the whole sigma star into
infinite classes
it doesn't make sense to
have fewer classes right it must be
greater than or equal to the number of
classes
okay
so
how do we discuss how many how many
classes we need
by using the equivalence relation
well in this case kind of tricky
consider that
we pick
any two different
strings
from
from this class
but sorry from this
from this
subset of all possible strings
okay
first one is i zeros and the second one
is j zeros and
i
is not equal to j
okay so in this case let's say x
and y
okay
then we need to try all possible z's
to see if they
if the resultant strings
are both in l or out of l or you know
one of one in l the other is not
something like that
and you will easily find that
there exists
a string
z
actually two z's in this case actually
two but let's say
when z is
one i
okay
i once actually
x what is xz
xz
will be
0i
1i
which is
in
b
and y z
is what is the row j
one i which is not
in b
right
so the other z will be
j once
right that will make
x z not in b and y z in b
okay
by our definition we know that
zero
i r
and the uh
zero j are in the are distinguishable by
b
so they are
what
they are they are distinguishable by p
and
you can easily find out any different
any different strings in this set
are
distinguishable by b
right
so
let's name it x
big x okay capital x
so
x here
is really
a pairwise distinguishable
uh it's really a set of string
that is pairwise distinguishable by b
and how large is x
here
actually the cardinality the size of x
is
infinite
right because arbitrary m here
so
we know that
b
has
an infinite
index
since b
has
an infinite index
we know that b is not
a regular
language
okay
so
remember that
the language we want to prove to be
regular or not regular
is
used to define
the equivalence relation
then
we are discussing
how many classes can be classified by
using the
equivalence equivalence relation defined
by the given language
we prove that language to be regular or
not
by checking
the size of the maximum size of the
pairwise distinguishable
set
okay so that's how we use my heel
the road theorem
and by using my heel on the road theorem
we can
prove some
language that is not
that is not
regular
while
we cannot use pumping lemma for regular
language to disprove it
for
an example of this kind of language you
can check on textbook
the third edition textbook
okay p page 19
sorry page 90
oh what am i doing
page 90
one problem 1.49
that language
has pamping leima
has the properties of pumping lemma for
regular languages but it's not regular
and we
we cannot use pumping lemma to disprove
it
while we can use my human raw theorem to
disprove it
as regular language
you