in the beginning of chapter 5 we talked
about the concept of reduction
reducibility and we said that
if a problem a
reduces to problem b we can use a
solution
to b to solve a
so that's
basically regarding the concepts of
reduction and
we say that reducibility says nothing
about solving a or b alone
and we further introduced that
when a
is reducible to b
solving a cannot be harder than solving
b because a solution to b gives a
solution to a and we basically believe
that
the difficulty of problems
cannot be
diminished uh diminished or reduced by
converting the problem itself so
solving a cannot be harder than solving
b
in
in the sense of uh in terms of the
relation we can know that
conceptually okay conceptually
if b is decidable
then we know that a is decidable because
solving a cannot be harder than solving
b also we know that a is undecidable
then we can know
b is undecidable
but all of these are
concepts
okay
and it doesn't mean that the proof we
we've already done in this chapter are
invalid
it doesn't mean that because the
validity of the proofs we have done
until
now
is is based on
uh proof by contradiction
we actually what we actually did
what we actually did are a lot of proofs
uh
proven by the technique of contradiction
right so it's not
it's not um
it's not about
using reducibility itself
as proving
uh as proven
technique
or
proven method
okay
so all the proofs we have done
are basically
by contradiction
so
that means
we want to prove
something is undecidable
we use atm or some other maybe etm
some other
known undecidable problems
and
we use b
to solve a that is we assume b is
decidable
then we can use b to solve a so
a becomes decidable that's a
contradiction
we use this kind of contradiction to
prove that b
is undecidable that's
about all the proof we have done in
chapter
five and here
in the last part of
chapter 5 we will be talking about
mapping reducibility
that is we will formalize
we will formalize
reduction
reduction and use that
directly
in the proof
and then we know we
won't
we won't need to use contradiction
anymore we only need to
uh give the existence of reduction then
everything
is proved okay
so what is mapping reducibility we say
that
being able to reduce problem a to
problem b by using
a mapping reducibility okay now we want
to define this term
means that
a computable function
which will be called reduction
okay
a computer the computable function is
reduction
if a computable function computable
function
exists that
converts
instances
of a
two
instances of b
okay
so let's define computable function
first what is computable function
well we go back to our computational
model which is turing machine right so
a turing machine computes a function by
starting with the input to the function
to the tape
okay so the same model here you have a
turing machine and
you have a tape
and the input string
is on the tape okay so that's the same
model here
and then you start the machine and the
machine process the string
but different from what we already uh we
are you the model we are using
this turing machine
does not uh report accept or reject
this type of tube machine
just stops
okay just stops so
after it completes the computation it
stops and when it stops
when it stops
what's left on the tape
is the output
of the function
okay so
imagine that you have a turing machine
and you input a string on the tape
and
after
it finishes
the computation
it stops
you can uh imagine that there is a
specific
state
maybe host state then after entering
that state the machine stops and what's
left on the tape is the function
is the output of the function
represented by the turing machine so you
can consider the machine
the function itself
okay
so
if you have
a function
that can be implement
implemented by using a turing machine
we call such a function
computable function
well because we are using tuning
machines as our computational model
right so what turing machine can do is
computation so if you have a function
which can be
done
with
turing machine by using turing machine
then we call that function computable
okay so that's a
that's pretty straightforward so again
let's say a function
from string
to
string
is a computable function
if
some turing machine n
on every input string w
holds
with
f of w on the tape
okay
so again you can define all kinds of
string
mapping to string functions right
as long as
a function
for a function you can find the turing
machine m
for every possible string
for a possible string
you input the string on the tape and the
starter machine after
the computation
the machine will leave
the motion will leave the output on the
tape then we call the function
computable function
okay
with the help of the
definition of computable function now we
can define
mapping reducibility formally
so we say that we say that
language a
is making reducible
maybe irreducible to language b
a language is a set of strings right so
a language a is maybe reducible to
language b
we were using the notation
like this
okay using a notation like this
because we believe that
you know conceptually
the difficulty to solve a
is less than
or equal to
to solve b
so we use the
symbol here and
we said that it's mapping reducibility
by using mapping reducibility
we said that the difficulty for solving
to solve a is less than or equal to soft
beat
something like that
so we say that language we say that the
language language a is maybe indivisible
to language b written as
a may be reducible to b
if there is
a computable function f
if there is a computable function f
for every
string here
if the string
is in a
then f of w is in b
if f of w is in b
w is in a
okay so that's a
if and only if
relation here
then we call the function such a
function
the reduction
of a to b
okay so again
the function is a computer function that
means there is a turing machine
able to
calculate or to compute that the
function okay and the requirement for
maybe
for mapping reducibility the requirement
for this function is only
such a relation
okay
don't overthink regarding the relation
okay the relation is as simple as it
seems
as long as the function uh the
input string is in a
the output is in b
and only if the input is in output is in
b the input
must must
be in a
okay what uh did i mean by overthink
such a relation has no unto and one to
one
don't overthink there is no unto there
is no one-to-one relationship here
that means
if you have a language a
okay
and you have a language b here
okay this function sorry this relation
only talks about
if you have a string in a
this string can
must be mapped into something in b
right
and if you have a string out of a
this string must be
mapped to something
out of b and that
and that's it
nothing more
because uh
previously some students uh thought that
you know if uh
different strings
in a
should be mapped to different strings in
b
no
okay there is no such thing here
for this relation
it can be
all strings in a map to one
string in b
that's okay okay that is okay
and o string outside of a
map to some string outside of b
then this relation
is satisfied
okay
there's nothing regarding every string
in b must be mapped no
so
don't overthink
okay
so the relation here
strings in a map to strings in b
and
strings not in a map to strings not in b
that's it
okay that is it nothing more
don't think about uh
well
i need to map to every string in b no
the computable function is only
responsible for
mapping all strings in a
to some strings in b and authoring out
of a to some string out of b
that's
about it
there is no need to one to one
and ang 2 or something like that no
okay let's go back to the definition
here so again we said that a language a
is maybe reducible to language b
if there is a computable function
for every string
belongs to a mapped to
some string belong to b and out of a to
out of b okay so that's the
uh if and only here and we call the
function the reduction
of a to b
okay
by using such a definition
by using such a definition we can
directly
prove
a theorem here
5 point
we can say that if a may be reducible to
b
and
b is decidable
we can prove that
a is decidable
okay
see now we can do the proof here we
cannot do that in the beginning of
chapter 5 because we don't have
a definition here
oh by the way actually there are other
reduction
definition
okay some of them may
including the requirements of of
one-to-one or some other requirements
but
those are not discussed in here
here we only discuss about
mapping reducibility okay
so
let's prove uh theorem 5.22
the theorem
again
if a is mapping reducible b and the b is
decidable
okay given the two
criteria here firstly we know that b is
decidable right so there is a decider
for b we call it m that's a turing
machine
and
a is mapping reducible to b
so there is a reduction from a to b we
call that f and don't forget that by
definition f here is a computable
function that means
there is also a turing machine
able to compute f
okay
then you know based on the tool machine
here
based on the two machines here we can
construct a new turing machine and
for
its input
firstly
we call f
and
by definition the turing machine
that can compute f will
hold and with the output f of w on the
tape
right so imagine that
the machine will construct
for its own
input here
then after calling f
after calling f we will have
f of w
here
right
we you know you can simulate f and
the behavior becomes f and we will
process w and finally the machine stops
the machine holds we get f w on the tape
as output
okay
then the next step
we call
m which is
the decider for b
and f w
okay
and remember that m is a decider for b
so m will tell us
f of w
belongs to b
or
not belongs to b right
and there will be
uh
m well definitely stops because it's
just decider
so we we know there there
the answer is either
f of w in b or not
and according to
the computable function f here
we know that if f of w is in b we know w
is in a
if
f of w is not in b we know
w is not in a
right so we just output whatever m
output
then
and here and here
is clearly
the decider for a
because for its input
the answer of n
will be accept when w belongs to a
will be
and its answer will be reject well
when w is not in a
okay
so
a is decidable because we can construct
the decider
for a
by using
the computable function
and decider
for b
okay
so
we can also have
a theorem here that
if a is mapping reducible to b
and
we already know that
a is undecidable
we know now
definitely b is
undecidable okay b is undecidable
and
you can apply theorem 5
2.22 with the contradiction stuff and we
can know
this one
right
because you can always construct this
one
and
assume b is decidable then m exists
then
n exists and is a decider for a but you
already know that a is undecidable so
b is undecidable okay so that's about
the proof
by contradiction
too
okay now
by using
uh sorry
which one
now by using the mapping reducibility
the definition
of mechanical disability and the theorem
here we can re we can
directly prove
what we already have of
previously
so firstly
let's say
okay in addition to decidable we can we
can also do recognizable okay we can
also do recognizable so if a
is mapping reducible to b and you
already know that b is too recognizable
then a is too recognizable so
the same
the same thing goes to
send proof process you just need to be
[Music]
you just need
to
change the word here
as
recognizable recognizer
and the same thing here and the end
here will be
the recognizer for a
let's go through it again okay so
if a
is
maybe reducible to b and that you
already know that b is recognizable
then we have a transmission n as a
recognizer for b and also f
the reduction from a to b
then we construct n here and first the
first first step is to calculate to
compute f of w then we have f of w on
the tape after the machine for f
holds
right then we run
m on f of w
but here the process is a little
a bit different remember that now m here
is not decided anymore it's a recognizer
so
if you run
this step there will be three
possibilities one accept
right two reject
three runs forever
so if accept
you know that f of w
in b then you know that's w
in a
if reject you know that f of w is not in
b
and you know that w is not in a
okay actually only the first condition
[Music]
we only need the first condition to
fulfill to satisfy the requirement of a
recognizer
right
because
all strings in a we got the answer of
accept
okay but
we further had we have further have the
second condition that
if the string not in a we know that in a
but sometimes that's sorry not in b
sometimes for string another in b you
got
running for every result in this case
since that string is nothing a
and
n
also runs for error because n runs
forever
then n will never accept those
string
so
you know the definition of recognizer is
satisfied so n
is the recognizer for a so a is
recognizable
so basically the same content here
we can use to prove also
theorem
2.5.28
okay 5.28
then
the same thing goes to if you already
know that
a is not
too recognizable then b is not too
recognizable and also using the same
process for
uh to do proof by contradiction
okay to do proof by
contradiction
[Applause]
and let's go back to
visit the
hold the tm2 atm
sorry proving for the tm to be
undecidable
proof
remember that
in the
previously we said that if we have
if we have a decider
for hold tm if we call that decider m
or m is not a good symbol here that's a
decider n
then we can use n
to construct atm design to help us to
construct a decider for atm right how do
how how did we do that we said that
for
a pair of machine
for a pair of machine and input
we send it to
n
to check
if m
on w
will stop or not right because whole t
the decider for whole t
is supposed to tell us whether or not m
will be
will hold on w
if
no then we know that
w is not
w will not be accepted by n then we can
say no
if yes
then we really
do
simulation
of n on
w
and but it's a safe simulation because
you know it will hold right and after
hold we report that if m accept w we
accept the pair if m reject w will
reject the pair then such a machine is
definitely
a decider for atm
then we
as we just described the whole proof
here
is established
on proving
by contradiction
because atm decider cannot exist so
how tn decider cannot exist so whole
team is undecidable that's why the proof
is correct okay
and we explain the concepts regarding
reduction there
however now we have the definition
for mapping reduction
we can say that
as long as
we present
a computable function f
as long as we present
then
see here
go back to here
we said by definition we said that
here
by definition we say that a is mapping
reducible b
if there is a computable function
providing such
relation right and that's the reduction
so as long as such function exists
a is maybe reducible to b by the
donation
and we further have sorry we have
further have this theorem
describing that
if a is maybe irreducible to b and the
b is undecidable
a is undecidable also
if a is mapping reducible to b
a is undecidable
then b is undecidable
okay
so you see if we already know atm is
undecidable
we want to prove
anything
for example problem p
any problem here to be undecidable
we want to establish such relationship
and by the definition here we need to
provide the computable function
providing
this relationship
so as long as we find we find we
establish or construct a function
providing such relationship
by definition atn
is mapping reducible to the problem we
want to prove to be undecidable
then calling these
corollary
we prove that problem is undecidable
that's how it works okay so now
by using mapping reducibility
we already know atm is undecidable
right atm is undecidable
then what we want to do is to establish
to establish
this relationship
between
atm and hold tm
and to establish less the relationship
we want to
present we need to present a computable
function
providing
the relationship
as this
okay and don't forget that the uh the
input for the machine for atm or whole
tm is the whole string okay
so
as long as the given input
is in atm
if and only if
the output is in hold tn
if we can
establish or construct a function
providing this situation
by using the
corollary there and the definition of
mapping usability we proved that
the problem here is undecidable
then how to present
a computable function a convoluted
function
is
compute computed by a turing machine so
again we construct a turing machine we
call f here
okay
so on on input
a pair of machine and input string
let's construct another turing machine
okay
so let's
write the program of the turing machine
here on its own input
on its own input
this machine
simulates the given machine m here
on
its
own
input okay
then
remember that there will be three
possibilities okay first one if n accept
the input of the machine
then
we accept
if m rejects
then m prime
enter a loop that means
runs forever
okay
and there will there
is the third party possibility here for
and on w never
stops okay m on w
never stops
so
these two case will be
the same
from the outside view right because
no matter this case or this case you
will see
if
n prime is running then it runs forever
anyway we send the source code
with the input w here
to our output as our output
okay
so
don't be confused
by
this step
okay don't be confused confused by this
step
there is no
process running here
we are
writing
a program okay
all f
o f does
is writing
a program called
m prime
f
doesn't
run
m or even m prime
f is just a string process
program
it reads m
you know as a program and reads w
and it outputs a program code
of m
n prime
only that
the program code
in the program code
we
intend
we intend
to run and on x
but actually we didn't do that okay
it never happened it just runs in code
just like
you open your text
editor
and write a c program and in your
program you write
for
something like this
maybe this
and
assume that it will
do an infinite loop
okay but you you you didn't you you will
not
actually run this program
you just output the program code
okay that's the key part
here
if you are confused regarding this code
many students
in previous semesters
they think how did how can i write f b
uh since
m on x will possibly you know run
forever
well the point is
you only write down the code you didn't
run that program
okay that's the key part
so
we write a program f which read the
input here
and
construct a program
here
you copy m here you copy w
uh no
you copy w here
and you
output
and source code and w as your output and
your program is done
okay your program is done
nothing more to do
so
you always can
write down such a program
right
and we know that
a turing machine f here
for its input
and its output
the input the relationship between the
input and output
does
have
these property
why
because if it's in atm
that means
the program we write
well
stops
on
w
so it's well
in
hot tn right
and vice versa or you can think that
if m
not in atm that means either
enters a loop
or
these steps is a loop
right
two possibility here
if n
w the pair
is not in atm
either and reject w
then m prime
enters
a loop
itself
if m
directly runs on w as long as will be
well runs or ever then
the loop
automatically creates without our
uh
manipulation
then
m prime w is not
in whole tm
so uh
it's w here
so we do
have such a relation among the between
the input and output of
the material machine f
solution machine f
is a computable function providing such
relation
since f exists
so
according to
the definition here
and theorem here sorry now this one
theorem here
we
give the evidence that
atm
is membrane reusable to hold the tm
right that evidence is f
we construct it and atm is undecidable
so hold the tm is undecidable that's how
we prove the theor proof the
undesirability
of halt tn via the uh help
of maple disability
okay
then let's go back to the recognizable
part
and
we want to prove something interesting
that
eqtn
is neither too recognizable nor code to
recognizable
okay that means
eqtm
is not too recognizable
and the eqtm bar
okay so that means equity is you know
uh
super difficult
it's totally out of our
uh
our touch
so
sorry
to prove that we need to know uh we need
to establish something interesting
okay
so uh
remember that i remember i what i just
described that
maybe reducibility
let's say a
and b
is the existence of a computable
function making something a to
something in b
and
something out of a to something
out of b
right
nothing more okay so you have this
f here
so what uh then we we
denote the relation like
a is maybe reducible to b
right
okay so what's interesting
here is that you see
out of a
out of b
in a in b
then
exactly the same function here you don't
need to change anything
exactly the same function here
a bar b bar
right so something in a bar
that is out of a
will be mapped to something out of b
that's something in b bar
also something
out of a bar
that's something in a
will be mapped to something in b
that's something out of b bar
so as long as we have the relation
a is maybe reducible to b
the exact
the exact function
provide us a
bar
is maybe reducible to b bar
right
so we shouldn't consider complements as
uh
negative or something or minus because
they are different
you see
with the existence of the same function
as long as we know a is mapping
reducible to b
we also know that a bar is maybe
reducible to b bar
right
so that's very interesting
and how is it because we can then use it
with
this
theorem
see
previously we established that
two
languages to be
not too recognizable right one is atm
bar the other is what uh the other is ld
right so we have two instances
not too recognizable
but
we want to prove other languages to be
not too recognizable it's kind of
difficult because
the concept regarding
not too recognizable is that you don't
even have an algorithm to correspond to
that problem
that's very you know abstract and very
difficult concept
but with the help of the
theorem here
we can plot atm bar here
right
and to prove something else
not too recognizable because we know atm
bar
is not too recognizable and then as long
as we can establish the
relationship regarding atm bar with some
other language we can prove some other
language to be not too recognizable
right
but
atm bar
is itself
difficult to understand
atm is easy
right because what is atm
that means you have a machine
input pair if the machine accepts the
input then
the
string
is in atm the language
but bar
not only
reject not only runs forever
it also contains remember that step zero
you need to do you know format checking
or something
many other things that
is not valid machine value input
something like that
they are all
they are all in atm board
so it's very difficult to
catch them all in some simple sentences
or
concepts
however
according to
the mapping reducibility we just
described
if we want to establish
the relationship
of atm bar of some language
if we want to
do this
we want to find a
reduction for the mapping new recipe
making reduceability here
the task
is exactly
the task is exactly
finding the reduction from atm 4 bar to
b bar
right
so double complement is the same the
original
language right
so
we can change our task
to an equivalent task that
if we can find
a reduction from atm to
some language
to some language
effectively
or to some complements of the language
if we can establish the relationship of
this
that is we find
the computable function for doing the
mapping reversibility
then equivalently we find
we establish
atm bar is mapping reducible to b
and then we prove b
is
not turing recognizable
not too
recognizable okay
so
go back to the question we want to solve
here
if we want to prove eqtm
to be
not too recognizable
what do we need to do
we need to
find
a reduction from atm bar
to eq
tn
right
by doing this we can
prove eqtm is not too recognizable
then we want to do this
doing this is equivalent
to
doing
this
right
so
because
the relationship here
using the same function exactly is then
function
so first step
we find we construct a function
doing the atm mapping reducible to eqtm
bar
to prove
eqtm is not too recognizable
that's the first thing we want to do
here okay don't be confused
so
see we now now we want to
do
eq atm is reducible to eqtm bar
that's why
okay that is why
so
we construct a tuning machine here
on the input
remember that if it's in atm we want to
make something in et eqtm bar
okay
so
we
produce
a turing machine m1 always reject
so
the language of m1 is empty set
okay
and we also construct two machine m2
on any input doesn't matter
m2 just wrong
and on w
and still don't be confused by
by the code it's just the program code
it doesn't mean that we really runs the
program
okay we just think about it
so
if n accepts w then m2 accept
then what is the accept here the second
accept that means m2 accept
its input
so doesn't matter which input as long as
m except w
lo of m2 is all possible string
okay
if m does not accept and uh does not
accept w then what do we have we have l
of
m2 empty set
right
so m on w the behavior of lnw is a
switch
switch between these two behavior
now you see
if m on w
m accept w
if m accept w
then
l of m one
is not l of m two because l of l1 is
empty set l of m2 is all possible
strings
if n
does not accept w
whether reject or runs forever
l of m1 is still empty set but
l of m2 now is empty set so they are
the same
so
m1
and m2
here will be in eqtm
and the not in eqtm bar and here in eqtm
bar
right
so f is able to provide such reduction
from atm
to
eqtm bar
then we know that atm
is mapping reducible to
eq
tm bar
and
this function here also provides the
same relation to
atn
is maybe reducible
sorry atm bar is maybe reducible to eqtm
therefore
we can prove eqtm is not turin
recognizable
okay so that's why the proof
is written this way
then we also want to prove that
eqtm is
nowhere called recognizable that means
eq
m bar
is not too recognizable either
so we go through the same thing we
provide another
computable function
but this time remember that we want to
prove
atn we want to establish the
relationship that atm bar
can be
maybe reducible to eqtm bar
to prove eqtm bar not recognizable too
recognizable
and the same function
provides
this relationship
so g
we using this and
gets this okay
so now
atm
if this string is in atm
we change
what we have m1
previously to here always accept
so m l of m one here is all possible
strings
then
m two here is the same
if f of m two uh if n accepts
w
of m2 is all possible strings otherwise
is
empty set
so if accept
they are in eqtm
if not then not in
eqtm
so we establish
the relationship like this and the same
function
it used the same function g here
provides this relationship
so we now know that
eqtm
bar
is not too recognizable either
okay
so
you can see in this theorem nut
with the help of
serum
2.28 and 2.29 we only need to establish
the relationship of two languages and
then we can have conclusions on
the other language
or
depends on which one you want to prove
okay
then according to all we have got we
know that
a language
and its own compliment
has only
okay let's talk about
decidable
undecidable
and but recognizable and outside
and not recognizable okay
so
you have only three possibilities here
it's not
there are three regions one two three
but it's not nine
possibility there are only three
that
a language either
complements and itself
are both indecidable
yeah because if
a language is decidable the complement
is decidable too right the same decider
you only need to reverse the answer of
the decider then you got
decider for the complement
so
the language and its own complements are
either
both in
decidable
or
both in
not decidable sorry not recognizable
like
eqtm we just proved right eqtm is here
eqtm bar is also here
also here
and
the other possibility is like atn
you have one in
here which is undecidable but
recognizable
and your compliment must be outside of
right
because
these
if it
falls into here
then atm becomes decidable we have proof
we have proved that right
because if you have a
language recognizable and
co-recognizable
that language is decidable
so it cannot be in this region
of course cannot be in this state region
so it can only be in this region so a
language and its own complement
are either both decidable
or
neither
itself nor its complement is too
recognizable
and over the final
possibilities that one is
recognizable but undecidable and the
other is not even too recognizable
okay
so
we have finished
chapter 5
and that's about the
computability
we want to talk about
so using turing machine as computational
model now we know
we have some problems that can be
in theory can be compute
basically we think that uh decidable
and
we have some problem
undecidable but recognizable well you
can think you can consider it like
we have a limited capability of solving
such problems
and finally we have a lot of problems
actually
not too recognizable that means we have
many many many problems we
[Music]
to which we cannot even write any
program corresponding to those problems
so that's our uh discussion
on computability