now let's uh
take a look at some examples
of problems in class mp okay
so the
first examples we want to introduce is
called
click
okay so what is the problem click
uh the problem of collecting is that
given
an undirected graph okay given an
undirected graph
and
specify
an integer
of course positive integer
integer k
if the undirected graph
has a k click
then we say that
the input string is in the language
okay
for example
if the graph
we are given is
like
like this one okay
so
well
if k is one what is one click okay uh
click is basically complete graph okay
so if k is one of course
there is one click right this one is one
one
uh complete graph of one note
and this one is also
a complete graph and this one is also a
complicated well it's a trivial uh
trivial quite a trivial question right
and then if k is two
then
this part is a two click and this part
is also a two click
right
then what about
k
is three
okay if in this case case three
then this graph has no
three click
right this
this one has no three click
so
this graph
three
is not
in click
it's not included okay
for another example here if we have like
graph like this one
okay
so
of course one click to click no problem
is there any three click yes there are
about i don't know
one two three four five there are five
three
so of course if
this graph with three
then it's in click
in this language
and how about four
actually there is a full click here
right
since four click is like this one
so this graph
four
also in click
but if k is five then it's not right
there is no
five notes
as a complete square
okay so click is that your problem given
an undirected graph and
uh specified
um
a positive integer
is there a k click within the given
underrated graph g
okay
and firstly can you write a decider for
that if no concern of running time of
course you can right you can try
let's say if the graph here
g is vertex and h right
you can try all possible
set
on the graph
and
if
any one of the combination is a complete
is a complete graph
then
the input string
is
in click
okay so there's no problem to solve this
uh well for computability there's no
problem now we are talking about
click is in mp
right
and
to prove that click is mp firstly we can
follow our
well as i called new
new deformation okay that is if we can
find a polynomial time verifier for
click then
uh click is in mp
okay
so
let's construct the polynomial time
verify here and for for
permanent time for verifier we can ask
for extra information right
so
in addition to the
string w here which we want to determine
if it is in click or not
we ask
certificate
and the certificate we ask here
is exactly the k notes
which forms
the click on the graph on the given
graph okay
so
based on these
criteria
our first step is to test
whether
c
is a set of k nodes in g
so how the test can be done
you just need to go through
the node specify in c right and the
check
okay note
if the amount is correct right k notes
if it is then you check if the first one
in g
second one in g
third one g etc
and there is no duplicate within
the node specified in c
okay let's do this test first
and how much time you need to do the
test uh to do to finish the test
it must be well within the polynomial
bound of the length of g
right you just need to
since there is only k at most k
nodes here
if it's more than k you can know that
it's a wrong certificate you just need
to reject it so you don't need to
process further right
then
at most k note here
and you just need to go back
go forward on the tape and how long is
the length here
it's about
the length of input length so there's no
problem
so you will be able to do the check
within polynomial time of the length of
g
actually input string
right it's g and the k
then
if certificate c
contains actually k nodes in g
then we check
if
the k nodes specified in c
according to g's h
g
is v
e right you check you check the e so
for k note specified in c
we check if this node connects to this
node by using e
and check
one two three to k right check one two
connect it one three 1 4 etc then 2 3
2 4 etc then 3
4 3 5 etc
of course you need about k square to do
that right but k
is well within the whole string the
polynomial bound of the whole input
string so there's no problem
so we test the g
contains all
edges connecting all the nodes
in c
if
both
steps
are okay
of course then
the k nodes specified by the certificate
is really the k click on
the undirected graph g
so accept
otherwise
any
thing goes wrong
anything goes wrong then we just reject
so that's our
verifier and as we described it the
verifier
must be
finished up
must
well finish its uh
execution within the polynomial time
bound
okay
because the whole thing is
straightforward and
you you can actually calculate how many
uh well approximately how many times you
how many times how much time sorry how
much time you need to finish the job
okay
and
alternative proof
that is we use the old definition
we construct we can try to construct a
non-deterministic
turing machine running in polynomial
time
to decide click
so for this
decider of course decider don't need
extra information don't need certificate
and
if you want to uh
design a point uh
if you want to design
a polynomial time decider for click how
how will you do it
it's pretty straightforward that
from the starting configuration you get
g k
right
then for each branch
for each branch
you get a combination
of k notes
so
we can fork
so many
branches
and each one
is
a k note set
then we verify if the k note
is a click on the graph
okay
so if any one of the branch
checks out okay
for example this one okay then
the string is in click
otherwise
if no
except here
none of the cases are accept uh
none of the cases are accepted then
the input string is not in click
okay
so
again
you'll you will find that
the height
how many computational steps the height
is well within polynomial time
although the width
might be
much larger than polynomial okay
so you see
this one is uh
i'm not sure primal or exponential
doesn't matter but we have the
exponential case next one
okay
so
we either construct a problem polynomial
time verifier to prove a language is in
mp
by using a new definition
or
we construct a non-deterministic machine
which can decide that language
in polynomial time
and remember that that polynomial time
is only height of the computational tree
not width
we actually use the property of
non-deterministic computation to guess
all possible solutions and the number
the amount of the all possible solutions
might be
much
more than
you know a polynomial polynomial
bound of the
length of the input string okay that's
the key part
okay then the second uh
example here is
subset stuff
okay what is subsystem
for subset sum
the input is the
is a
multiset okay the important thing is
here is this set is money set not only
set but money set
and what is a multiset in multiset you
can have duplicate members that's it
okay
so
you have a multiset of integers
and
you specified a number as the
as the sum
so if in
the given multiset for example one one
two three four four five
okay that's you know it's an arbitrary
multiset
and then if some of them
if you can get some of them
to sum as
for example 10
okay
then we say that the whole
s and t
the whole input stream is in subset sum
that's it
so you you are given
you are given a multiset of integers and
a sum
a specified sum
and
as long as
from the given body set you can choose
some of them for this example you can
choose
let's say
one four five
okay or
let's say one one three five
so one one three five
you add them together which is exactly
the specified
sum
then
the whole thing
is in subsystem
if you cannot do it for example let's
say t is 100 and it's
impossible it's impossible to have a
even even the whole uh subset uh
multiset add together is not 100 so
the problem instance is not in subset
sum
okay so it's a pretty straightforward
problem you just get some from the given
multiset and to see
if it can
checks out
as the specified thumb
now we want to uh prove that subset sum
is
in
mp the language itself is in mp
okay so again
two possibilities one is
we follow the new definition and
we found a new definition and
uh construct a
polynomial time verifier for subset sum
okay so
for
verifier
we get the input string w and we ask we
can ask
for actual information
and for in this case we ask exactly
what integers
from the subset of the multiset
can be add up to can be added up
as the specified sum
okay
so uh okay so the first step of this one
is
firstly test if c is a collection of
numbers sums to the specified
sum
okay
so for our example one one two three
four four five and ten
if someone gives you one one three five
then you add them up
okay it's ten
so
no problem for the first first step then
you test if
the number three specified in c is
really from s it's really contained uh
or
s contains all numbers in c
so in this case one one three five no
problem okay
for other example let's say someone
gives you 5 5
then add up 10 no problem
but
1 5 is from s but the other 5
you know s has only one five so it
doesn't
it doesn't work so reject
okay so in this case reject
so
you uh
verify
again there is some responsibility of
the verify is that based on correct
certificate it return correct result
well accept that's it
it doesn't need to
take care of the wrong certificate as
long as the certificate is wrong then it
just rejected
okay we reject the input string
so if both pass accepted
otherwise rejected then we have the
polynomial time we have the profile
and since the provider doesn't really
need to you know do a lot of things you
just need to add the integers and check
if they are in the
given multiset so
the whole process
can surely be
finished within the polynomial bound of
the input string
of the length of the industry
right
so
for another
proof again we use a non-deterministic
machine
to construct a divider and for the
non-deterministic machine and firstly
you know you just construct
sorry
you just need to construct all possible
solutions and what is the old possible
solutions in this case
it's probably true to the
community of the muddy set s
right i shouldn't
do that i should say here the same thing
but yeah
so you see
the
width here is obviously exponential
to the length of the
input stream
but you know we don't care about the
width we only care about
the height
so how many steps
you need to construct all possibility
all possible solutions
you just need to
you just need about cardinality of s
right because for all possible subset
for each integer in s
you either
include that integer
or
not include that integer so there are
two
possibilities for each in the integer in
s
so totally you have so many
possibilities but
the steps only about the cardinality of
s
okay
then you just need to you know add up
add up the selected integer to check if
it is t or not
any for any branches
if
the selected integers
the sum of the selected integers
is the specified
t then
accepted right then accept
then as long as one branch
returns accept then the whole machine
accepts the string
well as t
otherwise
if all
branches reject
then
the whole machine rejects its input
is so
uh
it is that straightforward so we just
need to do that and
we can
uh we can construct a non-deterministic
polynomial time verifier
to verify subset sum
okay
so no matter uh we prove it with a new
sorry uh yeah new
definition of cos np or old definition
of class mp
it's question forward
okay
so that's another uh that's another
example of uh problems in class np
okay
and let's
further define
uh some
class actually
so we define co mp
see again
call something right co x
we introduce such notation in like
co
recognize the uh tool recognizable right
what is culturally truly recognizable
if a language
is culture recognizable that means
the complement of that language is too
recognizable
so the same thing here
if a language
is incall mp that means the complement
of that language is in mp
okay
so
click
the complement
of click
is
in
column p
because
the complement of the complement of
click
is click
in mp
so the complement of click is in
p
okay
well
and
complement of subset sum is in
column p
because its complement
is in mp
so
this language is in column p
okay so
we introduce the class here
and then
currently as human beings
well we don't know
if co mp is different from mp
okay we we don't know the
the actual relationship between these
two classes
okay for some other classes we might
we might know actually for example
decidable
if a language is decidable
we know that the complement of languages
must be decidable right
so decidable and the code decidable is
the exactly the same clause
okay
and we know
to be recognizable
and cold to recognizable
is not equivalent
right we know that
because you know if
uh
if we remember that a language and its
accomplishment can only there are only
three possibilities
right then those hierarchy
let us know that coal too recognizable
and the two recognizable is not the same
thing
okay
and currently we don't know the
relationship between comp and mp so
that's the status quo okay
and
here comes the interesting uh
uh
discussion
as i described that
p class p
is the class of languages
for which
membership can be decided
quickly
right
give you a string you have a decider
you can decide the given string is in a
language or not within the polynomial
time
so quickly here means within polynomial
okay
and then
using an identical
computational model
mp is the class of languages
for which membership can be
verified
quickly
okay verify
act on
correct extra information you can verify
membership of that language
okay with the
identical computational models okay
that's easier
and by definition
okay by definition
you can
consider
designer for
a language
it's actually the verifier
for that language
right because you just ignore because
you can
independently
determine the membership so you can
ignore any extra information that means
no matter what information extra
information is provided you can always
give the correct answer so decider
by definition is a verifier
so according to this
according to this
class p and the class mp basically there
are two possibilities of their
relationship
the first possibility is that
since as i said
decider is actually verified
so p
must be
a subset of mp
okay
or
p
and mp
are the same class
okay
by drawing the left part we mean that
they are something here
like we draw for a regular expression as
a regular language and context-free
language or we draw it for decidable
undecidable but recognizable and
unrecognizable right
so
according to the definition of p and mp
we know
the relationship of classes p and mp
must be
this one of this one but we don't know
which one yet
okay you can find uh many proof to prove
this one or proof this one on the
internet actually as long as you google
there are some uh people collecting all
the proofs proof p equals to np or
uh
p is not equal to
mp
okay we have a lot of proof uh right now
but none of them are accept uh widely
accepted by the
academia okay so that's our
current state
for now
to be sure
what we can be sure of is that p
is a subset of exponential time
well we have the theorem to prove it
right
uh the proof is that we can you know use
a deterministic
turing machine to enumerate
the computational tree of the of a
non-deterministic tree machine so that
way that will result in exponential time
right that's the upper bound well for
some uh better cases it might not be a
uh
might not need to use exponential time
but
that's the worst case
and exponential time would be the union
of all possible time
of 2 to the n to the k power
and remember that 2 here is not really 2
you just need a number there okay to
express that
n is in the
exponential part
okay
so that's what we know
right now and we don't know whether mp
is content in a smaller deterministic
time compressive class
we are sure of
mp is in deterministic exponential time
but
any smaller time complexity class
deterministic time complexity class we
don't know okay that's
currently uh the current situation and
that's the limit of human knowledge
right now
okay
so
this one
or
is really we want to know
not only for now for the past uh maybe
50 years
and probably future with we want to know
which one is the
uh
we want to know which one is the real
relationship okay
so how do we uh
approach this problem
can uh how do we find a way to
try to study
left or right something like that
so
it is difficult because you know p is a
class which is a set
and mp is also a class which is a set
and
if you want to prove
for example if you want to prove p equal
to mp
because p is a class and np is a class
which are stats right so you must prove
some language in p
is in
mp
right
sorry here
then if you prove this direction that
means
p is in mp
p is p is a subset of mp okay i should
write it better
like this
and also you need to
prove that
if a language is an in np
the language is in p then
in this case you prove this
and if you have nt then p is equal p
equals to mp
okay and as i said by definition you
don't need to
do this
we already know it so the key part is
this one
okay
then you see if we want to prove p
equals to mp for what we we've already
known
we need to prove that all languages in
mp
are in p
see discuss about all languages that's
you know kind of
difficult
and
for the left part
the left part
if we want to prove p
and the mp
if you want to prove p and mp are
different
then we need to find an example
here
okay
the let if there is any language anyone
any language
if there is a language l which is not in
p
sorry
which is not in p but
it is in mp
if we have this language then we prove
this one
right
so you see for the midterm second
metering
examination
why did i ask you firstly
choose
true
or false
then based on
what you ch what you chose
you try to prove you are correct
so
it's quite the same thing here
we want to prove
p equals to np or p is not
equal to mp
then if you want to prove p equal to mp
you need to prove that all language is
np they are in p okay
or you want to prove p not equal to mp
then you need to find a language here
as soon as you find some language which
is not in p by the np then you
successfully prove that
p
is not equal to mp
okay
then
what if
we can find some
uh
well i would like to say spatial but
not that special
not that spatial but uh we're still
special okay what if we can find some
particular spatial language
so special that
as long as we find that
it is not
in p
then we prove
the right situation
or
if we find the language
in p
then we prove the second situation
again
what if we can find we can define some
language
of
spatial property
and according to that spatial property
the language can help us
to distinguish
left or right the situation on the left
or situation on the right
if we can
prove the language the arrow here
in p then p equals to mp if we can prove
that l here not in p then
p is not equal to mp
what if we have some language like this
okay
so that would be
mp complete
problem
okay
we will introduce np complete problem
the first one will be
satisfiability problem
i mean first one is not the first one i
want to introduce it is the first one in
human history to be
proved to be empty complete
then
it is the famous uh
theorem okay
if the satisfiability problem is in p
sorry uh the
satisfiability problem is in p if and
only if
p
equals to np
okay that we will prove this uh
slightly later
because we need some other mathematical
construction first okay and let's
introduce that first because uh we
always need to do that
so what is sat here
sat is that you have a
boolean formula
is this boolean formula satisfiable
if it is
then it's inset otherwise it's not in
set
okay so what is putting formula i think
most of them
most of you should already know it but
let's just describe it
so a boolean formula
is an expression
involving putting variables and
operators
so for example a putting formula like
this one so you have
x bar
and y
then
x and
z bar
and or
okay
then we said a boolean formula is
satisfiable
if
some assignments of 0 and 1
makes the whole formula
evaluated to 1
okay
here for 0 is 4 4
1 is true
for this particular example
if we assign
x zero so that would be one right x bar
is a complement of zero one's complement
okay
and
y to be one
so one and one is one
then it doesn't matter this one right
because it's over so
the whole formula evaluates to be one
then it's satisfied
then because the assignments
exist
we say that
this formula is satisfiable
right okay so that's the definition and
of course there are fooling formula
not satisfiable not satisfiable for
example if you have x
and x bar
okay it's not satisfiable right because
if you assign 0 to x then that'll be 0
and 1 so
n is 1. if you assign 0 to x then 1 at 1
to x then 1 and
also 0 so
no assignment satisfied this boolean
formula
so
when you have a boolean formula
it may be satisfiable or not
so
the language of sat
is all the satisfiable that is the set
of all the satisfiable boolean formula
okay
so you see
can you firstly can you uh have a turing
machine decide
a given
formula satisfiable or not of course you
can have you can have it it's decidable
because you just need to try
all possible
assignments if any one of them
satisfy the formula and the formula is
viable so it's decidable the problem is
that how much time you need
to do the decision okay
then
cook 11
proof that
if
you need only polynomial time
if and only if p equals to mp okay so
that's the importance of
uh satisfiability and also the concept
of and mp complete uh np complete and
the mp completeness
okay
so
let's go through our uh
mathematic mathematical construction
first
for
uh
follow-up discussion okay
so
we want to
since we want to uh
well uh properly define np-complete
we need the following
measurement construction but these
constructions are very similar to uh
section 5.3 mapping reducibility
it's well basically the same but we
we add the constraint on time that's it
okay so let's go through a definition
here
so
here we want to introduce uh
polynomial time reducibility okay
so it is still making reusability but
with the
constraint on time
okay let's say a function f from string
to string
is a polynomial time
computable
function if
some polynomial time to machine
m exists
holds
with just
f of w on its tape
when
started on any input w
okay
remember in section 5.3 we define its
computable function it doesn't matter
how much time you need for the exclusion
and here we
emphasize on polynomial time computable
computable function and such computation
has to be done by polynomial time to a
machine okay
so now we quantify a running time within
the polynomial bound of the input string
a polynomial of the length of the input
string okay
then we say that
language a
is polynomial time maintain reducable so
c still may be reducible but now we add
polynomial time as our
constraint on time okay or simply
polynomial time reducible things we are
all talking about may be reducible we
you know slightly simplify the
expression we are using
we say that language a is polynomial
time may be reducible to language b
return
here we use p here means polynomial time
okay
if a polynomial time computable function
exists
give
gives
such
relation
for every
input string
see that relation is identical to what
we have in section 5.3
okay that means
any string in a
map to a string in b and a string out of
a
map to string out of b
and remember that
there is no untwo or 1 to 1
okay there's no on 2 and 1 to 1
it is quite possible that
all strings in a map to exactly one
strings in b and all string out of a
exactly mapped to all string f
one string out of b that's
acceptable
by our definition here
okay
again so the computable function we have
here
only need to provide
the relationship between
w
and f of w is that w in a if and only if
f of w f of w in b
there's no other other criteria okay
then
if such a
polynomial time computable function
exists
for language a to language b we say that
language a is polynomial time maybe
reducible to language b and we call this
function f
the polynomial time reduction
of
a to b
okay
so you can map back to
section 5.3
basically the same definition
only that we add
time constraint okay
then
then we have
we can uh by using this definition
we can have
a theorem
uh here there are
seven 7.31
so
we can prove that
if a
is polynomial
time reducible to b and you already know
that b is in
p
then we can conclude a in p
okay
we can conclude that a is in p
how to prove this theorem
basically
we know that
b
in class p that means there is a
decider for b
deterministic machine as a decider for b
running in polynomial time right
then
by using this
relation we can construct a decider for
a
running in polynomial time
so the theorem is proved okay
so
we can prove that
in this way
so firstly
we know that
b is in p
so
there is a transmission m
deciding b
in polynomial time okay
so that's our
known fact here
and we know that a
is maybe reducible a polynomial time may
be reducible to b
by definition
there is a
polynomial time reduction from a to b
right polynomial time reduction
then we construct
the decider running in polynomial time
for a
then we can prove a theorem okay so how
to construct that
we construct the machine n here
and for w
for any input string w
we call f
we compute f of w
remember that the definition of f
what is that it is a turing machine
holds on all inputs
with its tape as f of w right so we
don't need to take care of uh we don't
need to care about like an infinite loop
or something here
in chapter seven
there is no undecidable stuff okay
so we just need to compute f of w
after the first step and how long does
the uh anyway let's do the correctness
first okay
after con compute f of w
we call
m which is the decider for b right
on the input of f of w
and
what
can f provide us f providers such
relation
right
so
we run m on f of w
and n is the desire for b
so
n
must hold
with
an answer which is accept or reject
if m says
accept that means f of w is in b
then we know w is in a then we report
also accept
otherwise if m says
no f of w is not in b
then according to the relationship here
we know that
w is not in a so we also report the same
result again
okay that's why
the second step says so
so
surely
n here
is a decider for a right no problem
decider for a
okay how much time does it need to
finish the computation
firstly
f
is a polynomial time reduction so
you need a polynomial time of length of
w to finish the computation of the first
step
that's no problem right
then
is a polynomial times decider for b
and here is the polynomial
decided for b but
remember that the polynomial time
for m
is the length of f of w
right don't don't forget that
everyone in polynomial time but how long
does it take
actually
it is a polynomial of
f of w
so the problem here is that
the running time
here
is the running time here also within the
polynomial bound of the length of w
yes it is
why
because
since f of w
takes
polynomial time to finish the
computation
the length of f of w
must be within the polynomial bound of
the length of w
remember the
one step
one
[Music]
tape space one transition step a
connection between time and space of the
turing machine
if you remember that then you know
since
when we calculate f
at most we take polynomial
steps
or we take the number of steps
polynomial to the length of
w
so
the length of f of w at the most
will be within the polynomial bound of
the length of w
then
n runs on the polynomial time of the
length of f of w so polynomials
polynomial
is still polynomial
right
so there's no problem and here is a
polynomial time
decider for a
so by definition
a is in p
okay
so
now we prove that
if you already know some language in p
and another language can be polynomial
time reducible to that language
then
the language that
the other language is in p2
okay
you