after we defined the running time or
time complexity
of deterministic machine as a function
to capture
the
worst case
for that turing machine to process input
strings of every
uh of every possible lenses
then we
employ the definition of big o notation
to describe the
asymptotic behavior of that two machines
then
we can try to analyze some
two machines to see how the
how the running time and the time
complexity
works okay
so let's say uh
let's use the language here as an
example
so
since we now use n
as you know the
length of the input string to a turing
machine so we change you know the local
variable to k here
so uh this language this language
contains uh what strings like epson
0 1
0 0 1 1
0 0 0 1 1 1 etc right so that uh this is
the first
non-regular language in our
course right so uh
if you remember that we write it as
this language but as i said now we use n
mostly
for the
input string length so we use k here
doesn't really matter okay
then
uh
this language is apparently decidable
because it is a context-free language
right
and
we have proved that there is a theorem
proving that
every context-free language is decidable
so no doubt
we know that the decider for this
language exists and
actually we can easily write a decider
for that right so here is the example of
one decider for that language okay
so we described the turing machine for
the language
in a high level style well not really
high level but
we describe the behavior of the two
machine to some extent that
everyone can agree upon the existence of
the possibility of the two machines to
decide the language okay
and
let's say
for the uh
an input string w
the machine
firstly
scan across the tape
and
reject if
a zero is found to the right of
one so you can imagine that
the types here right and you have the
input here
and you have infinite right-hand side
and the machine
when
putting the mach the head is
as the first location
then scan across the tape
and see if there is a zero
so you see zero zero
zero and starts with c1
one and if you found if the machine
found
zero
to the right
of a one
then
it cannot be zero sorry let's say zero k
one k
k
[Music]
bigger than equal to zero right so
reject right
so after the scan
and the going back
after
the input stream passed the first
uh checking step
you'll get a bunch of zero and then a
bunch of one okay
any string
that is not in the format of
zeros ones will be rejected by the first
step okay so i think that's pretty
uh easy to understand and
it is also why
we need to introduce to machine
in the detail in the uh fundamental
level
for you to you know go through the
tracing
uh processing
and
write down the configuration on your own
so that you can get a get an idea
regarding how turing machine exactly
operates
and why do we want to know that because
after you know how tune machine operates
basically you can determine
if some step
like this one
whether or some step
can be implemented by turing machine or
not
okay
okay so for this case
i guess everyone uh
can agree that uh this step can be
implemented by turing machine actually
we have seen similar things in our
examples right
and
let's say
what kind of statement cannot be
implemented by two machine
it's pretty easy okay uh
for example uh
today is uh
i don't know thursday or tuesday right
so
uh we have lottery and the winning
numbers will be drawn
in the evening
and how about write down some step like
second step
output
the winning numbers that will be drawn
tonight for
lottery
i guess
i believe
nobody will
believe
this state
this statement can be implemented
right
so
understanding or
familiar with the operations of two
machines
in the detailed level
help you to understand what kind of
statement is you know
or
would highly probably can be
implemented by a two machine well if
some statements that really can be
implemented but you don't believe it
that's one writing the statement
writing the statement
uh the person writing the statement have
to uh has to provide more evidence to
you okay so if uh some statement is in
doubt the designer of the two machine
have
give you
you know seven machine uh two machines
seven tuple and everything
layout and proof that that statement can
be implemented
but most of the time we don't go that
kind of detail that's too much
just like when you write a c program
john program
you will not
ask
the programmer to compile that program
into
let's say arm assembly
or intel cpu assembly or a java virtual
machine by code for you to exam you know
that's that that step is doable
so
pretty much the same idea here that the
high level statement here is uh
we we would like to
uh
draw an analogy between high level
statement here and
as the
programming language and the details of
the two machine as the assembly or
machine code
and
as long as we believe this statement can
be implemented we believe that's okay
so that's pretty much the idea so first
step of the machine is that we uh we
asked them or
the machine is designed to scale cursor
tab
reject if you found a zero after a one
okay then after
step one every string and you can see
that
for many string
it make a
process for many strings processed by
this machine it is possible that the
machine don't need to
[Music]
do many steps to reject that string
right for example if you find a if you
have a string one zero blah blah blah
very long
the machine only need to check one
zero and reject
two steps right
so
for this machine
it's not necessary to go through many
steps it depends on the input
okay
and you know that now we are doing worst
case analysis
but the worst case here
means that finally the
input string got accepted
so for this particular machine
the worst case is
the input string to be accepted
right so it's pretty interesting to
think of this way so let's say after
first step
you know that you have a bunch of zeros
and a bunch of ones as your input right
then
the machine repeat
the machine repeat uh i guess it will be
one
two three or two three four depends on
how you interpret the whole thing
because it's a
text statement
so we repeat the loop here and
scan across the tape
and across
a zero and a one so
a 0 and a 1
then go back
go back
then 0 and 1
and go back 0 and 1 and you repeat the
whole thing here
okay
and
if you found there's no zero
still ones or vice versa
still zeros here but no ones then reject
it right that means one is more than
zero or zero is more than one
so those string got rejected
otherwise
neither one
nor
zero
remain annotate that means one and zero
disappear at the same
time okay at the same step then we
accept it
see
so we can match we can uh have a desire
for the language a here
i think the correctness of this
algorithm
has been you know uh we don't need
we don't really need to prove that
because
it's kind of uh follow our definition
for
you know one to one maybe stuff right
because you have a bunch
zero and bunch one so cross one girls
one cross one cross one
and
uh
they are both used up at the same time
they have the same numbers although you
don't know
how many
right we don't know how many ones and
zeros but we know
the amount of ones and zeros are the
same
okay so
this machine can be uh not this machine
is a decider for the language a
now we want to analyze
we want to analyze
the running time
of the machine
see uh
recall that our running time is the
worst case so we want to analyze
this case
right the accept case
so
let's say
how many steps
for the machine
to finish
step uh stage one here or step one uh
stage one here
see on the input tab the machine need to
go
once
to the end of the input string
and go back reposition
right
so
unless
the turing machine is designed in a very
very very bad way
unless in that case
the
total steps
the total step
for the machine to do step one
is will be linear to the length
of the input string
right
because the input string one symbol
occupies one type symbol uh one tab uh
space right
so
it doesn't matter how many steps
you need to do
check
and go
right
and check and go right and check and
then finally
go back go back go back go back
here no matter how
many steps you need to do one
operation now should be a constant
right like three steps for one operation
or five step for one position doesn't
matter
the three or five is not related to n
here unless
you do that on purpose
otherwise the machine should
behave
in a way that
it needs about
linear uh it needs a number of steps
number of steps linear to end here
and we don't know how many
of the step or how many steps we need
but we know it should be linear right
and
that's why we have
big o notation here we know that
big o of n which means linear to
the length of the input string
linear steps
for stage one
is probably it right we probably need
linear steps but we don't know the
constant but we know it should be linear
unless you design a very bad machine
okay so that's why see
we don't even know
when
for stage one
how many steps we can have because we
don't have the exact machine here
that's why we
introduce
big old notation to help us to capture
much a detailed machine
the uh
to capture the machine which we don't
have the exact uh instrumentation
okay so that's the powerful
mathematical construction we are using
okay
so we have linear
steps
we have steps linear to the input of a
then input length
for scan and reposition
okay you check if one is
zero is behind one something like that
and
uh
at the end of the input string go back
to the first one
okay so
now take so many steps
then
how many steps for the loop
it's quite easy actually because you see
we have
after the first step we know that the
input stream would be
a bunch of 0 and at the function of 1.
so
how many
uh firstly how many steps you need to
cross a zero then go to
the part of one closer one
well you can say that it depends the
number of zeros and the number of ones
right
but don't forget that we are doing worst
case analysis we are doing the string
finally will get
accepted and that will be
half of n
and half of n
if you have only one zero and a lot of
one
this step will
down once
and then the string got rejected so you
will use fewer steps
right or
you have one another zero and you have
only a few ones
you will do
cross 0 cross 1
and then
reject it
you also get
fewer steps
so the worst case the
most
uh the most number of steps
will be
half
n and half m
zero and one
so
you will go
cross 1 a 0 and a 1
and go back right
so the same argument here
close 1 0 and 1 1
you need to close
you you do uh you need a step linear to
have n
right linear to that so we have here
do one crossing zero and one
and how many of them you want you uh you
you need to finish the job
to
[Music]
happen right
so we don't know exactly the steps here
but we know the iteration is exact
that's why
we write this way okay
so
have n
big o have n
however
half
is a constant
don't forget that half is a constant
so we write this one
okay
this one is an insane number and this
one is a big old notation
and we know that
and then we know that
what means by these
notation
you can think big o of n
is a description of some exact function
right
you know that
x there exists c a constant and n 0
another constant
after n0
this
function
is equal to or smaller than c
g of n which is n here
right
now you multiply
half and both sides
okay
then what you got
you got
and square here and have c here
and half c
is still constant let's say c prime
and we don't even need to change n0
that's why this term can be returned as
big o of n squared
because by definition
c
exists
and 0 exists so we can use
n square to be a big old description to
describe this exact function although we
don't know what that is
that is why
we can
write
this one
to depict
the whole thing here okay
so if you are in doubt you just need to
go back to definition and
think of it that would be
straightforward okay so you need so many
uh
steps for stage is it two and three
then
every time you do a final checking you
check if any
zero and the one left you scan across
the whole tab once so that's pretty much
the same thing as the stage one so
linear to
the length of input
okay
then what is the
uh
running time for the whole machine
basically we need to add them up
okay we need to add it up
so uh
you know that uh we can we can just uh
determine the highest order and we write
like this one but
without that we can have like this but
you
always go back to the definition and to
check it
okay
so
let's go uh do that once
so for this one that means there is an
f1 of n right
and
this one
there exists c1 and n1
when n is larger or equal to n1
f of 1 over n always smaller
than or equal to c 1
times
g of n which is m here
right
and then
same thing goes for uh goes to this one
so we say c2 and 2 exist
and the exact function f of 2 of n is
smaller than or equal to c 2 times n
square
right
and then there is another exact function
here
we have c three and three
f three of n
always smaller than here right
so the
function the exact function
for the whole machine
is a sum of f1 f2
f3 that is the f of n we want to have we
want to we want
to have as the running time or time
complexity of that to machine
and we already know that there are you
know uh
this part as we already know
so
go through some pretty
easy steps
you can find that
there must
exist some constant
and n0
probably the max n0 is probably the max
of um one
and two and three
okay probably i don't know but
we can uh do some derivation
and
that will be
end here
sorry not three sorry
it is possible to do the derivation here
and
if you are in doubt
you can make like a c
equal to some
plus something maybe one or two doesn't
really matter as long as c
larger than c two
these tan this term
and then you don't do it you change n
zero
as long as c
larger greater than c two
this term
will always
larger than the sum of the three
right
and like like we do that for
for this
see this one
imagine that
you have a five here then you choose c
larger than five then you can go back to
calculate
how many
for n0
then you will always the whole thing
bigger than the sum of this one
so the same thing goes to what we just
described then you can find c and n0
and then write
this notation to describe
the target function
of
something described by this one
okay that is why we can write
formula we can write equation this way
but you always need to go back to the
definition to derive the
expression you wanted to use
okay
okay now
since we
have uh the
time complexity described by
big o of
n squared
let's define
time complexity cost
okay let's t a function
map from natural number to positive
real numbers
we define
time
of
t
of n
okay that's pretty complicated but prime
of t of n
to be the collection
to be the collection of
all languages
that are decidable by and big o of t of
n time turing machine
okay
so
if we write time
of
n squared
so n squared here is t of n right
in this case plm t of n is n square
every language
can be determined by
big o of n square
tier machine we say that that language
is in
this class
okay
so
you can think of this definition here
simultaneously
define
many many many many
sets of languages
okay
you have a time t of n you have one
collections one set of languages you
have another t of n you you have another
of languages
so this definition here is a very
uh well it contains many many many many
collections of languages
and the labels
labeled by t of n
so given n square you define
a time complexity class given n another
one and cubic another one or n log
another one so you have according to
this definition we have defined many
many many many time complexity classes
okay
so what languages is in some particular
time
time complexity classes
as long as
that's language
decidable is decidable by an big o of t
of n time time machine that language is
in the particular time
time time complexity class
okay
so
since we already know that m1
decides
the language a which is 0k 1k right in
time we go of n square which we have the
result here
by this definition
we know that the language is in
time of n square
okay
so
according to what we have for pico
notation we know that
m1 is a big o of n square
time turing machine right
and for big o m ones
m ones
time complexity can also be written as
big o of n squared and cubic right
if you understand what we have
introduced the goal notation last
in last lecture
you know you can write the time
complexity for
m1s
because you can write it as n square you
can write it as n cubic and the even
higher orders
right so we know that a
is in time
square
also in time
cubic also in time
and to the first power and etc right
so
you can also imagine that let's say uh
this is
time
of n square
it contains all languages that are
decidable by
and big o of
n square machine
and then you have
cubic
time of cubic and the time
of force and the time
of
five right or you have something like
this one now be
n square log n
something like that so if you have
language here of course that language is
in
bigger superset
right so
don't be confused by the relationship
here
the definition if you
really understand the definition you
will not be confused okay
what we are
what we care about is how small that
language belong to not how large because
when you get higher order the of course
the uh
set will be larger right
then
that's uh
uh let's
continue the discussion here we know
that the language which is
you know in a concept for our course
corresponds to the problem right so we
know that okay there is a square time
algorithm
handle that
problem
so
is that problem uh
okay
so it's time uh square
the
uh in this uh here we actually uh
trying to use the
how much time you need to handle some
kind of problem to
evaluate to assess
to assess
the difficulty of a problem
okay the concept is that
if you need
for example if i i give you
a a homework assignment uh you can you
you need one hour to finish the
assignment
compared to you need five hours to five
hours to finish the
assignment you will think
the assignment
need uh
requires you to spend five hours is more
difficult or more complicated right
the same concept uh
applied here so
we know now we know that a the language
a language a here
is in
time of n square so that's
some kind of difficulty measurement you
can single it like that
then how about we use another algorithm
how about we use another algorithm so
we propose another algorithm as m2 here
okay
so what did uh what does this algorithm
do
this algorithm first step also format
checking okay
so
it checks
any
zero
to the right over one
if there's any then reject it so the
same steps
okay
then after that after that
as long as there are zeros and ones
the machine
check
scan across the tab again and checking
the total number of left
zeros and ones but we don't count the
number
not not one two three four five six
seven eight nine ten stuff like that no
we don't count the number we just count
if it's
even or odd
okay because if you want to count the
number you need to know the number you
need to store the number somewhere and
you cannot handle infinite number so it
cannot be implemented by two machines so
we don't do that but for odd and even
there are only two situations we can
handle that and we actually
have seen the example
in chapter
three right
so
imagine that
after step one you have a lot of zero
and ones like this
then
you count
the total length
of course the first
uh
the first round the first iteration that
would be n right
so you
count the
total number of zero and one
if it's odd
then reject
if it is odd
there
there will there will be no chance to
have zero k one k
right because
you need to have the same number of zero
and ones that'll be either
okay
then
if
it's even it's odd and reject right and
if it is even
then you cross
half of zero and half of one
okay so let's have an example here
so let's say we have zero zero zero zero
zero
one one one
okay over one more
that's let's do it this way
so we have one six zero four ones
okay so first that first stage use or we
scan across the tape and
format checking okay
right past format checking
then
we count
one two oh sorry
art even uh
okay
art even art even art even art even art
even okay so
go
to the fourth stage
then we cross
half of zero
and then half of one
okay and go back
to check so
this time
odd
even art
even
odd so reject
okay
because there is no way
to match
the number of zeros and ones
if zeros and ones are of the same
numbers
it will always be even
for the symbol left
on
the tape
right
so let's add one more
so
uh
so the first step okay right now
this one
then we have art even art even art
even
okay so let's continue
then
go back to
two
cross this one
cross this one every other zero okay
every other one
then again odd
even
then again we cross
this one and this one
there's no zero and the one on the tab
except
okay so that's how
m2
operates
how m2 operates
so you can check you can check
the uh
or verify the correctness of m2 actually
i have uh described that
it is correct because
firstly you know a bunch of zero before
a bunch of ones
then if
the number of zero and ones are exactly
the same
no matter how you
close out zero and one
i mean every time you cross half of zero
and have half of one
you always get the same numbers of zero
and one and finally there will be curls
together
then you will have no ones and zeros
left otherwise all strings are rejected
okay
now if we try to
uh analyze if we try to analyze
the
running time of m2 we'll know that
for every stage for every stage
described here
you got
linear steps
because you can consider
it's either scan
scan and operate on the whole
input
string
or half of it
well for m2 it's always the whole input
string
don't forget that when you close out
some symbol that symbol is still on the
tape
okay the content of the tape
since it would since we don't compress
the content of
uh
the contents of
input string on the tape the
length will not will not be reduced to a
smaller length right so
your operation will always go through
the whole
the length of the whole original input
string
so that'll be big o of n
so big o of n steps for every stage
then the problem the problem is how many
loop how many iterations you need
to go through the
iteration here
so that would be
it's not very
difficult
it's 1 plus
log
base 2 of n
right because
if you have
so many
zeros and ones
every time you close half of them
remember that since we are analyzed the
worst case the worst case is that
the string finally got accepted
right that's the worst case
for
let's say if you have fewer ones uh
fewer zeros a lot of ones
you only you you won't have many
iterations you just go through one or
twice then the string got rejected
so the worst case is that the string in
this case
the string
finally got accepted in that case
every time you cross half of zeros and
half of ones that will be half of the
whole input string
and how many times
what uh
will the iteration
goal that will be
log
base 2 and the length of the string
right
so plus 1
that will be the number of iterations
that's why we have
number of durations
and every stage is
big of n so
for the stages of 2 3 and 4 that would
be this one
okay and remember that this is the exact
number not in big o so the base the base
here still matters okay
then we just need to
add up the two
that will be
step stage one and two
three four things like this
and
you can go through the calculation again
and you will get you will find that
these expression
can be used via
the goal
to describe
what
these two
expressions described although we don't
know what exactly that is but we know we
can use
this notation to describe what this
notation described
okay well
then we know that
m2 decides a
the same language 0k1k
in time big of n log n
by definition of time complexity class
we know that a
is in
time and log n now
see
that's what i said
for m for the existence of m1 we know
that
a is in time n squared
okay a is in time n squared
and of course by definition we know that
since a is in time of n square
a is in time of
n cubic and
four
and etc right
so we don't care how
big the superstar is we are we usually
we care
how small the time complexity class can
be
so
by having m2 here
you know
you write a better program in some sense
you write a better program
by the existence of n2 m2 here we know
that
a actually belongs to a smaller time
complexity class that would be
n log n
okay
so
i think that's pretty clear so we know
that
now we know that n is a is in the
language of a the language a is in and
organ time comes time time of n log n
okay
so
see
if you write a better program
you either
sorry not only that you can solve the
uh
solve the problem faster
well in the theoretical sense not
practical sense theoretical sense solve
the proc
problem
faster
but also that you prove
the problem is actually easier than we
thought
see that's the uh interesting part
then
how about we use a you know slightly
different
machine
in chapter
3 right we proved that the variance the
variant of turing machine are basically
equivalent
but don't be confused here
those equivalence
is in terms of computability
okay computability
uh type a
query machine of type a can do
what type b can do and the vice versa
that's we say they are equivalent and we
didn't care about how many steps how
many times it needs we only care about
can or cannot
okay in chapter three four five computer
beauty but here let's see what will
happen
so if we use two type two machine
then we design m3 for the language
how do we do that
here
so m3 is actually easier than m2
the
so
we have now uh the machine have has
now has two type right so first type is
you know a bunch of zero and bunch of
one which is the input
input type okay
and the second tab initially empty
okay
then
first step is the same
we just
scan across the tab to check the format
if a bunch of zero and bunch of one then
it's okay otherwise reject it okay
then
go again
scan across zero part
until the first one let's say here
so we have
zero here and one here and don't forget
that we have two tape right so two head
can work
simultaneously so when we scan across
zero
we copy the zero to the second tip
okay
so it doesn't wan at that moment the
head will be the at the first one
and then ahead
you can well depends on how you write
the program doesn't really matter let's
say here
okay
then
for type for the first tape
we continue in the scanning
of one until the end of the input
so
we continue
scanning but at the same time
the
head on the second tape
go back
you see
we can go back here to zero right then
we close
one zero
then
one zero so every step
your first
tap head go right and the
second time head go left
so it's like
the whole thing would be
zero zero zero one 1 1 and firstly we
copy 0 0 0 on the second tab then cross
1 cross 0 cross 1 cross 0 cross 1 cross
0.
if
o zero
let's say
if o zero has been closed and you still
have one or vice versa then the string
is rejected otherwise
accept it
so it's pretty straightforward it's
pretty easy
actually easier than the
easier easier than m2
right
so
how many steps need the machine
m3 needs to
process a string
the same thing that every
stage
is linear to
the length of the input string
so
we have
here
and of course when you sum up sound when
you sum up all these terms you get a
linear time machine
okay
so we call the
we call m2 linear time
since m3 decides a in time because n
which is linear time
we know now we know that a
is in time of n
okay
so previously we know a is in time log n
that's m2 right
now by using a different type of turing
machine we can further
say that a is even in
time of n
well
that's okay but it create actually
creates a problem
okay
if someone use a different machine
and obtain a different
okay let's go back
for m2 and m1 you can say that we are
using the same machine
but
the person who designed m2 is smarter
he or she used a better algorithm
to solve
a
so the second person successfully proved
that
a is
easier than what we thought when we have
only m1
they are on the same computational model
that's no problem
but
someone creates an other
computational model another machine
slightly different and prove that
a is actually
can be handled faster
then that creates a problem the two
results
cannot really be compared
right
so at this point we need to
discuss the difference between
two machines between the variants of two
machines to clarify or to unify what we
will have
for the derivation for the
results we will have
okay