so after proving
the equivalence of context through
grammar and pdas
we can have a corollary here
here that every regular language is
context free
okay
why
because remember that we define regular
language as the language can be
recognized by
dfa
then we
prove that
dfa and
nfa are equivalent so that means
every language
can be recognized by nfa
is a regular language
right
and then
what is pda
pda
is
basically an nfa
with a stack
okay
so
imagine that if you have a pda but you
never use the capability of the stack
then
basically the stack of the pda becomes
exactly an effect
since pdas becomes exactly nfa that
means
all
regular languages can be recognized by
pda
right
and apparently
we already have pda recognizing some
sorry
since all regular languages can be
recognized by pda that means
regular languages
maybe exactly context-free languages or
a part of context-free languages right
that's the two possibilities
for the conclusion here
but we already have examples
that
the language here
the language as the example to be
non-regular here
which we call b that previously right
is not regular language
but
we can use
pda to recognize it right
so we know that
regular languages is a proper subset of
context free language
and of course you can easily write
grammar for this language
you just need one variable right
then
this variable can become epsilon
or
zero
s
one
right
so
since the language
can be generated by context free grammar
that language
is
context free
language
and it is not regular language so we
know
the relationship
between regular language and context
free language
is like this
now you can see that computational
models of
dfa nfa regular expression gnfa
the four models are equivalent and they
can handle regular languages
and the later two models we introduced
contextual grammar and pda
they can handle context free languages
and
regular languages is a proper subset of
context-free languages so apparently
context free grammar and pda
well in a sense
is more powerful
it's more powerful than
dfa and lfa regular expression and gnfa
okay
then we go back to our
idea that
languages are problems
so
we want to have we want to discuss
computational model computation
uh the capability limit limitation of
computation
again if
if
if contest free languages
are
all possible languages
just if okay
if context-free languages are all
possible languages
then
everything's fine and the pda
or contextual grammar
are universally powerful then
we have no problem at all
so
is there any
language
outside of
context-free languages
that's the question okay
so consider the language
let's say also called b
we have
n a's
and b's and c's and n
is
greater than
or equal to zero
okay
so you you can easily imagine what kinds
of strings are in the language that
would be
epsilon which n is zero right
a b c a a b b
c c
a a a b b b c c c etcetera right that's
pretty straightforward
and let's think about how to uh
write a grammar for a language or how to
design a pdf or language okay
and pdf probably easier to think right
so you think of okay i can use
a stack
to push
a
and then mesh with b and we all know a
and b
are of the same
length or not
but the problem is that you own you
always can only
basically can use stack to check the
first two symbols you won't be able to
check if
c
is
of the same length of b or a
because everything in your stack has
been popped out for checking and there
is nothing remember
how many
symbols you have processed
okay so
the idea is that
okay maybe we cannot design a pda
and of course we will be unable to write
a grammar for this language
what is language
but
such an idea
well cannot be
cannot be considered as proof in
mathematics because
just because we are unable to do it it
doesn't mean that other
people cannot do it right so we need
something
more convincing and actually absolutely
convincing so that's
it it can be
considered as
as a proof
so
here like in regular languages we
are introducing
pumping lemma for
context-free
languages
okay context-free languages
since we are already familiar with
paminema for regular languages so we
just
described
this dilemma for context free language
if uh
if a
is a context free language
then there is a p
which is called the pumping length
where
for
any string in a
of length at least p
okay at least pumping lemma see until
this part is exactly the same as company
for regular languages okay
then s may be divided okay same thing
maybe
divided into
five pieces okay in regular language
it's three right so now it's five phases
let's say u v x y z
satisfying the three conditions
let's also look at the
last two
so
the second condition is that
the
second and the fourth pieces
cannot
cannot be both empty that's why we write
u
y the length of u y
larger than zero that means
u and the y cannot
be
empty string at the same time
they can be they can both be none empty
that's okay
and you can have u
sorry v
you can
not u y v y okay
you can have
v
empty
and y non-empty or you can have v non
empty and y empty that's okay they just
cannot be
empty at the same time so we write
the condition like this
okay
and the middle three
pieces
v x y which is in the middle
the length of v x y
is less than or equal to
the pumping length
okay
so it's very much like
x y
less than or equal to p in the regular
language okay then the second one
is like
uh sorry
the regular language okay so for pumping
number five
pieces
and the second fourth pieces cannot both
be empty string and
the middle three pieces together their
length is smaller than or equal to the
pumping length
okay given this the first
condition is the pumping condition that
the second and the fourth part
of the string
can be removed
which is
i
zero
or you can re you can repeat them
indefinite times
for example
u v
b x y y z
must be in the language 2
and the u v
v v x y y y z
must also be in that language
so
u
4 time v
sorry
x
for z
must be in the language too
so etc
so in depth for each i
equal to or greater than zero
the resultant string like this
which you pump the second and the fourth
pieces
the resultant string
will always be
in that language
okay so that that is the pumping number
for context-free languages
okay that is the pumping name of account
speed languages
okay so let's see why we have such a
property for you know context-free
language
it's pretty simple
uh if you can if you consider the same
thing for regular languages
if you remember that
uh why lego languages have such property
because when the regular language
can
let's say
since it
since some language is regular means
that
there is a dfa recognized in the
language
and as long as that dfa can process
some very long
longer than the number of it states
a string
then while processing that string
the dfa must step on
duplicated
states
right
may go back to some states it has
stepped on before
so by using this property we know that
the repeating part can be repeated
indefinite times
right
and the same thing goes to here
because when a string is long enough
remember that we in context free grammar
we derive the string from start variable
right and you derive something then
derive something and derive something
and derive something right
and according to the length of the final
string the terminal string
if the lens is very
or not not not very long it's long
enough long enough
then the steps here
will be
more than some steps
and
you must
use the same variable somewhere because
you have a finite set of variables
okay
so
when you use the when you use the
duplicate variable you when you use the
same variable again
at that time
as i explained why the language is
called context 3
that means you don't
you don't need to
you don't need to apply some specific
rules you can
apply
either
one which is
valid right
so when you use the same variable for
example a here a here
you don't need to apply the same rule
here you can apply
you can apply the rule at this time
with this a or vice versa
so it creates
the property
described by the pumping lemma
so let's say
let g be a context-free grammar for
language for country language a
let's look at
the rules
let b
be the maximum number of symbols
in the right hand side of the rule okay
what is that that means if you have rule
like this
and like this
and like
this
and you choose
the maximum length of the rule okay do
you check which is
not maximum
you set it as b
then
that's derived you set it as b and
that's the
right
and
impossible
upper bounds
a ridiculous upper bound okay
it is impossible to reach but let's say
it is upper bound what is uh what what
upper bound let's say from the start
variable
there are at most
b leaves for one step
right at most
it it is impossible but
that's it it's an upper bound
and at the most
b
square
leaves four second steps
and of course at most b to the
h
power leaves for edge
steps
right
then
consider that
if the grammar can generate a string at
least
this long
then
the pass three
for this string
must be at least
h plus one high
right you need so many so many steps you
cannot generate that long string with
fewer steps
then that's the key
let's say
this is the cardinality of
okay this is the number of variables the
cardinality of the set b right the
number of variables
we set p as
this this uh
this number
then you will see that
to derive
string
of this length
the right string of distance you need to
have
the derivation
so many steps
then you must
used
some duplicate
variable along the derivation or the
parse tree
has
some duplicate the sum
variables so
let's say
from
start variable
you finally derived
the string like this
okay the string like the string like
this
and along the path
you use
duplicate
you use duplicate
variables
okay
then when you derived
within the derivation here
some some
in at some step you have
u
r
z
and also
you have
b
r
y
and also you have
z
oh sorry x x right
and you will see that
why don't you use
r generate x
in this part
yes you can because it's context-free so
you can have
this part right within that grammar
you can always do that because
you can
you can uh derive
at r you can use r to derive x directly
then you will have t
u r z and r becomes x so t
derives
u x d which is
u v zero x y zero z
right
and also
you can
have
uh v
r
y
r becomes v r y right and you can also
do that again when you encounter r here
so that will become
this one
t
derives
u
v
sorry
u r z
and then r derives v r y so u
v
r y z
right
and you do that again
you don't derive r
you don't derive x from r
immediately you do this again you will
get
u
b square
r y squared z
then if you like you can do that again
and again again right so you can do that
again if you want
and then to write again if you want
and so on
right so for each i
for each i
integer
the resultant
string is always
in that uh in the language of that
grammar
why because the past tree is always
there
and why the positive is always there
because
what we have
is to repeat
repeatedly
using
repeatedly using
the same variable and we already know
that
we already know that variable what that
variable can become
okay
so that is why we have the property of
context free grammar
uh sorry
the
property of
of pumping lame are for context-free
languages
okay
so all context-free languages
satisfy
pumping layman for context-free
languages
and which is
if a
is a context free language then there is
a confidence p
where
if s
is any string okay any string in the
language of length at least p
then
the string here
may be divided into five pieces
satisfying the three conditions first
one is that you can remove
the second and the fourth
pieces or repeat them in definite times
the resultant string is always in the
language
and the second
and the
fourth piece cannot be
[Music]
empty together
and the middle three
will be
less than or equal to p
okay
so
again like
complement for regular languages
permanent are for counter free languages
is
also a sufficient conditions
okay sufficient condition sorry
necessary condition sorry sorry
so it's also a necessary condition that
all
context-free languages
has such property
that means if a language has no such
property it's not context-free
but it doesn't mean that
if you know some language has this
property
it's a content context free it doesn't
mean that okay
so the only
way to use family name of account
accounts free languages
is to prove some language not
context-free
so how to use it
the way to use it is the same
that
we assume
a language b
to be context-free
okay
if we want to prove some language not
context-free you assume it to be
context-free first
since it is context-free the language
must have
the property described by the pumping
lemma
right
then
confidence p
exists
so for any string in the language can be
pumped if the length the string is long
enough
so we need to choose some particular
string s as our counter example
at what s must be it must be long enough
and then to prove that x
cannot be pumped as described
then we get the contradiction
so b
the language is not context free
okay so that's what we want to do here
so let's see an example for this
the example we just described that
we have a language b
which is
then
same number of a's b's and c's
okay
firstly
we assume that
the language is context-free
okay since it is context-free
there is a pumping length
for b we don't know how
what what the value what is the value
but there is a number here
then we know that for any string longer
than p must be pumped
but there must there must be some way
for that string to be pumped right
now we select
the counter example as
p asp bs and pcs
right pas pbs and pcs
so they'll be
a
b
c
and the length is p
p
m p
right
so what is the length the whole length
the whole the length of the whole string
is 3p
3p of course greater than and equal to p
so
firstly the string is long enough
okay long enough and the string is
apparently in a language
now we need to say that
we need to say that
such as there is no way to divide it the
way there is no way to divide the string
into five pieces
satisfying the three conditions
described in the polynomial for
context-free language at the same time
we must prove that it's impossible
the difficulty is that we cannot
try all possibilities
right because you don't know how
you cannot
since we don't know exactly what p is
then how can we
prove all possibilities so we need to
classify the situation and
to cover
all possibilities
okay
so we know that
for the second
condition
v y cannot both be
empty string at the same time right
and we know that
x
y
no not x y
v
x y the middle three pieces
is less than or equal to p
right we know that
the way to divide the string into five
pieces must satisfy
three conditions and this this is the
second one and the third one here
so
consider all
possible divisions satisfying
two and three
criteria two and three
we know that
we can
think of
where is the
three
middle three pieces see and
it is only
possible that
the middle three
will lie
here right because it must be
less than p right
so middle three in a
or middle three in b
or in c
right
or
cross the border like this
or cross the border like this
but
it will never
be like this
right because that would be longer than
p and it's impossible
so there are
only five
situations covers all
possibilities for dividing
the string
okay for dividing the string
then
within the five possible five situations
there are there are actually
only
[Music]
two
situations
if you consider them together
the first one is the three conditions
here that is both
the second
piece and the fourth piece
contain only one type of the alphabet
alphabet symbol right
so for the
situation number one here
b and y contains only a
so the situation number two here
b and y
contains only b
only a's only b
and for situation number three here
only c's
right
since
only one type of the alphabet symbols
is content
then you know that
as long as you check you
you all know that
for example if they are both a
then for the whole string here
you will have
more a's than b's and c's
right
so
the resultant string
will
be not in the language
right or your u and the y
content contain only b
then
after repeating v and y
the number of b
this b okay not the language b the the
alphabet symbol b
small b
will be
more
b's than
a's and c's
so that's not in c and also goes to
c
right
then again
for
c the same thing so
we know that for the
condition here it's impossible to have a
way to divide
the
counter example string here
then
let's go to the
second situation
the fourth
situation here
v
probably
v and y we don't know which part okay
but we know that together they probably
have both a and b
okay
or for the fifth situation here
it may they may both
together have b and c
but if they have b a and b
the same thing here
they are not in b
why
because they have only a and b and you
repeat b and y so the number of a
of a's and b's they may be you know kept
identical
but
the number of c's is not
increased right the number of c's stay
the same as what
p here
so the resultant string
will definitely not in b
okay
again
if v and y
together have b and c
same argument
the number of
a's
stay the same as p
no
no increase in the number of a's
so
the resultant string by repeating
v and y
will
be not in b
so
by
using the argument here we know that
there is no way
absolutely no way
to
divide
ap
bpcp here
into
three pieces satisfying
the three conditions
described
by
pumping lima for
context free language
like as here
there's no way
so we know that
we know that
the language
a n b and c n is not context free
okay so let's go back to see when
when
b
y one of them is empty string
it's actually quite easy because
if you see
the previous example we have here
see let's say
okay easy simple maybe okay
let's do this
okay
see
any string here
okay
on the path tree
they use the same variable
again right
since we have only one variable
any steps more than one you use the same
variable
then you know that
it can become
you know
so
that that makes it r
and of course it's only also r but we we
just use the
uh
last two so
this is x
right
and
another accessory
and these are
derived
this part
and the whole thing derives this part
okay
so we have
z here
and
we want to have u v
x y z
right
and let's use t okay
so t
derives
what
u
r
z
and r
the first r derives what
u uh
v
[Music]
r
y
then second r
derives x
okay
so here this a is x
and here
is b
and the u
is empty
and the y
okay
so
in this case
we will get t
derives
empty
r
z
and of course z eventually becomes xa
and sorry
the x here is not the x it's the this
part
so times a okay
and then the
first r here
derives
v
which will become a plus
r
and y y is empty right
and r here
derives
a
so
see
the fourth part here is
empty
and you can see that
we can repeat
v
indefinite times and the result in the
string is still in the language
okay
and
if you go with the
parser here you will have
second piece
as empty string
right if you choose r here and r here
so you will have
these parts as
u and the z
empty
because you have x as this one
and r
and
that will be y
right
so
you can see the situation that when your
position or the duplicated variables
are
you know uh
on the leftmost or on the right most
the second or fourth pieces will be
empty
okay
will be empty
okay so that's the that's why
in pumping layman for countless three
languages
we have the criteria that
b
y cannot both be
empty
they can
it is possible one of them is empty but
they cannot be both empty because you
always have some terminal strings
generated
along the way okay
okay
then let's go back to
here
then we know that
by using
pumping lemma for context-free languages
we can prove
actually we already proved
a language
b
a n
b n
c n
outside of
regular sorry contest-free languages
right
so we know
sadly
context-free languages are not
all possible languages
there are languages
not context free
and here is the concrete example
right
so we need to face the problem that uh
well pda country grammar
are not universal computational models
okay
so
that's it for now
we know that
there are something
here
and
probably many languages outside of
context three languages
that's
we can know so far
okay