for the last part of chapter 2
we are going to introduce
cyk algorithm for a membership test what
is
a membership test
if you have
a context-free language l
given
a string w
you want to know that
if
string w belongs to l or not
okay
and we know that it is
doable because
in mathematical way of thinking you can
derive since
w is given so the
length of w is known
and you can
use
the grammar for l
and start from the start variable let's
say s
and derive
all possible
strings
of which the length is
less than and or equal to w
then if you if you uh find that there is
no string
in
all the strings here
let's say x
and
x
and you'll find that
all the string derived
from
the star variable
of length
equal to or less than
w
within these strings there is no w then
w does not belong to l
otherwise you can find the derivation
from star variable to that string and
you know that the string
w is in l
okay so that's
for
uh in the mathematical
way it is doable
but
such a thinking is not practical for
real world you cannot use such a
thinking in
practical use
so we need some more efficient algorithm
for
testing membership of a string
so
here is the cyk algorithm and c y and k
are last names of the
uh proposing
this algorithm
okay
so uh
the basic idea of cyk algorithm is uh
also quite straightforward
quite intuitive
suppose that
for l
since l is a
context free
language
you can have the context with grammar
for l right
then we assume that the context three
grammar is in chomsky normal form
okay in chomsky no more form
and as we have proof that any
context free grammar can be converted
into chongqing normal phone
possibly with some exception
for epson right for empty string but you
can see that in the membership test case
you can test
empty string upfront so there's no
problem
for such an
exception
let's say if url has empty string then
you can just um
convert to a chomsky convert the grammar
into chomsky normal phone without
the empty string and when you do the
membership test you can
when you see empty string you say yes
that's no problem right
and
if your
language arrow
has no empty string then there is no
problem at all you can convert
the
given grammar into chongqing normal
phone
without any exception and that grammar
will be valid
for
chongqing normal phone
so why do we need
because
cnf
chomsky normal phone makes
this kind of job easy
okay
so uh easy put
if you re let's review the requirement
of chomsky normal phone
for
grammar in chomsky normal phone
that means
the rule of your grammar
is in uh
there are only two forms for the rules
in chomsky normal form one is that you
have one variable may become
two variable right and the other is that
you have one variable
become a terminal something like
these two
and of course there can be no start
variable appear
on the right hand side on the body part
and
uh
if
we allow an exception that uh the star
variable can become epsom okay
so that's our chomsky normal phone so
uh
if you have only these two kinds of
rules then you can imagine that
for any terminal strings
derived
by from the start variable now
the whole process would like
you have for example the
string here is like a
[Music]
let's say
w1 w2 w3
2wn right and the wi
is symbol
and since you have rules uh you have
only two kinds of rules so you will you
we can know that each symbol
directly derives from some variable
right for example
uh let's say variable a1
able a2
variable a3
and
variable am right
because
the rule for the right the rule can let
you have terminals only
only are in this
format
then you can see that
then
the
for the bottom side of the path three
you will have one variable corresponding
to one terminal according to
this kind of rules
right then you have quite limited
situation for variable two variable
because you have only this kind of rules
one variable to two variables may become
two verbal right
so for example
these two variables must be
derived from one
one variable or
these two variables must be derived from
one variable
right
so the possibilities are
kind of
fewer than if you don't limit the
possible
formats for the
rules so by doing this we can
push
from bottom
to top
right
so for example we can assume that uh
okay these two
if these two
are
from one variable then we see
is is it possible to have this one
or
these two from one variable is it
possible there is a variable like this
and another variable becomes this one
so
c y k
the c like algorithm
tries to ex
exploit this kind of relationship and
working from bottom to top to see
which variable in the given grammar can
derive
for some particular length of the
terminal string
okay
so
we will construct
a table
some like
the uh like the one we show here
and
for the terminal string
we separate the
terminals
okay so for this example we have a
terminal string
of length five
so that would be
five symbols a1 a2 a3 a4 and a5
and then
as i just explained
because the given grammar is in chomsky
normal form
for each
terminal symbol
you will
get that terminal symbol from exactly
one variable
uh i'm sorry not
i mean that's terminal will be from one
variable but that that variable will
uh will probably not be unique variable
in the grammar so
we can
put all variable
which can derive a one
in this
box okay and for the same reason we put
all variable that can derive
a 2 in this box and then
a 3 a 4 a 5
right
then you can think of this row for
example we call it row one okay
row one
this row
is
responsible for deriving
length
a terminal string of length one
right
so
let's say
this box the variables in this box
will be those
which can derive
a1
and the variables in this box will be
those which can derive
a2 and
this box
a3
etc okay
a4
and
a5
so that's the that's row 1
then
row 2
will be what
we want to have variables in this box
which can derived
which can derive
terminal
of length two terminal strings of length
two like in this uh example that will be
a1a2
and we want to
have variables in
this box
x
x 2 3
to be able to
derive
a 2 a3
okay
and variables in this box
derives
a 3 a4
the same goes to 4 5
which is
a4 a5
yes a4a5
okay
so it looks like
it will look like
for row 1 we
have variable deriving of these
substring of the given terminal string
and one two means we want to have
variables
we want to have variables
able to
give you
one a one a two
and the two three means we want to have
variable able to give you a to a three
so three four
three four four five
four five
right
so that's the responsibility for row one
row two and for row three yes we want to
have variables here
be able to derive what
a 1 a 2 a 3
1 3 okay
then 2 4
a 1
a 2
sorry a 2 a 3 a 4 and a 3 5
5 that's row 3 okay so the same thing
goes to 1 4
1 2 3 4
2 5
2 three four five and that's the row
four finally one five that's the whole
given terminal strings
okay
then why we why why do we want to build
this way because you can see that
for
the
since we have only two
kinds of rules in chongqing normal form
context free grammar right so that the
rule
variable the rule regarding variable
becomes variable is
e r o in this form a becomes b c
so consider that
b some variable
can derive
a one
let me use another
color here
consider the variable
derived a1 that will be in here right
possible
variable bs are in here and the possible
variable a's are in here
then we can fill in this box
with
the variable able to
derive
b
and
c right
and also
for a13
since a variable
becomes two variables
then
if you want to fill in a 1 at x 1 3
the variable in x1 suite of the box
b made from
x 1 1 c from
x
2 3
right because
some variable from x 1 3 becomes a
variable in
x 1 1 then it can become a 1
then
from
uh
another ver the other variable from x23
then it may
derive
a2 and a3 then you can have a one two
three
and the other possibility in this case
is that some variable from a
x one two
and the other from
three three you also have a one a two a
three
that's why we build the table this way
because we can
we can have all possible
all possibilities
included in the procedure of cyk
algorithm
okay
so the whole cyk algorithm
looks like uh here
firstly we build up
we we draw an empty table
then
we use the first kind of
rules
a variable may become a terminal
to fill up the bottom row that what i
called row one
then we use
we use the second
rules of the second kind to check all
possibilities and the field into the
corresponding box
then we will know
we will know
which variable in that given grammar can
derive some specific substrings of the
given terminal string
okay
so you may not be familiar with how the
basis induction step goes
but let's take a look at the example
then you will
it should be quite
clear how the cyk algorithm works
okay
so
let's see we have uh
uh we have a
grammar here
so uh let's check
is the grammar in chomping normal phone
firstly the grammar has s a b c five are
four variables
and there are
eight rules
and then
all the rules are either in
a variable may become two variable or a
variable may become one terminal right
and you can further check that there is
no start variable
on the
body part
so the grammar is no problem in
chongqing normal phone
then
let's say
the terminal string we want to check
if this string in
the language
generated by this grammar or not is
a b-a-a-b-a
okay
b-a-a-b-a
then
okay then
firstly
we
have a table uh empty table
then
we separate all symbols of the
given terminal string which is
b
a
a b
right
then
for the
for the basis
step
we just write
any variable
which can derive
this terminal
on
into
this into this
box right and you can check only
b can generate b
so
we write b
in this box
okay
and for the same procedure
we see we see that uh a can maybe count
may become a c
capital a may become
terminal a and capital c variable c may
become terminal a
into the box
right that means
variable a
may become
a
and also variable c may become a so this
this terminal a maybe from variable a or
from variable c
okay
so
here goes the same thing so a
c
and also here b and a
then we have finished
row one here
right so we know that for the given
terminal string
all
substrings of length 1 we know how they
can be derived
by the given grammar by the given rules
okay
then
we go into the induction steps so
firstly we want to fill up row two
right row two
so what what uh
what should uh row two boxes
in row two
do
we want this
box which is
we want this box to be able to generate
terminal string ba right
and also this box to be able to generate
terminal a a
something like that
okay so
if we want to generate let's
do the box
x12 here first
if we want to generate
ba
okay if we want to generate ba
what should we
what do we need
since
b can derive b right
a
can derived
derives a
and c also can derive a
then we need something
we need something derived va
or bc
right
then we check up the body part of the
grammar rule since all the rules
are in the form of
one variable may become two variables so
we check ba
so is there any ba here yes it is
right
so we
know that a may become ba
and we check b there's no b there's no b
a out of in other rules right so a may
become b a
and let's check bc so we have okay bc
here so as
bc here
right
so that means
in this
in this grammar
you may
have a
derived ba
then
b
derive to b
then
a derive to a
or you also can have
s become b c
and b
may become
b
and the c become a
okay so we put x oh sorry a and s into
this box
to indicate that
by the given grammar from variables a
or a
or
we can derived
we can derive
ba
the terminal string ba okay
so that's why we have s and a here
okay
so according to what we just discussed
then for the same reason
we want to
have
so we put
s and a here
and then for the same reason we want to
have variables put in here
which can generate which can derive
substring of the terminal string a a
okay row two
length two
okay
from the
position
then
we know that a can generates a
c also can generate a right
so we pair up all the possibilities so
we will have
we will
want to check
what variable can generate a
a
a c
c a
c c
right so there are four possibilities
then we check the uh
body of the all the rules to c a a a c c
a c c
right
so there's no a a
there is no ac
there is no ca only cc right so which
one this one and we know that b
may become
cc
so we write b we put b into the box that
means
from the variable of the grammar from
the variable from variable b of the
grammar it can derive c c
and c can become a
and the other c become a
so
variable b
may derive terminal string a a
so we put b in that box
like
this
okay b
can have
a a
then
same thing goes on we want to have a
variables
in this box
we want to have variables in this box
which can derive
a b
okay from here that's two
then we know a may become a c may become
a and the b may become b
so we want to check
for uh
for the given grammar
is there any variable may become a b
and
c b
right
so for a b
there are two variables right s
so s may become
a b c may become a b
and for c b there is no c b on the right
hand side so no c b
so we put
s
and c here
okay so that means x may become a b and
a become a b become b or c may become a
b and a become a b becomes b
okay
then for the last
for the last box of row two
same thing goes to ba
and we actually have filled up that so
that's
sa
right it's the same ba so ba the same
terminal string so actually that
well
i shouldn't say that we need to do that
again too so ba
bc
and no bc and ba 4a
sorry bc here so s
so sa
okay
so that's probably
it
for row two
okay
then
after row two we know we
we now know all the variables in this
given grammar which can generate
the
substrings of the given terminal string
of length 2
right substrings of length two of the
given terminal strings
then we continue to build up
row three here
okay
then for row three here
what do we want
in
this box
we want to have variables
in the given grammar
which can generate
from the first position here of
lens three
okay
and four length three
they unlike length two two you have one
plus one but for lens 3 you need to
consider 1 plus 2
or 2 plus 1. why because one variable
can only generate two variables
if you need to have a terminal string of
length three
then you must have one variable becomes
two variable and the one of the variable
becomes two
variable
again then you have three
okay so first possibility is that
one and two so
for the three
terminals here
we want to check up
1 plus 2
and
plus
two possibilities
right
and for 1 plus 2
what is 1 here
what is one here
one here is this box
all this two here
two here is this box right
so we want to see
if it is possible
to have
some variable becomes bb
right
let's say if it is possible
then we can know that first b
may derived b
and then second b
may derived
what uh what is in this case a a a b c a
c c okay maybe comes c c
then
the both c becomes a that's what we want
right
if some variable can generate bb
okay so that's one plus two
one
and
two
okay
so let's check if the any right hand
side of any rule have
bb
okay the answer is no
so we don't have any variables in this
grammar which can generate
bb then
after derivations we got baa
okay it's a dead end here
let's say the other possibility is 2
right
2 1 then what is 2 2 is here
and what is 1 1 is here right
so the same
argument
if we would like to have possibly let's
say
a's a
s c
a
a c
right
if let's say if we have a a here if
then
we know that the first a can
have
b
a
okay the first a b a
so that's two plus one what i said two
plus one yes
then the first b becomes b
second a becomes
second a becomes a and the final a
becomes a then we have baa
but unfortunately you can see that there
is there is no rule
there's
no rules right hand side
generate
the four combinations here
okay
and actually you can know that it's part
impossible for these two
why because
for our chomsky normal phone
start variable cannot be in the right
hand side in the body part of the rules
right
so you check
anyway
s-a-a-s-e-a-a-c there's no rule
generated from one variable to these two
variables
so
unfortunately we have nothing here okay
that's nothing that means for the given
grammar it is impossible from any
variable not only start variable any
variable
can
derive b
a a that's impossible for this grammar
from any variable not only the star
variable
okay
then let's say
what do we want to have in this box we
want to have the variables which can
generate the terminal string a a b
okay so one plus two or two plus one so
that's a one plus two
for one plus two we need to look at this
box and this box right
because
this box generates one
these box generate two
so
let's
have four pairs here a s
a c
c s
c c
right
then again if let's just say if there is
a
some some variable can generate a c c
for example cc
then from cc we have we can
we can have the first c derives a usa
right and the second c
second c
may have may become
that's
one stable at a time
then
the second c
derives a b
then the first a derives a
and the second a derives b then we will
have this one okay so let's check the
right hand side of all rules to see
any rules can derive asc cscc
but as we just described
for chomsky normal phone actually we
don't
need to check this one and this one
right
because star variable cannot be on the
right hand side so let's check ac and cc
and there's no rules generating ac
right but we have
b may become cc here yes so we know b
can derive cc
so we write b in this part
okay
so that's the one plus two we still need
to finish two plus one right
so for two plus one what is
2 plus 1 what is we already have b here
and what is 2 here 2 here is this one
and
1 here is this one
so we want to see if there is any bb
here
if
there
there is some rule generating bbe
same we can use
the first b
to have cc
that's we already know it's there are
rules for this right
then
let's say
after derivation first c become a second
c become a lets b
become b that's what we want but there
is no rule generating bb so no rule
then
after all we have
nothing here b here right that's what we
have now
then
for row 3
we have one
we have one more
box to go
which
generates a b a
okay
so again one plus two
and
two plus one
so one plus two we one we look at this
one and the two this one
right so
a s
a a
c s
c a
a s a a c s c a right and we don't need
to look at this one and this one because
there's no star star variable on the
right hand side of rules
so so for a a and c a
okay
aa there's no aa
and the ca there's no ca okay so there's
no variable going through one plus two
style to generate aba
right
then
let's check two plus one
so what is two plus one that will be two
here
just
which can generate the two here right
and one here which can generate one here
so that would be
s a
s c
c a
c c
again no need to check s a s c because
no star variable on the right hand side
and for ca no ca but we have b
may become cc
right
so
that's what we want b
derives cc
and
2 plus 1 right so the first c
further becomes
a b
then the first a becomes a
and second b becomes b
uh the last c becomes a so that's what
we want so
so we can have b here
okay
so now
after
the finish of row 3 we know that
from the gram of b
from the variable b in the grammar
it is possible that b after some steps
of derivations
can generate
a
b and
by using another
sequence of derivation it can generate
a e b a right these two
and
tracing back to how we construct the
entry how we put the entries into the
table we know we actually know
little that derivation
right that's the interesting part of
cyk algorithm
okay so let's go on to finish the whole
thing so row 4 what is row 4 here
for
the
sorry
for the box here
we want to have
variables in the grammar which can
generate
a
oh sorry b a a b length of four
and four four there will be three
possibilities
one plus three right and the two plus
two or three plus one three
possibilities
so for the first possibility 1 plus 3 we
already have the data
in the
table right
so
plus
here
right so we just need to check
if there is any variable
may become bb
again if there is if there is what we
want
what we will have is the first b becomes
b
right
then
the second b
becomes
derives
a a b that's one plus 3
right
but
there's no
rules
generates bb so
not working here
then let's check
2 plus 2.
okay so what is two plus two
that would be
two
plus
okay
two plus two so we need to see
ss right s c
a s
a
c
and there's no need to check ss s c s
right because uh again stars variable
will not be on the right hand side so we
need to check
ac
but there's no ac here there's no ac
here so
nothing
no rule in this grammar able to generate
ac or two plus two b a a b right
then finally three plus one
plus
1 here
and you know it doesn't work why because
no variable in this grammar may generate
this substring
so finally we have nothing here
we have nothing here
that means
for this given grammar
any variable not only the star variable
from any variable it is impossible to
generate b
a
a b
this substring it is impossible
okay so we
also know this extra information here
why would i call it extra information
because all we want to know if this
given string is a member of this
language or not right that's the goal
but
uh
during the procedure
of the
of uh
of knowing that
knowing the answer we know that many
additional information can be obtained
then
for the second box for the last box of
row 4 we want to know if
from any variable it
is it possible to generate b
or a a b a
so again we have uh three plus uh one
plus three two plus two and the three
plus one three possibilities
so let's say
uh first possibility
one plus
three so what is one here one here is
this box right
and the three is
here so we want to check if there is any
variable of the given grammar
i have a b
c b
right
so a b actually we have that's s and c
right a b but no c b here so we can
write s and c here
so
for 2 plus 2
two the first two is
here
the second two is here right because
this one generates this string and this
one generates this string
okay
so
we have bs
b i'm sorry
bs
b a
like this
but b is no need to check because no
star variable on the right hand side and
the ba yes we have ba here so we have a
here
okay and finally three plus one three
plus one
so what is three here 3 here is
this one
and the one here is
this one okay
so that would be
b a
b
c
and actually we have ba and the bc which
is a for ba
and s for bc so again
a and s
since there is duplicate there's no no
point to add them but if you want to if
you want to check all possible
derivations you can have a
have some information written in the box
to know that
see that's very uh that's interesting
that
from a you can go
ba
right
and then from b a you actually have two
possibilities to generate the final
terminal string a a b a
right
for this ba you have two plus two style
for this ba you have three plus one
style
right so that's interesting and we won't
go that any further and we stop here so
we have
s
a
c on the row four
okay
so finally we want to have
row 5 here and we have and what is this
box do
we want to have
we want to put
the variable in the given grammar that
can generate
exactly this given
terminal strings
okay
then since one variable may become two
variables we want to check we want to
check uh
one plus four
two plus three
what should i say two plus three and
three plus two and
one plus
uh sorry four plus one four
possibilities
because one variable
is responsible for generate this part
and the second this part or other
similar like this part and this part
something like this okay
so first possibility one plus four
so one plus or one plus four what is one
one here right
and four here one plus four that means
if it works then b here generates 1
and the variable
here generates a a
b a that's i y i called 1 plus 4.
so
what variable pairs we have we will have
bs
ba
bc in this case right three pairs
and there's no bs
yeah no bs okay
because uh star variable will not be on
the right hand side so we check ba and
bc
and the ba a may become b8 okay great
and s may become bc
so
we have
s and a written here
okay or i put it into the
box
s and a
here
good
then two plus two what is two
two plus two in this case is
the this one is two
oh sorry two plus three sorry and two
two plus three here is two
is this box
and three is this box right
because this box
is responsible for generating ba and the
list box is responsible for generating
aba
okay so what pairs uh if if there is any
variable
generating
sb
or
ab
then we can go on to have
terminal string ba and the termination
aba
okay
so sb
no because knows s here
on the right hand side and then a b
yes we have c may become a b so we
will put c here
okay
so that's for two plus 2.
see
2 plus 2 means
c can derive a b right according to this
rule
then a
here
not two plus two sorry two plus three a
may eventually derives
b a and the b here may eventually derive
a b a
so two plus three that's our terminal
strings
okay
then
the
third
third possibility is
3 plus 2. so what is 3 3 in this case is
this one
and the 2 will be this one
2 plus 3
2 this one
right 2 plus 3.
since there is no variable
able to generate
b
a a in this grammar
there is no variable
pair generated
we can
discover and the same thing goes to
4 plus 1
right
because
in this grammar
there is no variable at all
no variable at all
able to generate b
a a b
so we won't have
any variable being to generate some
variable and another variable then
generate the whole terminal string
that's impossible
so we don't have
variables generated by
three plus two and the four plus one
okay so finally we will have
s
a
c
on row five the final row we uh we want
to construct the final box we want to
construct it okay
okay so
we finally can have our answer that's if
this given terminal string b a a b a
belongs to uh does this terminal string
belong to
l of g
or not
then that's going back to our derivation
definition
what what what is l of g
what is the the definition
l of g is defined as all
strings
which
which is
from the derivation start from the start
variable right
that's what we
have for the definition
then remember that from start variable
so we want to check if the start
variable
in this
box or not okay
a or c
don't matter
but
we just need to check if s
if the star variable in
this box or not
okay so in this case yes
right
then you know that
from s
you can have a derivation to derive
b a a b a
okay we actually need to
keep some information during the process
so we can make it easier but we can
still try to uh
derive it like s may become uh sorry s
derives and we know that it must be like
uh one plus four right or
two uh two plus three it should be one
plus four right
so let's say s
derives bc
so we want it to be like b
and
c here right
then let's make the first b
derives here
then i actually forgot uh where
b goes
right where
c can become
a b so i guess that will be
a and b right
so let's make it a b
then
the a
becomes
is one and the b is responsible for aba
right
then
we have derivation
b
a
and the b
becomes
this c
and this c
okay
so c c
and
the first c
becomes
a
b
so we have b a
then a become a
and then
b become b c become a okay we uh we
succeeded in the life deriving
from the star variable to the given
terminal string like this okay
so
if we can we we leave some information
during the construction it makes it
easier but we can anyway we know that
there is a path reversed so the
derivation can be obtained from the
start variable to the given terminal
string that means that given terminal
string
is a member of the language generated by
the given grammar
okay so that's the cyk algorithm
then let's say
if
you don't have s
you don't have s if you don't have s in
this box
that means
the terminal string is not
is not a member of the language
okay
but you say oh a is in the box and the c
is in the box yes
that only means
from the variable a
or c
in the grammar
you can
actually derive to derive
b-a-a-b-a that's that's no problem
but
in order to consider a string a member
of the language
it must be from the star variable so
even we have some variable
in
let's say
box
x15
that doesn't mean that variable is a
member string
only as only the start variable
in that box
indicates the given terminal string is
in the language
okay that's the first note
then
also note that
after constructing the whole table
you basically know about all
substrings of the given terminal string
why because
not only
we now know that not only baaba is in
the language
but
what other substring of dependent string
c as here right
so we know ba
is also in the language
but b is not
a string only b is not right
and
cs here so we also know that
a a b a
is
in the language let's say
not only
b a b a we know that b a is in a
language in the language and we also
know that a
a
b a
in the same language
right
and see here
that would be
a b
and as here that will be
b a
in the language
okay i guess that's probably all of them
right so we will know that
all the substring the membership o of
all the substring of the terminal string
of the given terminal string to test the
membership
and all others are not in the language
right for example
you see b here
that that's uh this box this box
corresponds to
aab
then we know that a a b
is not in that language
right because no
no variable no not no the star variable
cannot derive that string
and
of course something like this one
b a a b
is not in the language because
absolutely no variable can derive this
substring
so the same goes to for example this
this one so that will be
a b a
aba
not in the language
okay
so constructing such a table we know
much more than
if the given terminal string
in is in the language or not we also
know
we also can know a lot of
extra information regarding the terminal
string okay
and we also know which variable can
generate the substring of the terminal
string
okay so a cyk algorithm can efficiently
test the membership in
instead of you know try all possible
durations
we can just do the
button up
do the test in the style of button up
patient and very efficient
compared to trying all possible
derivations that would be a breakfast
search right that's not efficient in
this case
okay so
uh that will be all for chapter two
and uh also that will be all for
uh the content of chapters one and two
which is the
which is the scope of our first
return examination