okay we have introduced pumping lemma
for context-free language so we have a
way to prove some
language not to be
context-free
now we are going to introduce
we are going to introduce another
layman for country languages which is
called organs lemma for context free
languages okay
and
unlike
my here on the road theorem for
regular languages
ogden's lemma for context free languages
is
not a sufficient and necessary condition
okay it is a
it is an advanced version of pumping
lemma
for context free languages so
basically you can
think of ogden's lima for context with
languages
providing you more
way
to
prove
another way
more
control on how you can construct the
counter examples okay
so uh let's describe the layman first
then we discussed the uh difference
between this layman and pampynema for
context free languages so what is
ogden's lemar for context free languages
if a line if
a the language a is a context free
language then there is a number p which
is basically pumping length okay
then there is a number p where
any string all strings
in a
of length at least p
okay you see here
until here is exactly the same as
pumping them up for context free
languages okay
here is the difference
in which
we select any p or more
positions
p or more positions to be distinguished
okay you can consider
it as
some position you want to look at and
ignoring others something like that
but the criteria is you have to select p
or more positions okay at least p at
least
p
at least p or more positions
the string s
may be
divided into five pieces
five pieces satisfying the following
conditions
firstly
the second and the fourth pieces
can be removed
which is i equals little or can be
pumped
some
identical to what we have in pumping
lemma
etc
all of them are will be still in that
language okay that's the first condition
and second condition is that
the second and the fourth piece
at least one
distinguished positions which you just
choose at
this step
okay
and
third condition is that the middle three
pieces head
has at most p
distinguished positions okay that's all
that's all organ slimmer for context
with languages
so essentially
it's very very similar to pumping demand
for complexity languages only that
you have one more control here you can
select some positions to be
distinguished
okay and the only criteria is that you
have to select p or more
let's uh
look at this way
if for any string s
for any string s
in the language
you select the whole string
okay you select the whole string since
the length of
s
is at least p
if you select the whole string every
symbol
is distinguished
then you can see that the whole organs
lemma for contextview languages becomes
pumping them up for context languages
right because if you select
the whole string as positions as
distinguished positions
then
the first condition is exactly the same
as
that's in pumping demand
the second condition since you select
all positions as distinguished so
the number of positions is exactly
the same as the depth of you know the
strings and also goes for
vxy
right
so for any select for any string in a
of length at least p
if you select all positions
the whole
octane's lemma goes back to pumping
lemma
so you see now you have a way to select
fewer positions
if your string
the length of your
s is exactly you have no choice right
but
if you have a string longer than p
then
you don't need you don't need to select
them oh you just need to select p or
more positions then
the lemma will work
so that's our control on
establishing control examples okay
so
let's firstly have an example
of this language
okay we will prove that
not really
yes it's proof we will prove that this
language can be pumped okay this
language satisfies pamping lemma for
contextual language
but we can use ogden's lemma for
contextual language to prove that this
language is not context-free
okay
so
what what is this language
it the string of this language composed
of
four symbols a b c d
and you have i a's j b k c's and l ds
okay
and
you either
have
no a's
or
bcd the number of bcds
are identical
so it's like
if you have a let's say if you have a
then
you have you have some a's
then you must have same number of b c d
okay so that's the first case
uh sorry it actually is the second case
here
if you don't have a
the number of b
c
d
is arbitrary
right
i equal to 0 noise then you have no
restriction on bcd
or if you have a
bcd
must be
of the same length okay so the language
the the language contains such strings
then let's check
for pumping lemurs okay for pumping
lemmas
for any
p
greater than zero and
any string in the language okay in this
language let's call it l
and for any string
there are two forms right firstly i
equal to zero
in this case
the string looks like
jb's kcd
kcs and lds
and
jk arrow can be any integer
so
it it apparently
satisfies pumping lemma
right
you can arbitrarily actually you can
arbitrarily
uh split any string
uh split strings like this to any five
pieces
as long as
you have
second and the
fourth piece none empty
and the middle three
less than p
then
you can choose
the middle three only one symbol
then it doesn't matter that
how you pump or remove that string
because
ijk can be any integer so
as long as
the second piece and the fourth piece
contains only one kind of symbol doesn't
matter which one but you can manipulate
them right
so
a string
of this form
in that language can be
pumped
okay
so here is an example
we can choose
the second
piece as b
and
x epsilon y epsilon
so you see only b for the middle three
that would be
the length will be less than p right
so
in this case
no matter what end is no matter what n
is the resultant string must be in l
right and you can
also do that for middle three contains
only one c or one d doesn't matter they
all work
okay
for the second
format of the string
let's say you have a
you have a so i is greater than zero
in this case
j
k
l are the same right okay for this kind
of string for this kind of string we can
choose the second piece
as one a
okay you have a right so
we have one a
then x
make uh we make x epsilon y epsilon
then you see
the string is like looks like a some a's
and the b
the same
number of b and the z and the d let's
say n n n
then we choose we can
split the string into
v
just one a
and anything previous
anything before b is u
and
x epsilon
y epsilon and this part that makes it c
okay
so
if let's say if you have only one a
then v is a right and the u is epsilon
and
everything the same and when you remove
that a
it doesn't matter because this part
falls into the first kind
and if you pump it
you may you make copies of v
the i i equal
0 something like that it doesn't matter
either because you can have more a
arbitrary number of a and since
b and c n
d n is the
z
not changed so the resultant string is
still in
l
so
this
language
actually satisfies
the criteria
actually has the property described by
pumping for context free language
then
we can use
oakland's name of context free languages
to prove
this language
not to be context-free
okay so how do we use that how do we do
that
actually we
the same since uh oakland's lemma for
context free languages is you know an
advanced version of pumpkin lemon so the
whole the usage is the same
so
we assume that
the language is a context free language
so it has the property described by
ogden's lemma
then
there is a p here
so we choose an s longer than p right so
here in this case we choose
one a and p
b c d so the string looks like a
okay
see here we have
a control here let's
select
more p or more positions to be
distinguished
so we select
all this
okay and we don't select
a
so first uh sorry firstly
how long is s
that will be three p plus one right
and we select all symbols of b
c's and d's so how many position we
select we selected
which is 3p
since 3p bigger than p okay
we can do it because we select p or more
positions
in this case
see
according to wagton's lemma
for context with languages this string
this string
must be
there is a way to divide into this
string into five pieces
okay and the uv
sorry v y the second
piece and the fourth piece
must contain
one of b c d why because v y
has at least one selected distinguished
position
okay
and we know that
v
x y
has at most p positions
okay
then
consider where
v x y can go
you either
let's make it like this
so where v x y can go
you either go
this way
right
or
the
v x y
or o in b
or
cross b c
o in c
or cross c d or o in d
okay that's the only way
x b x y can go
but either way you know that
b y
cannot
v y contain
one of b or c or d
right so for example in this case
b y can possibly contain only b
right
and for this for this
possibility that will be b
and
for this possibility v y can contain b
and c
i'm not saying it contains b c but it
can contain b and c okay so for this
possibility c only for this possibility
c
d and for this
d
okay
so
because of the constraint here
v x y has at most p positions
and
we know that
v
y
cannot contain all vcds
so in any way
in any way
that's pumped
second or and fourth fourth piece
and
u v two x
y two z
will definitely not in l
right because you still have a
so for the resultant string
b and c and ds must be identical the
length of b and c and d must be
identical
and
since v and y do not have or
do not have
b and c and d at the same time
so the numbers in the resultant string
the b uh the numbers for of b and c and
these in the resultant string will not
be equal will not be identical so
the resultant string will not be in l
so the language is not
a context-free language
okay
and actually the analysis here is
exactly the same as we use pumping lemma
for context free languages to
proof a n b and c n
not
a context free language
okay
so you see when we can select
distinguished positions as long as we
follow the criteria
we have
one more control on constructing the
control examples
and therefore we can prove that
this language
we can prove that
which cannot be proved by using
pumping number for countless languages
to be not context-free
okay
and if you have no problem here
we can consider
pumping layma sorry ogden's lemon for
countless three languages and you will
know that
we can have
ogden's lemma for contest-free grammars
okay
so
family number for oakton's name of
context languages are
description of the property of languages
countless free languages and now the
layman here is for grammars okay for
grammars but
they
they they actually comes from the same
phenomenon which we have already
described
okay
before because uh
to generate
a long enough terminal string
you must have some
properties of the parse trees
that's the
uh
proper that's the source of the lemma
anyway so
let's g be a context free grammar there
exists a number p
a natural number p
such that for all strings
in the language generated by the grammar
we can mark as
to uh
so that it has p or more distinguished
positions it's the same as we have in
ogden's lemma for pumping languages so
for context-free languages
there exists a variable in the grammar
see
we know that there will be a variable in
the grammar and terminal string
x
v sorry u v x y z
satisfying the following conditions okay
it looks like
many seven conditions but actually more
they are exactly the same
as those we described previously firstly
the string s
is composed of the five strings okay so
a string may be divided into five pieces
okay
and either v or y
has distinguished positions
that is the y
has at least one distinguished positions
okay
and the v x y
hat has no more than p distinguished
positions yes at most p okay so that's
the same description
then
the four conditions here
actually is the first condition we
were talking about so from the start
variable of that grammar
of g
it must be
able to derive to
u
which is the first terminal string here
a
the variable here
and z the
the fifth
terminal string here
we have already
uh drew the
part three right so we just
make it more formally as a
theorem here so from the start variable
of that grammar
there must be
a derivation to u a c
and from a
there is a derivation to
second
piece
v
and itself a
and
fourth piece y
and also from a you can have
x
and
make them together you get
oh i shouldn't use this
make a make make them together you get
the seventh condition
okay actually the sec uh we don't need
all of them
we need the
last two you get this
right because you repeatedly use
the fifth rule then you will get x
l a can derive to
be a y
then
v
a
y squared then
v
cubic y
and so on and then you make a becomes x
so you can get any i x y i
for i
zero
okay and also you'll know that
as the star variable can derive to
this thing
so
the final
resultant string is in the language
okay
so the point of this this lemma
is to describe the property of the lay
of the grammar so we know that from the
star variable there is some
variable has this property
okay
then
we can use this uh
optimus lemma for context reground us to
to
prove something about grammars right
because now you know that okay at least
one variable
have such properties and you can then we
can use this we can use it to do
something
and what we want to do we want to prove
that
this language l
let's say
the number of a's and b's are identical
or the number of b's and c's are
identical okay
and previously we said that this
language
is inherently ambiguous that means
all possible grammars
describing
generating this language must be
ambiguous
so we we want to prove that all grammars
generating this language must be
must be ambiguous okay so that's
something about grammar so we need
ultima for contextual grammar
okay
but firstly we need to prove that this
language is a context free language
right if it is not a context languages
then
we don't need to talk about that
so
how to prove a language to be
context-free you either design a pda
right or
give the
give the grammar generating this
language so let's give a grammar
actually it's pretty easy because you
see
i equals to j over
i
j equal to k so that's a two language a
union of two languages right so let's
write the first one so
we want to have a language we want to
have language like
a n
b n
c n
okay
so
n
and
0 something like that so let's say l1 is
the language here
and it's pretty easy to write grammar
for that we
here we uh ignore the formal description
okay so we just write rules so start
from the start variable
we
use one variable here
let me
change the variable okay
so that's a
star variable
we have
we use the variable here b and c
and we want b to generate identical
numbers of a
a's and b's and use c to generate you
know c so b
may become epsilon
right
so n equals to zero
or
a
b
see that's all
and c
generates epsilon
or
what
let's say c
c
okay you will see the five rules
three
variables
finishes the
grammar
if you want to write it formally you say
that okay grammar for l1
is a full tuple
the
variable is a and b and c
and then
terminals is a b
a small case this
small case a and b
and then rules the five rows here and
the star variable is a okay
and the same thing goes to l2
let's say
you have
some a and the same number of b and c
same thing okay
so we have that let's make it like uh
d
becomes
e f
and the e
let's make it generating a okay so
epsilon
a
e
and then f
that's then epsilon generates b and c so
b
f
c
so exactly the same
oh okay very very similar
just you know some
like symmetric
so
star variable is d
and
generates ef
e either generates some a's or not and f
either generates
equal numbers of b and c or not that's
it
then this language arrow here is just a
union of the two languages as we
introduced
uh
the concept of contextual grammar we
only need to add
a new variable s
which becomes may become a
or
d
right we add one new variable as our
star variable for the
grammar for l
and the two rules a may become a
and the second rule a may become d
so you see
the language here
l here can be
generated
by
how many variables
three
six
seven seven variables
a
s a b
f
f right
sorry
seven variables
and how many rows
five
ten twelve
twelve rules
right
so
apparently this language is a context
free language
now we want to prove that
all the grammar possibly
generating this language
must be ambiguous
okay
so what is a
what what what
what what what does it mean that the
grammation figures
for the language there is at least one
string
there will be two or more pastries
that's grammar ambiguous right
so
let's start a proof
since l is a contextual languages we
just prove it
and for any context free grammar g
generating l okay so g here is an
arbitrary grammar that can generate l
by octane's lemma for context-free
grammars there
is p
a natural number for g
and without loss of generality we assume
p
is greater than one
okay
usually p
is not it won't be zero or one okay so p
equal to
greater than one
so
let's uh check out a string
s
which we we will make it
pas pb and
p plus
p plus p
factorial c
and for
uh
contrast that's uh think about another
string okay another string
p plus p factorial a's and the p c's and
the p
p b's and the pcs
right
and
you'll you see that the two string here
the two string here are both in l okay
there's no problem with that
and
we mark all b's
as distinguished
okay we mark all b's as they distinguish
for oakland's landmark for complexity
grammar we
need to mark at least the p positions
now for both strings there are exactly p
b's so there's no problem here
then
by oakton's lemma we know that
for the grammar g
it must contain a variable a
such that start from the start variable
there is a derivation there is a
derivation
to some terminal string u and then
a
and then z
okay
and for the string s prime here let's
assume that there is a variable a and b
may be the same variable or maybe not we
just use another variable to talk about
it okay
so
the star variable has
a derivation to
perhaps some other
first piece and then b and then z prime
okay so according to orton's lemma we
have this
uh derivation
after
that we know that
the variable a
have
we will have derivations for error
variable a to arbitrary and greater or
equal to zero as vn x y n
and the same thing goes to
b
okay so that's
the
inference from octane's lemma
and then we pump s
okay we pump x
well how to how to how do we pump how uh
how do we pump it
since s is
u v x y z or x prime as u prime v prime
x y from z plus uh
y prime zero right
since the only way to pump s is that the
second
peace as
ks
and the
fourth
piece as
be case
why
because you see
if you don't if the let's say there is a
way to divide the string and it can be
pumped
but
the other way is not arbitrary because
uh and
we must have the second piece as kas and
the fourth piece as kb's otherwise
otherwise the pumping won't work
okay so the uh
according to ogden's lema the only way
to pump
is
b
as kx and y as kb
so in this case
okay and the k is
within 1 to p
okay
so that's that's n
p factorial
divided by k
plus 1 okay
well the question here is can we make n
as this figure as this value
because n here must be an integer okay
so let's talk about a little bit what is
p
p is 1 oh sorry what is p factorial
p factorial is 1 times 2
p right that's a definition
and
since k
is
something
let's say k is here
so the whole thing divided by k
is
like this
so it's an integer and plus one
individual of course
so
no problem we can set we can let n as
this figure
and we know that
the whole thing
can be derived
so what can be derived
that'll be
since v
v is a k right and
repeated
it
so many times
so many times so
like this
okay
so you will have
p factorial plus k a
and
x here
and then
b
factorial plus kb
and for the other string we have this
with the same reason okay we have this
then
you see
according to obtain's name of a
contextry grammar
from the start variable
we will have a direction to uaz
and
a
we have a derivation from a to this
string
so we plug this string into here we got
this one
okay
and since the second three second pieces
is second piece is
kase these parts become
v and these parts become y
right
and
we know that
what is u
u v
x
y
z what is it
this
is s
right and oh sorry string s that's the
variable not the star variable okay and
what is this what is the string the
string is
a
pas
p b
and
p factorial plus p
c
so
you plug p factorial a
into
somewhere inside this and also p
factorial b somewhere inside this
you get
p plus p
p factorial plus p a and the p factorial
plus p b
and also p factorial plus p c
okay so
number
of abc are the same
that means
from some variable
to derive
to derive a string like this
and for the same process we can we can
know that from the start variable of the
same the
front variable of grammar g
we also have a way
via
another probably another
verbal and another terminal string to
pump
this string what is this string which is
p
plus p factorial a right and the
pb's
p c that's our
that's our start starting point right
and from this starting point by doing
the
pumping like this
we can
have the same string
okay we have we can have the same the
same string
so
up
uh
it looks like we have two derivations
right we have two derivations from star
variable going through two derivations
getting the same string
if so
the grammar is ambiguous right if so the
grammar is ambiguous so now we need to
prove that
the two process the two derivation here
are actually different
they represent different
trees
we must prove that okay otherwise it is
possible
the same derivation or corresponding to
the same past tree
you you just are writing the derivation
of one pastry with different orders or
something
that's not what we want we want to prove
that
these two derivation this one and this
one actually corresponds to different
parts trees then we proved
then we can prove the grammar is
ambiguous
so
let's say
the two parts three
are different
okay
so left hand side we have from start
variable we have uaz and finally gets
the string like this
and from the right hand side we have
this and getting this
and
let's say
the alpha is the string of this
and the beta is a string of this okay
we know that
the variable a
derived alpha and the variable c derives
beta
and
let's say
if
if they are
describing the same pastry
if they are describing the same pastry
this part
and
must be
either
disjoint
or
one is the subtree of the other
okay
if the two derivation
you think about this as this way
corresponds to
the same parse tree
this part
must be disjoint
on the terminal strings
or
another
sorry a subset one is the subset of
it is impossible that
for some
that make it this way for some variable
here
and if the variable is here the
corresponding terminal will be here
right
and impossible that you have another
variable here but generate overlap
overlapped
terminals it's impossible for
context-free languages
right
so
let's see
since from the variable a
a generate a generates this part of the
terminal string
and the b generate
this part of terminal string
let's say the whole terminal string is
this right the whole terminal string
and we we know that
this terminal string has
p plus
p of p factorial plus pbs
okay
and we know
alpha has zombies beta
beta has some b
and
since p
greater than one
oh sorry not this
since k
is
within 1 and p
so alpha at least has at least p plus 1
b
beta or also has
at least one
factorial p factorial plus one b's
but you we know that the the
the whole terminal string has only
p plus 1 p
b
so
it cannot be
separate to beta and alpha because p
factorial plus 1
is greater than
p factorial plus p
divided by 2.
so
alpha and the beta
must
overlap
okay
why because
the total number of b's in the terminal
string
cannot be cannot satisfy the number of
these contents
in
alpha and in beta
so
they must be overlapped there must be
overlapped portion of the terminal
string
however
however what is alpha
alpha has some a's
right
and the beta has some b c's
so
neither alpha nor beta
is
a substring of the other
and we know that as we just described
if the two derivation here
representing
the same
posture
the portion of terminal string derived
from a
and the portion of terminal string
derived from b
are either disjoint okay are either
disjoint on the terminal string that is
determination here and this part derived
from a
and this part derived from b
or
this part arrived from a or b and the
other part is a substring that's the
only two possibilities
for the derivation of context-free
grammar contextual language it is not
possible for the same
parse tree to have something like this
okay
but now we seem to have this case so
it's a contradiction
that means
for the particular string here
for a particular string here
any grammar g
for l
has
two
different
parse trees
so we know that
any grammar g for l must be
ambiguous okay must be ambiguous
so
l is inherently
ambiguous
because
all possible grammar generating l
are ambiguous
okay so we have it proved