last time we talked about
the relationship among classes of
languages like
like the
diagram shows in figure 4.10
and last time we proved that
decidable
and to recognizable are different
classes and of course by definition we
know that
two indecidable languages are within two
recognizable languages and
we approved
a
language here which is
atm
okay
so
in theory we can think about that atm is
is an undecidable but two recognizable
languages
then
currently we uh to currently
turn
turin recognizable
is the
uh
let's say
largest
class of languages that we know
we can find turing machine which is you
know
a way of computation
to handle although
recognizable
as we
discussed last time recognizable
languages are not really considered
computable
in
practice right so because
given any
problem instances
the
the language uh the er the algorithm or
the turing machine
might not be able to answer that
so
anyway but
the next question is that
as we as we asked before the next
question is
is turin recognizable
all the possible languages
is the class of to recognizable
all
contents all possible
languages
okay
so that's the next question
then
for the uh figure here
that question can be translated to let's
say
is there any language
is there any languages
outside
of
turin recognizable
is there anything
outside of the
biggest largest
eclipse eclipse
that's the question okay
so
uh
that's what we want to
discuss in this lecture
apparently
you've guessed yes there are something
there right but
that's what we are discussing right now
so
before we do that we need to have some
uh
mathematical tools mathematical weapons
in our arsenal so that we can use it to
do the discussion okay
so uh
what we want to introduce is
called the diagonalization method
okay the
diagonalization method
well firstly we want to
introduce a way
to measure the sizes of infinite set
of infinite sets
okay
so
let's say if you have two
sets
can you compare
or can you say that uh this set
has more members than
the other
so let's
give an example here
let's say
you have two
you have two balls
okay
and
there are green beans
they are green beans
in the
in the left
ball
and red beans in the right
okay
then
if i ask you
which one has more beans
you have more green beans or you have
more
red beans
then if you try to answer this question
there are many
or several ways you can
go uh you can do
you can answer my question
the easiest way is that or someone said
we can count the number of the beans
right
so you can
get all the beans out of like
let's say left ball
and then you count how many green beans
in the bowl
for example we have one two three four
five beans
okay
then you do the same thing to the
red beans in the right bowl so maybe you
get like
one two three four
six beans
then you tell me that
okay we have more
red beans than we have
green beans
right so that's one way to do
and you will find that
this thing
will only
i mean the procedure we just talked
about can only be applied to finite set
and of course
all possible finite sets can be compared
this way since they are finite you can
just count how many of them and you
compare the number
directly if you have like
one two three four five then you said
they we have same numbers of
green beans and red beans
right something like that
okay then
sadly such
a procedure cannot be carried over to
handle infinite sets okay
to handle infinite set
because
for infinite sets there is no
you know number
of elements
infinite is a
is an abstract concept regarding you
know
there is no
definite
or a constant for the measurement for
that the size of that set
so
you cannot say how many or you cannot
say okay i
uh there is a there is a finite uh
quantity
can be uh or uh the number of the
elements can be bounded by by
by some finite quantity
so that's infinite
and
we need to find a way
to
measure or to compare sizes of infinite
sets
then we
can go back to our finite sets and start
from there again
let's say back to my example here
another possible way to compare
the beans in the bowls are
let's imagine that
you uh
you use your
left hand
to
pick up one
green bean
and the one
and use your right hand
to pick up one red bean at the same time
and then you throw them away
okay
and you repeat this again so you pick up
another red bean
sorry green bean here and another red
bean here
at the same time and
throw them away
and then repeat that again
and repeat that again
okay
so you
keep you keep repeating this procedure
repeat and repeat and repeat and repeat
what will happen
as our example here for example here
then finally
you will have a you will have an empty
left ball but you have
one more
red bean in the rifle right
so we can say that
we have more red beans than we have
green beans
right
if
they have the same
the the numbers of the beans are the
same
then you won't have this one
you will
empty
them
at the same time
right you make them empty
the lesbian
you the lesbians
you throw them away at the same time and
you got two empty bowls at the same time
then you can say that we have
same numbers of red and green beans
so you will find okay this is another
way to compare the size of
currency finite set
but you will
such a procedure can be extend
can be extended to
compare the sizes of infinite set
okay
so
we define that
we
use
you can think of that
when we pick up
one
when we pick up one green bean
and one red bean
we do a mapping
we always use the mapping in mathematics
to
[Music]
theorize the concept of picking two
beans from the two balls at the same
time okay
so
we already have a mathematics
construction and everybody should
uh
should be quite familiar with that which
is function
okay
we think of left one
that our green beans
and
on the left and
our red beans on the right and we use a
function mapping
this domain
to
okay
so
the f here
is that
abstract mapping
okay
so every bin
in the level
we map two
pin
in the right uh
right ball
so this is fx
and every red bean sorry green bean
leftover we map to one
in a rival
and
since uh
and we define
one to one
function that means
different
green beans in the left wall
we map two
different beans in the right bowl
okay so that we call one two one
and actually we need reverse thing that
we need reverse one but
we don't uh
i should rephrase that
we actually need
both direction
because you use your both hand
pick up two beans one in left and one in
right together right so we need
both direction but
we don't need
this direction here because
functions the definition of functions
in mathematics already
already took care of that for us
because functions cannot map one
two
different
things right
this is not a function
when we talk
talk about the fun a function we have
only
something like this
or
something like this right
it's 1 to 1
is
many to 1
so that's in the definition of function
we don't have one too many
if you want to define something
conte uh include one too many that's
another function when we talk about a
function
we don't have this situation we only
have these two
and
now we need to implement what is
described as you use your both hands
to pick up
bins in both balls
so we want this one that's why we only
need to
[Music]
do the restriction like this then we can
ensure that
it's a one-to-one
function that that would that will
implement what i described
we pick two beans
throw them away together
okay
then
we need to
make
all bins
out
together
so
we say
the left hand ball is a and the rehabble
is b
for all b
in b
so for all red beans in the right
bowl
there is
a green bean mapped to that
for example this one map to this one and
the map one
this one map to that one
okay
so for all red beans
for all red beans
there is a green bean mapped to that
there's a green bean
map to that
we call it
angchu
and for uh for the same reason we also
need a reverse reverse situation that
o green beans
map 2 red beans right but
function the definition of function also
took care of that
okay
since our function is one green beam
mapped to a red bean
so
every green bean map to some red bean
right
every green beans
every grape in green been mapped to some
wrapping so we already have that inside
the definition of the function
so we only need to describe our
restrict
mega constraint here
to say that all red bean
have been mapped
each red bean has been mapped by
some green bean
right
so that's why
we said that all the red beans
can be mapped by
some green bean
and if you if the function
satisfy
these two satisfies these two
criteria at the same time
so different
green beans
mapped to different red bean
and all the red beans
each
well all the red beans
has been mapped have been mapped
we said that such a function
such a function
is a correspondence
which is one two one and on two
okay and we then we consider
a
the set the infinite set of actually
finite or infinite they both they both
work
the
set a and the set b
are of the same size
okay
so it's kind of a long definition but
that's repeated pretty pretty quickly
again
so if you have if we have two infinite
sets actually infinite or finite doesn't
matter
we can use the same
definition to handle both finite and
infinite sets okay so we have a two set
and b
if we can find a function
mapping
a to b mapping from a to b
and
the function
is one to one
that means
different elements in a
map to different
elements in b
and
onto
that means
all elements in b
have been mapped
then we call the function
one two one and r2
if such a function exists
then we say that
the size of a
and the size of b
are the same
and such a function
is called
correspondence between a and b
okay
so we can use
such a
concept to compare the size of
of course either finite or infinite sets
okay
so let's define one more thing
we say that
a set a
is countable
okay we say that a is countable
if either it is finite
because for finance that you can
actually
what is count
counter is like you uh
name
each element with a unique number like
one the first one two the second one
three the third one four the fourth one
etc etc
so you can name each
element one two three four five
you can count you can count
the elements in a set
so a set is countable means you can
count elements
don't think about all sets are countable
okay there are
sets that
that is not countable okay anyway we
will prove that but
firstly
if uh
if a set is finite reset it is countable
or
for infinite sets the set has same size
as the natural numbers we also say
it is countable why because
since they are
since the set has same size as n that
means there is a one to one and on two
mapping from n to that set
then you just need to count from the
the element mapped with
one
you count it as first and the elements
uh mapped by two you count it as second
etc then you can count the whole set
right so why it is countable although it
is infinite we consider
this kind of infinite state countable
okay
so
let's have some example here
so the first example is that
we want to prove that
even
natural numbers
okay that is
2 4 6 8 10 12 14 etc
we want to prove
even numbers even natural numbers
has the same size as natural numbers
which is you know
one two three four five six seven
etc
well it's kind of uh counterintuitive
because
the intuition
may just tell us that even numbers even
natural numbers are fewer
actually half
of the natural numbers how can we say
that they have the same size
right that's weird but according to our
definition
according to our definition
we have to accept that they are of the
same size because
that's the only way
we can extend
the comparison of size of sets from
finances to
infinite set well well i shouldn't say
the only way but that's the way we adopt
it adopt right now
okay maybe there are other ways
actually but we are using that
uh
using the
you
we are using that way
right now
so
to prove
natural numbers and the even natural
numbers are of
the same
have the same size we need to find the
correspondence which is the one to one
and onto function between the two sets
right
so the function is easy we map each
we map each natural number to
itself times two
right so that's what we said here
and map2n
in this way
two
map to four
three map26 etc right
and you will find that it is a one to
one because
x when x and y are different
we have
different
red beans right we have different green
beans we have different red beans
so that's one to one
and of course all
all natural all even natural numbers
are mapped for every
natural numbers
you know there is some
thing
some natural numbers actually which is
half of the
number right
in
n
such that f of x
is
y so
the course the function here is one to
one and on two so we call it
correspondence
and
we conclude that
the set of natural numbers
and the set of even
even natural numbers are
of the same size
according to our definition
okay that's the first
example here
and let's
take a look at another example that we
want to
prove that
nature numbers and
rational numbers
okay what is the rational numbers if for
simplicity that's considered only
positive
or
we
consider only
for for rational numbers it can be
written as
two integers uh
divided by let's say m divided by n
right that's the definition of rational
numbers
and for simplicity we current we we now
uh consider only m in n and n in also in
n
okay we don't consider all possible uh
including negative integers let's
consider only
rational rational numbers as
in this form
okay
then
if we find if we can find a one-to-one
and the n2
function between n and q which is
rational numbers then we prove that they
are of the same size they have the same
size
even
intuitively
you know we think
rational numbers should be more uh be
more that the num uh
there should be more rational numbers
than
natural numbers right because two
natural numbers composite one
rational numbers there should be more
rational numbers
but
we can easily find
a correspondence how do we do that
we think of you know
two uh
x's here so this one is n this one is m
okay they are integer so
you can easily find that all rational
numbers let's say uh in this form
will be in the plan
spent by n
axis and the n axis
right
then we can say that
the first uh we can start to count all
rational numbers as the first one
right then we count
second one
we count third one
then go back to count
fourth one
and we can skip the one we already count
right and five
number five
number six number seven number eight
number nine
and then ten
and
etc
so
it is possible that
we have a not possible we
provide the possibility of the
correspondence between
n and q
okay
so that's why we have to admit that
according to the definition according to
the judge
criteria here
we have to admit that
n and q
have the same size
okay have the same size
so that's
another
counterintuitive conclusions
here
[Applause]
okay so
that's
is there any
set
uh uncountable
larger
than
natural numbers
of course there are
and let's see the
theorem here
we want to prove that the set of
the set of real numbers
is uncountable
that means
there exists
no correspondence
between n and r
natural numbers and
real numbers
okay as we already uh use the argument
many times that
we
we are unable to find the correspondence
doesn't mean
others cannot do this
uh find the correspondence right maybe
they are smarter they can really find
the correspondence so we have we need to
have some arguments which is absolutely
convincing
to prove
it's not possible
okay
so we use the same technique again let's
say
we assume that
we assume not
r is countable
okay
let's assume it
what means by r uh is countable what
means by
real numbers the set of real numbers is
countable
that means
there exists
a one two one and on two functions
between
natural numbers and real numbers right
there exists a correspondence
okay so
let's assume the correspondence look
like this way no the first
real numbers this is one
the second real number is this one the
third real number is this one the fourth
real number is this one etc right
etc there there and and most importantly
firstly they are one to one right
one two one
and secondly
on two so that's all
real numbers
right that's all real numbers no
no one real number is uh
outside of this uh
table
however
someone look at the table and
say that
let me put the integer part 0
okay
and
let's take the first
in the first digit of the first real
number
and change it for example that's changed
to four
and let me take the second digit of the
second real number
and change it for example six
okay
and take the third
digit of the third
real number and change it
four
and then fourth
digit of the fourth
real number for example change to one
and we keep doing this so
the fifth number and of the fifth real
number uh fifth digit of the fifth real
number and change to something else
not zero okay
i shouldn't use it
change to something else
and also this one let's do it again
and this one let's do it again
and
etcetera
right
then you will find something
weird
we have a contradiction here
what what contradiction
you can see
this number
is definitely a real
number right this number is definitely a
real number
but
let's say x
but x here
is not
in
the table
why
because you will find that the x here
has at least a one digit difference
between all the members on the table all
the real numbers on the table
x is
not
x is not the first one
first real number because the first
digit is different
x is not the second real number on the
table because the second digit
is different at least the second digit
is different
and it is not
i
element on the table because
at least five digit is different
so
you tell me that or someone tell you
that
the table contains
all the real numbers
while you can find one real number out
of the table but not in the table
so apparently it's a contradiction
that's why r cannot be countable
because
as long as anyone couldn't r is
countable
that correspondence
it's wrong
okay another chorus that correspondence
must be wrong there exists no
correspondence
for real numbers to be
the same size as natural number
okay
so
you will find that what we are doing is
finding the first
using the first digit of the first
element first real number and the second
of the second third of the third
fourth of the first etc
so that's a diagonal
and we do a diagonalization here
that's why
we
say that it is
the diagonalization method because we
you we are using the property of
diagonalization
or like that diagonal
okay
of course they are for this proof there
are some
rules about how to change the digit
one two four five two six there are some
other rules you can
refer to the textbook but
concepts are the same that
we can always
going through a diagonal
and come up with some elements which is
not on the table
and therefore to prove that this kind of
table such a table cannot be
written down cannot exist
okay
so that's uh
the proof for theorem 4.17 r is
uncountable
okay
then
we can use the same
technique
to prove that
there are languages
that are not even turian recognizable
okay
some languages are not too recognizable
we want to prove that
how do we prove it
let's consider alphabets
zero one and don't forget that zero one
here are just two symbols not integer
zero and one okay
you can come you can also uh think
consider a b
instead of 0 1 maybe it's easier for you
but
doesn't matter
as long as you have an alphabet
you can enumerate all possible strings
right so
then zero empty string length one zero
one length two zero zero zero one one
zero one one
then three
there are eight of them right and then
four five
six seven and etc etc you can
enumerate them
and what is the language
what is the language on the alphabet
a set of strings
right
so any language is a
possible subset of sigma star
let's say
we have a language
the string of the language is 0 0 0 0 1
0 0 0 0 1 etc right
and then we use
we use
a spatial
that's the vector or
zero one string to
represent that
language okay
how do we use a
0 1 or binary string to represent the
language
it's pretty easy that
if the language a
has no
epsilon
we write 0 here
now you see that the 0 here is not the
alphabet 0 not the symbol 0. the 0 here
means
language a has no epsilon has no empty
string okay
then language a has zero so we have one
here
no one
zero here
zero zero
one here zero one yes so one here there
is no one zero in a zero here there's no
uh one one a zero here there is zero
zero zero here in a so one here
one here etc
okay
then you can find that
all possible
subset of sigma star
we can use
such a string
to represent
the language
right
then we prove that
the number of languages
are uncountable
how do we prove that
firstly we assume that
languages
are countable
then you can have a table like
then you can you can have a table like
the first language the second language
the third language the fourth language
etc right
and then
for the first language
that would be 0 0 1 1 0 1 etc etc right
and for the second one maybe it's like
etc and then for the third language you
have also a one
zero one string representation for the
first one
maybe like this
and remember that since we are assuming
all languages are countable
accountable so
that
all the languages are here
then using
diagonalization method
we can have one language
if you encounter zero you make it one if
your counter is one then make it zero
and you do this one for example 1 1 1 0
etc
and you will find
this language
is not
in
the left-hand side of the table
right it's not on the table
so
that means such a correspondence doesn't
exist
so
all possible languages are
infinitely
actually uncountably infinite
yes
they cannot be countable so their
size
is larger than the size of natural
numbers
okay
but we know that
for turing machine
tuning machines are apparently countable
why
because turning machine
has an encoding
as a strings
right
if you think of all the programs you
write your programs are
you know encodings of some file
so there must be encodings for tuning
machines
and as long as you fix
the alphabet
all strings
that can be generated by that alphabet
is countable
you count from length one sorry length
zero then one length two then three
right
so
the number of languages are
much actually much larger than the
number of two machines
so we know that
there must be some languages
are not touring recognizable even you
consider all possible turing machines
there are more language than that
right so even each turing machine if you
consider each string as a turing machine
and
recognize some language even recognize
different language sorry
even each
individual string as a tuning machine
mapped to an unique language the number
of languages
is still much larger
so there are some languages that are not
too recognizable
okay
so
we've proved that
by using
size
to prove serum 4.18
that some languages are not purely
recognizable
because the numbers of languages
the number of languages is much larger
than the number of possible turing
machines
okay
so that means
there are
something out there
okay there are something
but you know slightly different than
what we've previously done
we have an extent instance here we have
an instance here we have an instance
here right
but now we know that okay there are
something out there but
can you give me an example
yes we do so let's
have an example here that we want to
prove
we want to prove
an
example of
touring unrecognizable language
so firstly let's define
a language is code to unrecognizable
if the language is
if uh it is the complement
of a
turin recognizable language
okay
so let's say
if there is a language a
then we said
a is called recognizable
that means
a bar is too recognizable
because a is the complement of a bar and
the a bar is too recognizable in this
case we say
a
is too recognizable
actually you will see code
something
in many definitions that means
if a
is co x
that means a
is a complement of
some instance of x
so in this case
x is too recognizable so when we say
language a is called recognizable that
means
a bar is too recognizable
and a is the complement of a bar so we
call
a is code to recognizable
so
have a have this definition for
uh
first to describe theorem 4.22 easier
that
let's say a language is decidable
if and only if okay if and only
the language is tuned recognizable and
culturally recognizable
okay
so
let's prove the theorem first let's
prove the theorem first
if
a language a
is too recognizable
if language a is too recognizable
then
and
sorry
[Applause]
if language a is decidable
then
there is a turing machine m
as a decider
right
and the two machine
m
since it is a decider so it is the
recognizer so firstly a is to
recognizable right
and since m is a decider
you just need to switch the
accept state
and reject state
you make the decider for a bar
right
so
the decider n prime for a bar
is the recognizer
of
the complement of a
so since a is also
since a bar is a recognizable a is
called recognizable
so we prove this direction
if a language is designable that's
decider
you can directly use it as recognizer
and you with
a small modification you can use it as
the recognizer of its complement
so if the language's complement is
recognizable that language is called
recognizable
okay
and
for the reverse direction if a language
is too recognizable
then you will have a machine as its
recognizer
and
code to recognizable that means
the complement of that language
is recognizable so you have a recognizer
for
the complement right
and then
we can use
these two
turing machine
because
the two language here is all possible
strings right
then we can use the two tuning machine
to make the decider for a
how do we do that we can do that this
way
we construct m on all possible strings
we run
m1 and m2 which is m a and m a bar as i
have on the
slide
in parallel
but what that means by in parallel
you cannot do it like
you put w in a to see the answer then
in
m a bar to see the answer you cannot do
that because one of them may not give
you an answer because they are only
recognizer
so you do that in parallel by parallel
means we do that alternatively
so we
simulate m a and the n a prime
together but by together that we have a
machine
run one step of ma simulate one step and
the simulate one step and simulate one
step simulate one state
so
every machine goes one step goes one
step something like that then eventually
one of them will
accept the string
right
if m a or m one accepts you know that
w is in a
then this machine accepts
if m2 which is a bar here accepts that
means w is in a bar
so we
reject
and as i said
a the union of a a buys all possible
strings so eventually
one of the process will stop and give
you accept
then we can construct our recognizer
sorry decider for a this way
okay
so after
we have this we can
have a
we can have a
concrete example
outside to recognizable okay that would
be
atm bar
okay atm bar
why
because we know that atm
is
turin recognizable
we already proved that right
so if atm bar
is to recognizable 2
then atm would be decidable according to
jiren 4.22 right
so
atm bar
must be
during unrecognizable or let's say must
not be
turin recognizable
according to
theorem
4.22
okay
so now we have a concrete example
outside of recognizable that
atm bar
because we already proved atn as
recognizable but undecidable so atm bar
must
not be
recognizable
okay
okay we can have another concrete
example here that's defined that
we
we enumerate all zero one string this
way okay let's just construct another
language here
so let's say if we have alphabet
zero
we have alphabet zero one
so
we make the first one
we enumerate all possible strings and
the first one is empty
empty string the second one is zero
third one is one etc
then you will find an interesting
uh
interesting
relationship here that the ninth string
is
one
zero zero
one which is nine
okay
so
like this one the six strings
you put one
in front of
the string here one one zero that will
be 6.
so you can
directly like
written down all possible for example
this one
you can have the binary
representation
here
and
put one here
oh sorry and remove the first one then
you know that binary string okay it's
very easy to
have that
so
we can say that
that's defined
let's define a language you like we
consider every binance binary string a
turing machine
of course some of them are evaluating
machine so we consider that kind of
invalid turing machine accepts no
strings okay
but main but there will be some binary
strings representing valid turing
machines legal tuning machines
so we define that there's a language ld
for those wi
considered as
turing string turing machine
does not accept
the
itself as input
if wi as a tune machine does not accept
itself as to as input
we say that
the language is in the string is in this
language
a string is in this language
by defining
ld this way we can prove the theorem
that
there is no tier machine
accepts this particular language
but except here is recognized
okay
there is no transmission recognize ld
why
because you can simply
have a diagonalization method to prove
it
like
each binary string considered as a
machine and compared to
its own as input
if let's say machine one accept
string one
we have one here otherwise we have zero
here
then imagine that we have zero one as
zero not except
one except
here
then collect
the diagonal
diagonal here
and
put 0 into ld that's the definition of
rld so in this case rld would have
w1 because 0 here
and no w2 no w3 w4 because 0 here
and
etc
and you will easily
conclude that there is no machine
there's no machine
recognize this language why
because for this language
you can find
there uh let's say if you say that
the i
the ice machine let's say this one
the ice machine
recognize this language
i would say you are wrong why
because you just need to
check the i
string here
if this machine
wi
accepts
then wi will not in the language
so it's not
recognized by the by the ice machine
on the other hand
if
the if machine
does not accept wi then wi will be in ld
again so if machine
does not recognize aod
so
by define lt
this way
we define a language
recognized by
no turing machines
so
led is not too recognizable
so in this way
we have two examples
outside of
two recognizable one is what a t
m bar
and the other one is ld
okay
so now we have two concrete example
outside of two recognizable