last time we
introduced the formal definition
of context-free grammars and
we defined that
the language generated by
context requirements are context-free
languages okay so that's the title of
chapter two and
why it is called text
context free context-free grammar
context free language
okay the reason to code the grammar the
language
context free is that
for the rule to derive
strings terminal strings and the mixture
of terminal and the variable strings
you can see that
as long as you have a rule like this
let's say variable a may become
a string w
whenever you see a here in a mixture of
variables and
terminals you can you can
make a w
okay and as
you can see like in natural language
or article you know newspaper something
like that
u a v here
what is u and what is v that's your
context
you know imagine that you are having a
chat with your classmates or friends
and you use pronouns like you
me okay me and i may be
clear but they he
she pronounced like that
how do you know who is he
or who is she in your conversation
if you just heard
a sentence like uh
she is going there something like that
and you won't be able to know
what is that so
in our most
most of our conversations or articles
anything in natural language
they are bounded in
the particular context
so for that example you
here according to you here you know
or you know what a can become
or what a have to become
okay so this kind of expansion rule
the derivation rule we will call it
context sensitive
all right so like in the conversation
after you know that
some particular person is the
she or is the he then
you know late in the later part of the
conversation
she refers to that particular person
so for context sensitive language
or counter-sensitive grammars you can
specify
something like this whenever you see
uav then in that case
you can
make a w
okay only in this case not in other
cases
so that's called context sensitive and
it on the con in contrast to context
sensitive
what we have here is that
no matter your context is
no matter what the context is
a always can be
w according to our rule here
that's why the language we are talking
about
is called context free language and
the grammar is called context-free
grammar
because the variable in the grammar
can freely
yield the string which is the body
specified by the rules
okay as long as you have a rule like
b become a
c b b a something like this
and in any situation for example
you have a b b
c c a then you
no matter the context
you can change b to the string
that is context free okay
so
it's the it's the reason why we call it
context free
and the rule
here w here
can be any
string in
the mixture of
variables and terminals right
which is called body here
and according to the definition here we
can know that
the rule of a grammar can be you know
quite
arbitrary you can write any string as
you like
as long as it follows the spec
the formal definition of the grammar
that is a
valid context free grammar
well you can have a rule like s become
a a c c b s s
b b c a something
and then you can also have x become
epsilon
right so as you can imagine
there can be many kinds of you know
rules
as long as you follow the specs
but if we want to discuss
some property characteristics
of context grammar context-free grammars
or context-free languages
we will we will need something more
simple something more uh
easy to do operations okay
so that's why we are introducing
normal form
what is a normal form
you can think of it that way a normal
phone is
some way to you have some way
to write all
the grammars or
uh all context requirements can be
written
in some particular way and we call that
way
a normal form okay normal that
like everybody's that something like
that and
uh there are several kinds of normal
phones for context-free
grammars like bnf or g something
and the normal phone we want to
introduce here
is called chomsky nomophong and chong
chomsky is a famous american
linguist i guess he's older than
90 years old now anyway so we say
a context free grammar is in
chomsky normal form
if every rule
in that grammar is one
of the following form first form is
you have one variable may become two
variables
two variables or you have one variable
that variable
can become a terminal
okay so
basically uh that's it
you see if all your
rules in the grammar either
one variable becomes two variables or
one variable become may become a
terminal
and of course there they there are
and uh restriction that
the variables on the right hand side
or let's say in the body of the rule
cannot be variable
okay cannot be startable and
also and
also an exception
that star variable can become
empty string okay
so we call it chomsky normal phone okay
let me
uh say that again
a free a context-free grammar is in
chongqing normal form
if every rule is one of the form
first a variable becomes
may become two variables or a variable
may become a terminal okay
then the variable on the right hand side
cannot be start variable
okay then if you think of it
you see from start variable
either it becomes a terminal
or it becomes two variables
and cannot be storable okay and
anyway there cannot be absolute
right if your grammar
has only these kinds of rules it is
it is impossible from start variable
derives an empty string
all right so that creates a problem that
if the language you want to describe
has empty string then we will have a
problem here
right so let us
think of that way if you have
if you have a language
which can be described by some
context-free grammar
so the language is context-free language
right
and we can convert that grammar
into okay the language you have
can be described by some context free
grammar
and then we can convert this grammar
into a grammar in
chongqing normal phone but chong's
normal form cannot let's say
in this case there are two ways to
handle it
there are two ways to handle it one way
is that you convert
choose chunks normal phone
and you allow that if the original
language
has epson
has epson is in the original language
you allow that the grammar you converted
is actually the original
sorry i shouldn't write it this way
grammar you converted the language of
the
grammar in chongqing nomophong is the
original language
without episode
okay that's one way to handle it if
the language if the grammar you convert
it from a language and
that's grammar sorry that language has
empty string then you are willing to
allow
the converted grammar in chomsky normal
phone
describe generate a language
equal to the original language without
empty string so that's one possible way
to handle it
the other possible way to handle it is
the one we used
here we allow
exception in the form of rule
so we allow
star variable directly become
may become empty string in this way
we can have a chongxin aguama in chongxi
novo phong
exactly describe
the original language generate
the original language okay let me
say that again if you have a context
free language
and if that language has
no empty string then there is no problem
at all
if that language has empty string
then there are two ways to handle it
in some textbook they they don't allow
exception in rules but they
allow exception that the converted
grammar the language described generated
by the converted grammar
has no empty string
so the resultant language and the
original language
are you know different by one
empty string that's one way to handle
this
and the other way is what we adopted
here
we allow exceptions
in the form of rules we allow that
we allow that start variable
may become empty string directly so
we can have an totally equivalent
language okay so
again what is chongxi nomophong chomping
in our textbook is that the rule in your
grammar
are either one rule one variable may
become two variables or one variable
may become one terminal
okay and right hand side cannot have
the variable and you may have
this kind of rule for you know the
exception
empty string okay then what what do we
want
okay first since it is a normal asset
set
all possible context with grammars
can be returned into this kind of form
okay that's why it is called normal
phone of course there are slightly
uh issues regarding empty string but
you know that that can be handled
and why do we want a normal phone like
this because
it it will be much easier to discuss
the derivation the positivity
the property of those quantities
okay you see since you have
one variable may become two variable so
on the past three
you may have something like
a variable becomes two variable
right and then a variable becomes two
variable
and then variable becomes like terminal
c you will see that
the terminal string the number of
terminals
in the length of terminal string
is exactly
if you uh consider the last
variable
the number of the last the leaf let's
say
leave leave leaf
variables are exactly the same as the
the length of the terminal string
okay that's first and the second you
know that
these three is a binary tree
right because it always one node
has two node as child always
a binary tree then
since it is the positivity must be a
binary tree then
you can have all the theorems proven on
binary trees
for in your arsenal right you can use
any theorem to describe the derivation
process the size of the posterior or
things like that
and also the length of the terminal
string
and bounded the height
of the pastry
so that'll be easier for discussion
okay so chongqing normal form and we
will use that
later so let's say
we present now we present a process
to convert any grammar into
chongqing normal form okay and the
process is pretty easy actually easier
than you know
nfa to dfa in my personal
viewpoint okay there are only four
steps and as long as you remember
what chomsky normal phone is
you will remember the four steps because
they are course
they are corresponding to each other
okay
so the first step is add a new start
variable
okay when you have a context free
grammar
don't don't forget that a context free
is what variables
terminals rules and star variable
right and since you want to convert the
form of the given grammar
into chongqing normal form
there is nothing to do with the
terminals because you don't need to
change
anything right and start variable you
don't need to change
anything and you know that you want to
change
rules and you want to make rules
the start variable not showing
in the right hand side and you don't
know
the given grammar
you don't know the rules in a given
grammar so the
first thing to do is you add
a new start variable then that will not
that new star variable will not show in
the
right hand side of the rules right
because the rules are given
so first step is to add a new star
variable
second step because we only permit
start variable to become epsilon
empty string so we want to eliminate
o at epsom rules
like this one in the original rule set
okay then
we only allow one variable to become two
variable
so
we eliminate all unit rules
in the original grammar okay after that
you can you can
think about it after that you will have
the grammar have something like a
variable become terminal
and variable becomes some
two or three or
four
the length of two or three or four the
bodies
the length of the bodies are like this
then
we make them
chunks okay so that's the example and
you will know the four steps are
pretty straightforward
so assuming that the grammar is from the
textbook
so assuming that
we have a grammar g6 we want to convert
to chongqing normal phone
and here we only have the rules but you
formally you need to describe that okay
i have a grammar g6
for table right now b s
a b uh
okay as our variables and terminal
is a and b right yes
and then rules are you know the six
rules
one two three four
five six rules here
and then usually we use s as star
variable
so that's the formal definition of g6
now we want to convert g6 into chomsky
normal form
so first step what is first step add a
new
start variable so we add a new start
variable called
s0 and s0 is the star variable
and if we want to add a new star
variable and without changing the
language generated by the grammar
what should we do we should add one rule
like this
right and only one rule
and according to the derivation of
context-free grammar you know that
see what is the language of g6
6 l of g6
is all possible string
in terminal
which can be derived
from s
right that's our definition then
we add as 0 here as our new variable
we just need to add these
rule then we have what is the
what is the language of this
new grammar the language of this new
grammar
let's say is
by definition all string
all possible string determine all
possible terminal string
which can be derived from s0
right and you know
there is only one way for s 0 to become
something
so s 0 b always become
s and become w
see so that's the original language
of g6 right
okay so we will have this all the way
through
every step we do is actually
can make the grammar connect the
modified or converted grammar
generates exactly what the original
grammar
generate so the context free language
is not changed we only
change the rules
to make them in chongqing number four
okay if you have no problem here
then you know that adding
a new star variable so that's you see
the star variable original star variable
on the right hand
side doesn't matter anymore and we add
this rule here
so the language is not changed
okay then next step
we want to eliminate what epsilon rules
like this one okay so how do we
eliminate absent rules without
changing all the strings possibly
generated
by the original grammar well
it's kind of simple
and some someone may think them tricky
but actually it's not
you think of think of the rule here
you know you have a rule b may become
empty string so
whenever you have a string like a
b a c c or
no c here sorry a b a a
b something like this and the b
may eventually become m strong or
may become b right that means
this string may become
a b a a
b or
a nothing right empty string
a a b
right so there will be
two possibility for
b here
right and one will you have b
the capital b always
generated by
other rules right hand side
right you start from the start variable
and when
you get capital b and you know later
that capital b may become epsilon
if we do that if we do
that a step
a derivation step before
b we can keep
we can maintain all possibilities
so for this example here right
so this example here
assume that the b is generated by
a b or a b
a or something anyway so
when a b is generated
we make it to version
we change the process here
make the possibility here
one step
ahead okay so
when some string make a b
a a b we make it make
two possibilities a b
a a b and
a a a
b then this will be only
a b a a b
okay how do we do that
we examine the right hand side with b
with capital b and we make
a b and other version without
b which is empty string a
also like this one we make a two version
and epsilon okay
so in this way we can make the
derivation step
one step uh another head actually before
that step
okay so you you move the derivation
steps
then as long as we leave all
possibilities
we can eliminate eliminate this rule
so it's like we eliminate
b become epsilon
then for this one we have two version
one is a capital b but capital b
here will be small b
and no epsilon anymore but the
capital b the version for capital b to
become
epsilon we kept recap we keep the
possibility here okay so for the send
for the same idea we
make it we make the capital b here two
version
first version capital b itself but this
version now cannot be empty string
anymore
and also we make it empty string the
possibility
we need to keep okay
after that we remove
b may become epsom the rule here
then we check again we find that okay
actually we create another epsilon
rule then we keep removing it
so we want to remove this one
in order to remove a may become epsilon
we need to consider all the capital a
on the right hand side in the body body
strings
so we have asa here
okay then since there are two a
here we need to make four versions
the first one is a
s a right but the asa
is not the asa anymore because the asa
the two a's cannot be apt cannot be
empty string anymore but we need to
keep the possibility so we add
s a that means the first a becomes
empty string and a s
the second a becomes empty string and
s both a become empty strings
so we add three new possibilities here
okay i i think this
this case is easier to understand right
because
x may become a s a
and originally that a that both a
may become empty string
since we want to eliminate a may become
empty string but we still need
all the strings
which can be derived in the original
grammar
we make the possibility here so
we directly eliminate a right so
asa s a a s
and s so all possibilities
are kept right in this case
we can eliminate a may become epsilon
now
so let's check again
after this step there is no epsilon rule
anymore
and here comes the interesting part that
if if the language
generated by the original grammar really
has
empty string as the terminal string
for this example here obviously we know
that
g6 l of g6 doesn't have
empty string as its member okay
if the original
grammar the language described generated
by the original grammar has the empty
string
then eventually you will have
s0 or s may become
empty string see you will finally
convert your conversion
into this row and this is allowed
so we also will stop the process and we
also know that
the original language will uh does have
empty string
okay but in this case we don't have we
don't we don't have empty string so we
don't need
that exception here
then after the absolute
rules we want to remove units rules that
is
one variable become may become one
variable
and also the the same idea
is as we do the
epsilon rules removing
if we want to remove unit rules okay so
one unit rules is pretty easy that s
become
s there is nothing to do to remove
s become may become s right because
nothing
happened you have one more derivation
step
but no uh no change
will be cost
by remove just removing this one because
s is
s right so that's the easy part
then we want to we want to
move remove other unit rules
then we also the
idea is like removing epsilon
rules we want to keep all possibilities
so
s may become s if we want to remove this
row
how do we do that
it's pretty easy that we remove s here
with that with that as the row
may become anything
that s may become so we copy everything
here
so
we get sorry
we get this one just the
you know copy and paste see that's
pretty straightforward right
you just let s neuro become anything
else can become
then you can remove s0 becomes s
right and also generate exactly the same
set of terminal strings
so follow the same thing
we want to remove a become b we just
copy what b make become
and remove here and a may become
s we copy everything
as here right
okay then done right
step three is done so after step three
what do we have
we have a grammar
that is close to the chongqing nomophong
and what grammar is that that would be
a variable either generate a terminal
like this
or this
or generate
two things
or three things or longer okay so one
terminal one terminal
then it's pretty straightforward that
you just need
everything
longer than one becomes all
variables and then split it
okay so
we uh introduce a new variable
become a
in general you you you you will need to
have
a new variable like you
become a b become b
and so on you
give each terminal a variable
and then replace all terminals
in rules
longer than one
two or three or longer you
change all the terminals in that rows
as variables okay so in this case
the the author only adds u becomes a
and you change all a's
in the rule right so change this one
change this one and this one
and then you make all
rules longer than two
more rules okay so in this case
a s a
s may become asa you make
the two variable one new variable
s a and rewrite this as a one
so that's what we have here
and in general you can do something like
this
you have a become a
whatever b c d
e f okay then
you make this for another variable
so g become
c and you want you you want to have
d e f another variable
d then
i become e f
and you fill it back i h
right and then this part will be
what g so a become
b g and then you can
remove these rules become the four rules
here
see a become b g and g becomes c h
h becomes the i i become ef so
a will become abcdef
well you use the number of rules
to replace the length of
of a body of a body of a rule right in
general you can do that
anyway and you don't need to care about
the you know finite set thing because
the rule here
the body length here is finite
then you convert to number of rules
which is finite
so no problem with it with that okay
so we can convert any
grammar into normal phone
and it is one example
again some uh i remember that someone
asked me
can we okay in that case a become
b c d e
can we make this one a variable this one
a variable
for example uh f g so
a can become f g and f
can become b c and the g can become
d e yes you can but
uh you then you need to write
some more clever way to handle
long bodies right there's no
rules against that you can you know
use your imagination to do all possible
operation
to minimize the rule the number of rules
but in mathematics
usually optimization on
these not important part
is not that important because what we
care
what mathematicians care is
the existence is the possibility
that a grammar can be converted
to chomsky normal form
if the answer is yes then okay it's yes
we don't really care about you know uh
making rules or variables
as few as possible
that's not you can do that but that's
not the thing
we care about in this course or in the
field
of uh in a related field
okay so of course you can do that that
and we only want to provide us
a safest way to do
it okay maybe stupid but it
always works so that's why i said
for a very long body you kept the first
one
and you make then
another rule and you
have the first one here and make the
rest
another rule and finally you will get
the last two
here so maybe last two here
then you have the you have the grammar
in chongqing normal phone okay
anyway so we
now know that uh there are
at least there is a chomsky normal phone
for context pre-grammar
and all possible chomsky all possible
context-free grammar can be converted
into chongxin normal phone
only that if your original
context-free language has empty string
then there will be there
will there may be an exception for that
otherwise everything is almost identical
okay all non-empty strings
are kept and there is no
more uh no other non
empty string can be generated
okay so that's the uh
conversion for
context-free grammars into chongusky
normal phone