the reason why we use our turing machine
as computational models and the turing
machines are popular for discussing
computation
it's because
two machines are closer to what we have
for modern computers
if you consider uh underlying
architecture and uh
like uh
organize a computer organization two
machine is pretty uh similar or close to
what we have right now
and the other important reason is that
uh
many
variants of turing machines are
basically equivalent to each other
for example if we have a
dfa
and
to be
if we add
non-deterministic
capability to dfa
then
final automata becomes non-deterministic
final automata which is nfa and we prove
that nfn dfa i-current right
but for pda pda is
uh intrinsically non-deterministic if we
if we make pda deterministic that will
become dpda which we skipped as uh
section 2.4 in the textbook right
and you can if you are interested you
can go back to
check
chapter 4 uh chapter 2 section 2.4
and you will know that
there is the gap
of computational capability between
pda and the dpda they are different they
are not equivalent
and
as
nfa
if you add a stack that will become pda
right and we know that
nfa can recognize
regular languages but pda can recognize
context-free languages there is also a
gap between
the two type of machines and which
are different
which are different in
having a stack or not so variant
variance between computational models
may create
a
difference in
the
capability of computation or
computational limitations
but
for turing machines
variants
many variants many uh
we can prove that they are equivalent so
it will it creates convenience for us to
discussing computation
because uh no matter we as long as we
prove that
uh
we proved the equivalence between
variants
then we can use whatever we have
to prove
what we want to prove okay so that's uh
the other important reason
to uh
accept turing machines as
computational models
so
here we will introduce some variants of
turing machines and the proof
that they are equivalent
so the first one is a k-type multi-type
tube machine as i introduced previously
some textbook cheat
uh
like three tape to machine
as the fundamental one in their textbook
yeah in their book
so uh basically multi-tab turing machine
multiple turing machines are
that you have k tabs okay k k tips
so
the k
here is a finite number like two or
three actually one is the same machine
basically
okay and two or three or a very large
number like a median
but k is not infinite as long as k
is finite
then
we have a k type 2 machine
and since you have k tab you we we need
to slightly modify the definition of a
transition function as
there is a current state of the turing
machine and then
the k symbols you you will
read on the k tab
like
something like this if you have two tape
uh for type one you may be reading this
one and for tab two
you may be reading this one something
like that okay then according to
your uh your state
and
for example
for type one you read a for type two you
read b
stuff like that
and
give
the transition to the other states you
want to transition to and
rewrite or keep the sand on the k tab
and for each tape the head can go left
right or or stay
or stay
in the
center uh position the same location of
the tape
so
for this example you may have uh transit
to p
and you change this symbol to c
and
keep the same symbol the same sorry we
have one more thing here
and then you go for example
go
right
and
stay
at that position something like this
okay so that's a k-type turing machine
and we want to prove that
um
k-type turing machine case final number
k-type turing machine is it
is
equivalent to
our
fundamental to machine okay that's one
tab and
you have a left hand end
okay
of course for this k-type tube machine
we also have left and left-hand end for
each tape
though the right hand side is infinite
then if you want to prove the
equivalence we want to we need to prove
two directions okay
so our fundamental two machine
every
language
or every computation can be done by our
fundamental machine can be done
by
k-tap tube machine
and also k-type 2 machine
anything k type 2 machine
can do can be done by our
two machine fundamental type
but for this
for this
if and only if and only if relationship
we only need to
uh let's say
anything our two machine can
do can be done by
a category machine is trivial
why because
basically
our fundamental turing machine is a
special case of k type 2 machine with
basically k equals 1 right so we don't
prove this direction because that's
trivial
that like
just like dfa is a special case of an
ave
right so
we want to prove the other
direction which really need to be proven
okay so we have a theorem here
every multi-type 2 machine has
an equivalent single tap turing machine
okay by single type 2 machine we mean
the fundamental one we defined
previously
so how to prove the theorem here
the idea here is that
the first the first thing you might
think is that okay i have a single tap
turning machine
like this
we have a left hand end and
hand side infinite right
now
you have
a k type 2 machine
okay type 2 machine
how do you
simulate
the k type 2 machine in
a single tattoo machine that's the first
thing we want to
think about right
but
think about it there is no problem the
first thing you might think is the
size of the storage of all the memory
but don't forget that we have infinite
tape
so k infinite tape and the one infinite
table basically is the same
okay
you can think about
integer okay integer
and odd number
and even number
okay
so
let's mark
the tape like
the first the first
space second
third fourth fifth sixth etcetera
and the thing about you have two tape
crack
two tape
and you can store
you uh you can
store
one three five seven nine etc and the
two four six eight ten etc
right so
in this way
one
single
tape infinite tape can
actually store
k
infinite tape
okay
the relation we want to use is slightly
different than this one but
this uh the the relationship we
introduced here give you some thought to
understand how the whole thing works
okay so
the idea is that
we have a multi-tab tool machine
for this example k equals three right
and then we have a single type 2 machine
here
we want to simulate
k-type 2 machine with our single tap
tube machine
okay and how to do that
firstly
imagine that
initial when you want to put a
multi-temperature machine initially the
input is
stored on the first tape
okay and initially all other k minus one
tape are
empty
so
we can put
we can design a single tab turing
machine we can design a simple single
tab two machine with a special character
as separator to separate
different tape
of the machine you want to simulate
and then initially we put w here
and separate
and then
initially the second tab is empty right
let's say let's do this the second tab
is empty and the third tab is empty
okay and of course infinite blank
on the right hand side
then
we
design
two versions
two versions of each
type alphabet
the uh
two version is weird anyway we will make
duplicate
tape alphabet of each tape
and then
use that on our
single tape
for example here for the first tape the
alphabet may be 0 and 1 right
then we duplicate and
we make it 0 1 low
dot
okay
well you can use other symbols as you
know 0.1 dot it doesn't matter
but it just
it just
it they are just symbols that we want to
use as
0 is same as 0
1 as same as one but that means
that that
the head of that tape is at this
location
okay just want to carry more information
with the symbol
so the same thing goes to for example
the second the type alphabet for the
second and the third table is
let's say a and b and c
so we make them
a
b
c and duplicate with a dot
b dot c dot
okay
then
okay uh so i probably need to
do this this way
so
and
we need a blank here for the second tape
and we need a blank here for the third
tape okay
then
we also need
blank and blank dot
okay that means the head is at that
location
so initially
we have
w1 dot here
if the probability w1 is 0 or 1 right
and we have blank dot here and the blank
dot here that means that means
the for the first tape
we will read the symbol w1
and for the second tab we will read
blank for third tab will read
blank
okay
so
every time
we can use a single tab two machine to
scan
the tape once and
collect
the dots
symbol for example for this example we
collect one
we collect a we collect b
right
and we can use the state
to trace
m's state
like we are doing
like we are doing in
using one dfa to trace two dfas
okay
pretty similar with that
we incorporate m's state into s state
everything every state of s is
keep uh keep tracking the state of n
then
after collecting one a b we know m's
state and the 1
a b
then we check up this entry
where
transition
of m
goes for example it goes to mp
and for example
change to
and change to
b
and
keep the same way and stay
and go left
go right
for example okay
then we implement the transition on
the tab here
so
we will
we will make
this symbol zero
dot
right because stay and change to zero
so that would be 0 dot
then we make a
a dot here
b
and make
this one
a dot indicate that
the head move to left right
move to left
and then
keep the same
symbol but
it will become b instead of b dot and
the head move right
so that'll be a dot
okay
so
in this way we can implement any
transition
done by m
onto our s
and using the tape to do that
and someone may
argue that okay uh actually you have
infinite tape how do you handle that
there's no problem at all here because
initially you have w here right like i
write this part and
other tabs are empty
and here comes the
i don't know pretty essential property
of
turing machines that
for turing machines
one step
one transition
can generate at most
one symbol appended to
the string or that say
written on to the unused tape space
okay
so for this example if you want to fill
this box
by c you want you need to spend one
transition right
and again one transition one transition
right
so
you will spend transitions on feeding
tab space to grow the type content
so in that case there is no problem to
handle that for by single type right so
you can see in this example if
if you want to fill this one
as let's say a
and then we
write a blank after a
how do we do that we just need to move
the whole thing
back
one space well it's pretty
i don't know tedious work or you may
think it stupid but
it
it can be done
right it can be done
in this systematic way so every time you
need to
extend
a tape
the space of a tape you just need to
copy everything
you just need to copy everything
one
one block once uh
space away then you have one more space
here then you can do whatever you want
to do
okay
so there's no problem for one single
tape to handle the storage of multi
tab
okay is finite
number
okay
so by doing this way uh in
in the textbook is writing more you know
uh formal way here
we
for
on every
input
oh okay here is what i just write
there
we initially have this part on our
single step turing machine
so the
there are separator here here here and
maybe more tape right here
then firstly you will read w1 and for
other tabs blank
okay
so every time
to simulate uh to simulate a single move
of m every time as our single tattoo
machine scans the tag
of one
scanner type
from the left hand end
to the final tapes and then you know
which symbol will be read on each tape
then we simulate that move and implement
the change onto our single tab
then we can pretty much similar simulate
anything
and what uh anything ends doing
so in this way
if n
if n goes to accept
we can go s can go to its own q accept
to indicate
the input is accepted or
reject and we go
reject okay and if it's keep running we
keep running so
we can pretty much build up
equivalent single tap tube machine given
any possible multi-type turing machine
okay
so
since they are equivalent since they are
equivalent
we can extend our
definition of recognizable
even decidable to
uh multi-type 2 machine right
so we can say that a language is too
recognizable if and if and only if
some multi-tab 2 machine recognizes the
language
see
so for computability they are equivalent
and then we are going to
we are going to
look at the non-deterministic
computation for turing machines
and remember that non-deterministic
means
there are several choices at any point
as i said you shouldn't
think choices as the truth you do no you
don't you don't choose anything
the machine just fork enough
branches and go
and go
each branch
to the end okay so it's
doing anything possibly
in the computation and return the
accept accept okay
and to do the non-deterministic
computation we also need to change the
transition function of the turing
machine
so
see we have uh
state and the symbol red from the tape
then map2
you see this part is in our fundamental
definition now it's non-deterministic
computation so we map to power set
that means any possible subset can be
mapped to
so
you can have
any
any next step you want to design for the
non-vitamins tube machine
okay
so
it is interesting that you see for dfa
and nfa
we can prove the equivalence
of
having
the capability of non-deterministic or
not right
but
for pda like i just described dpda is
different from
pda we have introduced
in chapter two they are different but
for two machines they are equivalent
again okay they are current again
so
the same argument goes here that we want
to
prove that to machine
has equivalent
non-deterministic machine and also
non-deterministic machine
has an equivalent to a machine
but
this direction
is trivial right because the same as dfa
nfa because a deterministic machine is
a special case of non-deterministic
machine so by definition
any
deterministic machine has an equivalent
non-deterministic machine
which behaves exactly like that
deterministic machine right because you
only need to
have the transition function
exactly only one possible next move as
the determination machine so that
there's no problem there so what we want
to prove here is that every
non-deterministic turing machine
has an equivalent deterministic machine
okay so that's our
theorem
3.16
i will give you my version of the
proof concept
explaining how the whole proof
goes and
it is not a formal proof but it will be
a explanation to what the proof on the
textbook
how it works
okay
so
let's think about it for
non-deterministic computation
you start from
for two machine let's say you start from
a
star configuration like q0 w right
so that's your start configuration
then
it is possible that you have let's say
two branches right so c one one may goes
to c one c two one and c two two
and then
this point may have three branches right
and this point have two branches
something like that
and then you have c
three
one c three two c three three
c
is not a good i think
let's say uh
that's remembering this as 1 2 and 1
sorry 1 1
and
then
you have 1 1 one
one one two one one three okay three
branches and then see one two one one
two two
right
and then possibly you have more
more
things like that
okay so you can see that why we want to
define configuration and all this stuff
because we can easily represent the
whole state of uh
a snapshot of a turing machine so
you can think of you are writing a
single temperature machine because you
have infinite tape
right
so initially you use your infinite tape
as
this you use a separator and store c1
here
okay
and since you have c1
you can check up the machines the
non-deterministic machines transition
function and the notes that oh c1
will map to
c11 and c12
of course the
transition function here does not
directly give you c11 and c12 it is only
a transition right about a state
and
symbol and give you
two
state
q1
b
and
probably
right
and the q
become p and the c and right something
like that
then
look at the c1 you implement the
transition to c1 you can get
c12 and implement this transition you
can get c
sorry
c11 and implement this transition you
will get c12
right so
in this way
you think of you
implement a single type 2 machine
which
use the tape as a cue
okay then you write c1 first then starts
the whole procedure
then each time in the iteration
you remove the first
configuration
of the tape
then
implement the first one
you you look at the c1 you know
there are two branches later so you
implement the first
transition to c1 and
write
c11 onto the tape and implement the
second one write c12 onto the tape
okay
so every iteration
the machine does this thing just just
this thing so next iteration
it will remove c11
and look at c11
and
look up the delta function the
transition function of the
non-determining machine and the notes
that they will there will be c11 c12 c13
right
so
we just write c11 onto the tape
c112 onto the tape and then c113 onto
the tape
okay
then go back to the head
because you have to remove this one
right
then
go back remove c12 and also look up
the
transition function you know there will
be c1 to 1
and the c12
and you remove this one
okay
so you just
remove the first configuration
in the tape
and then implement all
implemented transition you
obtain from the transition function of
the non-deterministic
machine you want to simulate and then
you know how many configurations will be
generated and write them down on the
tape append them to the to the end of
the tab content and you have infinite
tape right which is infinite storage so
you don't need to worry about the space
and you just repeat the whole thing and
what do you have
you will have
something similar to
bread
first
triversal of a computation tree
right
because you start from
you start from the
start configuration then you
run this one and
run this one
and then you go this one this one
this one
and as we just explained see
then you actually
traverse the whole
possible computational tree in a breadth
first way
so let's compare
the concept regarding
non-theta music computation
nfa and ntn
for
non-deterministic computation tree
it may look like
something like
this
right
so you have many computational
branches and
some you have one path and some not
and some you have
two or three
something like this
and for the
non-deterministic finite authentic the
nfa proof an effect to dfa proof
what we did is we consider
all possibility of the same
level
one
state that's what we did in that proof
okay
one state
and then
we did something like this
and as long as one is accept then this
is accept otherwise it's not right so
that's
an fa
two dfa
equivalent dfa it works like
the right-hand side
but
here for ntn
we find a
an equivalent deterministic tv machine
what we did is
start from the start
start configuration and then breadth
first search traversal
and then we know there will be two
configuration and then we know
it will be this one from
this one and this one goes through
so the whole thing
is
something similar to
this
but the difference is that
for nfa to dfa we
make each level
one step
but for ntm to dtm we traverse
breakfast
traverse the whole computation tree
that's why
this dtn
is equivalent to the ntn because the dtm
the determination machine will
go through
all possible configurations
by that ntn
okay so that's the concept okay
so in this case
in this case
the same definition goes to
uh non-deterministic non-determination
that as long as one of
one of
the configuration is accepting
configuration we consider the machine
except the string so in that case if
there is a accepting configuration we
will know
right
and when
we consider the machine reject the
string
there is no accepting configuration and
the o
branch ends
right all branch ends
then since o branch ends
and
when
if it ends it must end
at a
accepting or configuration
configuration then if the all terminal
nodes are
rejecting we know that the machine will
reject the string right
and then
if there are brain branch infinitely
growing then we know with our dtm and
goes infinite
right so they are equivalent
they are equivalent
so let's make back the proof to the what
we have on the textbook
that
in
the the proof in the textbook actually
provides
one possible implement implementation of
what i just described the concept okay
so it used the first uh tape as the
input table to
to put the input string and then use the
second tab as a working buffer to do the
you know c11
expansion and look up the
transition function and implement one
transition and the notes that c11 will
become c111 c112 and c113 something like
that
and then it used address tape to
do the branch trace what branch choice
so
you have
one branch 2.3 branch and one branch two
branch
one branch two branch one branch
two branch three branch so that's one
two one two okay so they use a dress
tape to trace the branch
so it goes to
very similar things that
it's uh
basically tracing
uh the computation tree
of that non-defamation machine
okay
so that's the
that's the uh
proof
of the equivalence between
non-deterministic machine and the
deterministic machine
so since they are equivalent so the thin
definition goes to
if
a language is turing recognizable if an
only
non-determinatory machine recognizes the
language
and also if a language is decidable
if and only if non-deterministic machine
decides it okay
so
we know that they are
equivalent
so next
we want to
prove that
there is a
computational model called
enumerator
okay what is enumerator enumerator is uh
also uh imagine
in is also a conceptual
computational model that it will
enumerate strings
you can
consider enumerator as a finite control
and a working tape but
it is unvisible
it is invisible to user and for user you
you only see that
in enumerator here
keep output strings okay
and
one enumerator
represents a
language a set of strings and it just
repeatedly
outputs
the strings it
contains
and it is possible that uh it will
output the same string twice or three
times doesn't matter but eventually
eventually
a an enumerator will output all the
strings
it contains okay eventually so if one
string is in the language represented by
a in an enumerator
that string will eventually be output
something like that
so we want to prove that
we can build up a turing machine
which is equivalent to one enumerator
so
we uh the prove
the equivalence
is like
this
okay
so enumerator all the the
the language represented by the
numerator will be recognized by some
tuning machine and vice versa
so given
an enumerator so now we want to do the
if and only thing
both direction
so given an enumerator
we want to build a tube machine like
this
okay
so
whenever
we have a
string to determine
we run the enumerator we use the turing
machine to run the enumerator
and every time the enumerator outputs a
string we compare with the input
since by definition
the string
of
the enumerator will eventually be output
so
we just wait until it appears
if
compares the same
we accept okay so you will see that l of
m
will be
all string outputted by le
but
you also know that for other strings
four strings
for strings not in error of e what will
this machine do
this machine will never give you an
answer
okay but this string can accept all
strings
that is in l e
on the other hand we want to prove the
other direction if you have a two
machine and
how do you
output all strings
in
l of n so we build up an enumerator and
as i said the numerator doesn't have
input
okay
so for
for intuitive
uh for a intuit intuitive way of
thinking you may
say that okay for for alphabet like
for example zero one
we just enumerate all strings yes so
lens revolve lens one
length two
lens three
right
so you can always enumerate all possible
strings
built
by
build upon and
alphabet
we call it let's call graph
lexicographical
order
okay
but
you cannot you actually cannot uh test
each string like you
feed
empty string to the m to see if it
accepts zero to the to m to see if it uh
it accepts you cannot do that why
because
machine n
if the string is accepted by machine m
is okay right then you can output that
string but
if that string is not accepted by
machine m it is possible that machine m
will loop forever and your enumerator
gets dark
for example here that
doesn't work okay that doesn't work you
cannot just
uh using lexical graphical order and
test each string that doesn't work so
what we do want to do
here is that
we
have all the strings like uh this this
is the first string second string third
string fourth string etc like s1 s2
here okay
but we do the loop
for i
equal to 1 2 3 et cetera and what did
what do we do we do that for s1
we feed it into n
but run only one step
okay wrong only one step
one step
and then
we
fit s1 again
to end and let it run two steps
and then
s2 two steps okay
and
s1 s2 s3
three steps
then
i equal to four
s1 s2 s3 as for four steps etc
okay so i equal to let's say n
you have s1 s2
sorry
s1 s2
2sn
n steps and then so on
so on so forth
then
you will see that
our machine m here will never be
stuck by some particular string that it
will never accept
on the other hand if
some string will be accepted eventually
it will be accept
right for example stream
213 will be accepted
by using m
with like 1 million steps okay then
when i equal to 1 million you will
accept 1 to two one three then you will
output two and three
so
we can build up a enumerator
in this way to enumerate all strings
represented by
that
uh
turing machine
okay
so
we can
say that a language is tuning
recognizable
if and only
if some enumerate enumerates the
language
okay that's
what we have done
and for chapter three
so chapter three finally let's go back
to the definition of algorithm so what
exactly
an algorithm or
procedure or recipe
if you see the numerical analysis or
computation there are many things called
recipes which means how you can do the
computation okay it goes back to
uh hilbert's problem
in hilbert's problem is one of the
famous
problem is that
he asks us to find an algorithm to
determine whether or whether a given
uh polynomial
diaphanetite
equation with integer coefficient has an
integer solution whether or not
so
he used some words in french actually
but
something like find that means
he
never believed that the algorithm not ex
the
non-existence of that algorithm okay
anyway so mathematicians and scholars
tries to solve this problem
so they found uh very soon they found
they found that we need to define
algorithm first
that is we need to define computation
first
so church proposed lambda calculus i
under calculus as i just as i previously
described and turing proposed turing
machines and
later they proved that they are
equivalent okay
so if we use turing machine terminology
then
the whole problem here becomes
is there
is the problem as a language to
indecidable to unrecognizable
if it is desirable then that two machine
is the algorithm it is not too
recognizable or too undecidable then we
don't have an algorithm something like
that
okay
so anyway
if you are interested you can look up
wiki or google this problem of the
beginning of study on computations and
we know that in general
there is no such algorithm now we know
that but for particular
form of such equation like over one
variable with
over one variable we can determine that
because you can do an exhaustive search
anyway so that's the beginning
and for turing machines
we actually will use different levels of
detail for two machines the first level
is
formal description okay
so
for formal description actually
everything eventually must be done at
the formal description level because you
need to formally define the seventh
tuple of artillery machine
including states including alphabets etc
okay that's required
but sometimes
okay actually often often times
we don't
do formal description
like we have
as m2 here we don't do formal
description like this
okay we do description more like
implementation level like
we
have here
for incoming
implementation level we need to describe
how
turing machine moves the head how data
is
data are stored and how you manipulate
that as long as
everybody agrees upon the
implementation which can be
realized realized by a turing machine
then
there's no problem
okay
then
more openly we
will do something like
this thing
okay so
well that that's uh
between
implementation description and high
level description
well for high level distribution is more
like we have here
okay we have here
these two machine is
kind of high level description we
describe what we want to do and
with
sufficient
knowledge regarding trade machine you
may believe that that's doable biotin
machine in that case
it's okay you don't need to speed out
all states transitions the formal
description
so in a way okay in a way formal
description is more like a
machine
machine code
or at least assembly language
assembly program which is
very closely attached to the underlying
machine okay
and you can see you can think of
implementation
description like some c program java
program you are writing
that's an implementation
okay hi
and high level description is more like
a pseudo code
it's more like
pseudocode we have
in like paper or something so
you may encounter some situation that
people give pseudo code and you believe
that's implementable right it can be
implemented or people write in some
pseudocode you don't believe it can be
implemented then you will ask him or her
to implement
at least the java programs the programs
the plus program python program etc
and
if
this kind of this level cannot convince
you finally you will need to have some
program that can run on your machine to
verify it that's basically formal
description okay so we will use the
three kinds of different level of detail
and
from now on mostly like high level
description because we won't go back to
do a formal
way of turing machine because that's
very tedious
however you still need to convince
others that what you want to do with tui
machine
is really doable okay that's also a
a
mathematical way
and
let's see an example here if we want to
determine a graph is connected
then we define in a transmission way we
define
graph
as a string
and
the language is that
the graph is connected
the string is in the language
so let's have a high level description
of a turing machine that decides a that
means
the string in a language a will accept
not in a language a will reject okay
so you can simply read the whole thing
here that you select the first node and
mark it and
repeat
the loop until no new nodes are marked
right
and
you just check each node
if it attached by an edge to a node that
is already marked then mark the node and
every iteration you mark some node right
since g has in
finite nodes and it
oh it uh each iteration you mark some
nodes eventually it will stop
and after stop you check if all nodes
are marked then accept because they are
connected otherwise reject
okay so
in a way we all believe that this uh
this algorithm can be implemented by two
machines so that's a
high level description okay
and by this example finally we want to
say that
all
all problems you want to model you need
to determine some encoding scheme for
this example we want to encode a
graph
onto the as the input string so
one possible encoding scheme is that is
like this we use left parenthesis
one two three four and a comma comma
comma right parenthesis to encode the
vertex
and then we encode
h
and graph is verticent h right graphics
vertex and h
so that comes to the encodings of the
mathematic
objects in mathematics okay you need to
have a reasonable you need to have
reasonable
way to encode
the input string that will not can be
processed by your turing machine and we
will
discuss that a little bit later but in
this in this example particularly this
example you must know that firstly
1 2 3 4 are not integers they are just
symbols
and secondly such encoding
cannot be basically cannot be general
why because
you cannot encode an arbitrary finite
numbers of nodes
if you want to do that you need to have
some new enumerating system for
like know the
node number
2134 something like that and then you
can encode arbitrary
numbers of
vertex
but for easy representation we use we
usually use uh something like this and
we know that it can be
understandable that uh
the encoding scheme is important for
designing a turing machine
okay