okay we have introduced
uh non-different music final automata
didn't miss the final automata
uh in a way we are trying to use
computational models or machines to
specify
languages and don't forget that
languages are problems and the strings
in the language is the problem instances
of that
of those problems and
using a machine to indicate languages is
like
we have a machine here and you ask
it to process some string right
it will either accept or not and
when it accept the string and all the
string can be accepted by the machine
we use the notation error of m to
indicate that set
right that means the machine in
our concept the machine can
solve this particular problem
which is represented by the language of
that particular machine
so that's why we
use the computational model to define
computation
and to reflect which kind of
language can be handled by the machine
so previously we named the language
can be handled by either
deterministic final automata or
equivalent non-deterministic final
automata
we name that language regular language
okay so in the previous
sections the regular
comes from nowhere actually but
here we think of uh we think of the
language another way okay we not think
of
we uh try to express the language
in another way see in previously we
defined
a dfa and actually what we want to
discuss
is the language of that machine
so give you a dfa you exactly have the
details of that machine
you have the source code but what this
machine can do you actually have no
idea
however we can discuss the language
of that machine in that indirect way
so in this section we try to
design expressions
to directly express
languages okay so
what we want to do here is called
is called regular expressions
okay and as i said we want to
design some way
to indicate to specify
some language directly
so recall something
is a regular expression if
it goes with
the definition here okay
and before
we define a language we need to have a
alphabet first okay we need to have
alphabet first so let's say if the
alphabet
is like let's say zero
and one okay
so don't forget that zero and one here
is not
integers zero and one it's just you know
we use zero the symbol and
one symbol to to to specify two symbols
okay zero and one here we define
regular expressions for this alphabet
and pay attention here
every symbol every symbol
in this alphabet we make it
a regular expression
okay so again that's zero
you might mistake it with
integer zero as i said it's not it's
just a symbol
the simple zero here we
make it a regular expression
that means we overload the meaning of
that symbol
again okay so in this case we use
as a regular expression
so the 0 here is not integer 0 it's not
the symbol 0 in the alphabet
it's a
regular expression
and the purpose to have regular
expression is to
express language right
always remember that a regular
expression represents
a language which is a set of strings
okay so when zero here
as an as a regular expression
what language it represents
we define that when we use a symbol
here from some alphabet
we make the symbol regular expression
the regular expression
indicates specifies the language
of one string language is a set of
strings
right and the language specified
for this example the language specified
by zero as the regular expression
is a set of string containing
only one string which one
the one
contains only one simple
of
the alphabet which is this
regular expression okay so
when we write this way the zero here
it is actually a string
a string of length one and that
one symbol is the symbol zero
okay well in for some reason it's pretty
confusing for many people
but you need to understand that
in addition to integer 0 i use here
there are actually three meanings
or or you can think of it as the data
type
in like java c plus plus
in that way you have the same name
but when it is
considered as different data type they
are different okay so
the first meaning here is that
in alphabet it's symbol
okay and as regular expression
the data type are let's say regular
expression
or we use you know program language
reg exp
the third one is here the zero here
is string not a symbol it's a string
but a string of lens one that one
is the symbol zero okay
so to understand
the first definition you need to know
that
from an alphabet here
the a here is a symbol
from the alphabet okay and we make
the exactly same symbol we
overload the meaning of the exact same
symbol
as regular expression
okay and the regular expression
here the language of the regular
expressions
here is a set of strings
which contains only one string and
that string so here
is the string
and that string is a
sorry is a
and
okay so that means
for an alphabet
zero one we use
the first definition to create
a regular expression 0
and when 0 is the regular expression
the language specified by the regular
expression
is one sorry zero
the string only this string
the set of only this string and also
we also make one as regular expression
and
it indicates this
language okay so that one here
is a string
then we also make epsilon which
we are using to indicate a
empty string we also make it
as a regular language that's a regular
expression
when it is a regular expression the
language of
this regular expression is
this language
which is a set of strings
and this set has only
one string which is
empty string okay
okay so further
we make empty set the symbol for
empty set as regular expression
and as regular expression
this regular expression indicates
empty set okay empty set
although there are no same symbol on the
slide
but they are actually different
they are of different types data types
they are of different
you know meanings
so the
three definition here creates
so many
regular expressions for a given alphabet
right so in our case here zero and one
we have four
uh regular expression
and you can you can easily
find that this regular expression
defines the language
containing zero member
that is no member okay the zero here is
really really integer
zero and
these two these two
definition defines
regular expressions indicating
set of strings that contains only
one strings right
this is one string okay and
this is one string two
and here the second rule
defines the regular expression indicates
set of strings containing one string
but that string the length of that
string
is zero
then the first definition
defines all
regular expressions for the given
alphabet
contains one string and the length of
this
string is one
okay so our first
sorry our basic case is
covered languages
has no member that would be this one
and the languages have only one members
and the one members the length zero
and one all of them
okay
okay then
given an alphabet here
we use the three rules
to cover the basic regular expressions
oh by the way someone might ask what's
the difference what's the difference
between
empty set and empty string well
it is a very difficult question because
they are totally different they are
nothing
alike okay empty set
is a set contain nothing
but empty string is a string
contains nothing they are
you know totally different concept
so it's like you don't have
bank account and
you have a bank account but you have no
money in it
see that's totally different okay so
that's a
similar situation here anyway
so based on the three uh basic
definition
we use three
more slightly more complicated
definition to add
the variation of regular expressions
so firstly we use
the operator let's call it cup
okay cup we use the operator cup here
to make new regular expressions
so whenever r1 and r2
are regular expressions we say that
r1 cup r2
is also a regular expression
see that's our definition since
it is a regular expression what is
this regular expression
means or what language is represented
is indicated by this
this regular expression
it will be since r1 is a regular
expression
so r1 really indicates some
language right which is set of strings
and the same thing goes to r2
right so we say that when you
use cup operator to connect r1 and
r2 the language the
language of the new regular expression
here
is the language of a one
union with language of r2
so that's why we write it this way
okay so for the same
style of definition we defined that
circle is another operator to construct
a more complicated
regular expressions so when r1 and r2
are regular expressions
we write r1 circle r2
as a regular expression and such
a regular expression indicates specifies
the language of r1
concatenates with language of r2
so goes to the final one
if we do a star here if r1 is a regular
regular expression r1 star
is also a regular expression and the
language
indicated by r1 star
is the language of r1
with the star operation
okay and don't remember
sorry don't forget that
parenthesis here
parentheses here is not
basically is not in the definition of
regular expressions
parenthesis here is you know expressing
the uh priority of cabin
combination or operations
that's it so it's a common mechanism
okay
so you see we
for any given alphabet we use three
basic definition
to define basic
regular expression then we use
three operators cup circle
and star to make to make
regular expression more complicated okay
let's see some example examples in the
textbook
okay so these are examples from
the textbook and assume that
the alphabet is 0 1 and
again they are not integers 0 and 1 they
are just you know 0
and 1 as symbols so
according to the basic
definitions we know that if we consider
one as an a regular expression
the language indicated by zero
what is
this set contains only
one string of zero which is a string
and also we have
1 as regular expression we have this
language
okay so you see then
when we write 0 star
1 0 star and
please note that we usually
ignore circle
in here and the circle in here
okay so the whole regular expression
is actually zero
star which is a regular expression right
and the circle one circle
zero star
we usually consider circle operation
is more like multiplication
why because it's a concatenation right
and you can see some interesting
uh properties like if you have a string
one zero zero one
and the con the length of the string is
four
right and you contain it with
1 0 1 then the length is
2 so the length
after concatenation will be 6
right that'll be one zero zero one
zero one and
it's like uh uh exponential
uh like a power law stuff like that so
combination is likely
to be considered something similar to
multiplication
and we can also consider cup here
more or less like addition okay so it's
multiplication
addition that's why we usually ignore
circle here okay so in that case
we have this one so
for zero star what is the language
that would be this language
doing the operation right so
you know it's like this and
what will this be this will be
artificial epsilon right and
itself and
square cubic
and the fourth power and so on
okay and also
when we concatenate this
language with this one
and it's cell the the visual star
again
what will be the resulting
language you can easily see that
you will have all strings that contains
exactly a single one
right so doing concatenation and
combination here
you will have the string containing
exactly a single one described
by this regular expression
okay then not part of the
regular expression definition but
it's more or less like a
syntax sugar we use
sigma itself see sigma here
is a set which is our alphabet the
set of symbols but
we use sigma here as the
syntax syntax sugar to indicate a
regular
expression and what is that sigma
here the language of sigma here
is actually the language
of all symbols as regular expressions
in the alphabet so that will be
[Music]
this language and remember that
0 here is a string one here is a string
okay so you can think of that
sigma as regular expression means
all possible strings
composed by the alphabet of
length one okay so
if you have a sigma a
b c then
as a regular expression this regular
expression
means a b
c the string of the set of the strings
and each string is length one so
the a here is the extreme b here is a
string and c here is a string okay
so what is sigma star
in this case in in
in what i just described you can think
of sigma star
what is
empty string artificial right
artificially created
empty string
sorry union sigma itself
union sigma squared union
sigma cubic and so on to infinity
then that will be
sigma right and that's for the
0 1 example here so
sigma itself 0 1 right what is square
0 0 0 1
1 0 1 1
all the string of length 2 composed
from the symbols of sigma and for square
0 0 0 0 0
1 0 1 0 0
1 1 0 sorry
1 0 0 1 0 1 1
1 0 and 1 1 1 all strings
of length 3 composed
by symbols in sigma
so
it is a very very very convenient way to
indicate
for a given alphabet
all possible strings
composed by the symbols of the given
alphabet
you actually already seen such
definition in our previous previous
slides
so that's why we write
sigma star as all possible strings
from the given alphabet
so that's why
that's why this regular expression
it indicates the string that has at
least the one
the string has at least one is the one
one okay another
definition here is the plus okay
so plus what is plus let's say if you
have
star that means a 0
a 1 a 2
a 3 etc
and the star sorry plus
is the same thing without this one
okay so plus is a1 a2
a3 et cetera
okay
so that's the plus and
it is interesting to see some uh
property here that
see if we have
this
regular expression then you can see that
the regular expression is zero one star
cup epsilon one star
right but since
epsilon the regular expression epsilon
means the set
of one string
empty string and concatenate
with what is one star that will be
epsilon 1 1 1
1 1 1 etc right
so what is the result of this one it is
exactly this one right
because every string
if you have an empty string in front of
every string is
nothing changed right
so epsom
as a regular expression put in front of
our back of any regular expressions
there will be no change so f zone one
star
is one star one star
f song is one star
so it's very like the
unit element for multiplication
right because like 5 times 1 is 5
1 times 5 is 5. so it's like
this one is concatenation and this one
is epsilon
so it's like that and
for empty set
well it's slightly more interesting
because
one star what is one star the language
of one star will be
epsilon 1 1 1 1 1 1
etc right and you concur
it with nothing
remember it's nothing so what will be
the result of this one
it will be nothing why
because the empty set cannot give any
elements for you to do the cartesian
product or contamination
so there will be no result no results
for this
as a set so that would be an empty set
by definition then it creates something
like
if you concatenate with
empty set as regular expression
the result is always
empty set so it's also very like uh
it's similar to phi times
zero becomes zero it's 0
times 5 becomes 0 and
any integer times with
0 the result is 0.
what is what is it called
and it is called annihilation element
annihilation element it destroys
everything
concatenated with it right
and well finally artificially
pretty artificially
if we do start on empty set
as regular expressions all right
what is the language here so by
definition
star empty
doing start will be
this right then
that will be what is this empty set
and the doing star sorry that i should
do one more
like this then
you will have artificial
this one right union
star zero uh sorry mt 0
mt itself and empty twice empty
cubic etc
all these are you know nothing
but this one is artificially
inserted so the final result would be
this that's why we have
this here it's pretty artificial that
you you have an empty set and
after doing the operation the empty set
has one string which is empty string out
of nowhere
okay so that's it so that's a
artificial definition for the result of
the star operation
you always have inserted the empty
string
here so
now we can say that it it is pretty
straightforward that
using regular expression
can be we can use regular expression to
specify specify
languages you can use the cup
and the circle and the star operators to
make
a regular expression pretty you know
complicated okay now we have defined
our regular expressions and
if you think about it you can easily uh
find that
for the three basic definition
here this one is
indicates the well uh empty set
which is a string but nothing
oh sorry which is a set with no
elements in it right empty set
and it is apparently
a regular language why because
you can have some
finite automata without any accept
states
then that final automata recognized
empty set
and this one is also regular language
and this one is also regular language we
will
prove that later
and since all these
three more complicated regular
expressions
we already proved the closure property
of
regular expressions at regular languages
with these operations and
you probably can see the connection
between
finite automata and regular expressions
and
you are not wrong so we want to
prove the equivalence with final
automata
okay and don't forget that every time
you see the word
equivalence equivalent you need to
understand how to judge the equivalent
and
here is also that we want to say
some language okay some language
if it is regular what is
what does that mean our definition says
that a language
is regular because some
finite automata can recognize it right
okay now we want to prove that a
language is regular
if and only only if you can use
regular expression to describe it
okay so the language
can be recognized by
some final automata such language
can be described by some regular
expression that's why that's what we
mean by equivalence
equivalence okay so
there are two part of it if
and only if okay
so firstly
we prove one direction here that
if a language is described by a regular
expression
that means arbitrarily you write some
regular expression
like what this will stop 1
1 0
1 star 0 0 1 something like this
the regular expression the language
described by the regular expression
it is regular
that means we can find a finite automata
to recognize this language that
means the language of the final automata
is exactly
the language of the regular expression
that means
every string
in this set will be accepted by
the machine here and every string not
in this set will not be
accepted by the final automata
okay then
how do we uh prove this direction
it is quite easy we start from the
definition
of the regular expression
so for
and alphabet we make every symbol in
that alphabet a regular expression
right so
for a single alphabet regular expression
the language is a string
of length one and the dot string is
exactly
the alphabet so for each alphabet we can
design an nfa
a non-deterministic final automata like
this
right so
stop right stop start state and
accept states and consume
one symbol you can easily see that
such an fa recognize
exactly this language
okay exactly this language and as we
uh discussed we cannot use diagram
although or visualization here we need
to
formally describe this machine so
that's formally described this machine
let's say
the machine has two states namely
q1
q1 and q2 and
the sigma is given and
q1 is the star state and only q2
are is in the accept states
and the transition function is that
at q1 the input signal
input symbol is a goes to q2 that would
be this transition
otherwise everything goes to
nowhere okay otherwise everything goes
to nowhere
so that would be the formal description
of this
nfa and according to our
our result we know that this language
can be recognized by nfa it can be
recognized by dfa
therefore all possible regular
expression in this
form
well gives a regular language right okay
so for the second for the second
uh definition we use m
epsilon as the regular expression the
language for that
regular expression is a
set of string containing only an empty
string right
then we we design
this nfa for modi we can write this this
way
sorry that would be
too many lines so only this one
and you can see that this nfa
recognize exactly this language
right if you have one symbol then
it will not recognize it it starts from
this state but any one symbol any
if you input anything any empty thing
then goes nowhere and it doesn't accept
that string
right you can also uh refer to the
definition of acceptance of strings
that'll be pretty important
so that's our nfa here
and finally as we already described
if we use empty set as regular
expression
then the language is empty set and
pretty easy you just design
an nfa without accept states
so formally we describe it this way
then see empty set is also regular
and actually any
finite set of strings
are regular because you just need to
expand everything
and write it as dfa and the state
must be finite because you have finite
string
string or finite length then everything
is regular
okay so we have
three basic
regular expression and we already proved
that
with the three basic definition
with the regular expressions defined by
the three basic definitions
all the language described are regular
right then our proof is basically
finished why because
we define the cup operator
as the union of two languages
and we know that we already proved that
the class of regular languages is
is closed under the union operation
right so we already prove it
and we also
already prove it because concatenation
we already
proved the crucial property right also
star operation
see so it goes like
we any of languages described
by the first three definition
are regular and we know that
any regular languages operated
with the three operations
here will result in regular languages
so that's why we know that
a language is described by a regular
expression
it must be regular okay so
that's our proof and we can have an
example here
for example if you have alphabets a and
b
okay a and b then we use
a as regular expression
then what is the regular expression
what language is the rig will be the
regular explaining
regular expression described that will
be a right
and the corresponding nfa is like this
and the same thing goes for b
and if we use a circle to
construct a slightly more complicated
regular expression
like what is the language
that would be a b
right and
according to our proof we just need to
concatenate
the two machine and
remove the acceptance here right
and add one epson transition here
and the process has been described in
the previous proof
so that would be the concatenation then
doing a union
so see then we can control the machine
to recognize
to the language language of
two languages
the union of two languages described by
a regular expression
so we copy this part and copy
this part as one new
start state and epsilon
transition right then we do
a star operation on this one how do we
do that
we copy the whole thing here we copy the
whole thing here
then add one more start state
also a new accept state and abstrom
absolute absolute then create this one
so as you see any way you write
your design you developed
a valid regular expression you can
easily
create the corresponding
non-deterministic finite automata
for that regular expression so any
language
that can be described by
regular expressions are
regular because by definition we can
have the corresponding nfa
right away
okay so that's about it
for this hour