now we know that regular languages are
not all possible languages
then we will discuss closure properties
of regular languages
and we will discuss the following
operations
for regular languages
so the first one is union
uh the we have used two
kinds of computational model to prove
the closure property of the operation
of union the first one would be dfa
we proved that theorem 1.25 yes
and by constructing a new
dfa for
to ch to to track to keep track
of the transition of the two
corresponding dfas
if you uh remember that then
in short
since a is a regular language there is a
dfa m1 recognize a and the b
has m2 as its organizer
and we construct a new machine
m by simulating
you know the concept uh is stimulating
the two machines
but with the m's own states transition
function
etc and the transition function of m
is actually composed of transitions of
m1
and m2 and effectively
if we want m1 and m2 to process some
string
the computational path of m1 would be
like this and therefore m2 would be
like this and the m which constructed
considers the
two states a combination of the two
states of the machines m1 and m2 as
one state of the uh
newly constructed machine so the whole
process
for n is
something like this
then as long as one
of the two machines
as well as the one states of the two
states
of the two machines m1 m2 is a
is an accept state of the original
machine then we set the state
accept state otherwise it's not an
accept state
by doing this we can construct a machine
dfam recognized
to the union of two regular languages
okay so that's the actually the first
proof
in this course and we also use nfa
another computational model equivalent
to dfa
to prove the closure property of
operation union
so how do we do that since we have
two nfa and
let's say n1 for a and
n2 for b then we
add a new start
we copy all states from n1 and n2
assuming they are disjoint and add one
more states
and for this one more states we
have epson arrow epsilon transition
to the star state of n1 and n2
and basically the construction are like
this
we copy everything of n1 and n2
and add one more states which is the new
state
and so when we want this
new machine let's say n to process a
string w
initially start from the start state
there is a process going to n1 and
going to and the other going to n2
and we don't need to care about the
following operations
as known as one of the n1 and n2 except
the string
we consider our newly constructed nfa
and
accepts the string right so that's for
the union of a and b
by using the computational power
actually the property
of non-deterministic computation it's
quite easy to prove the closure property
of regular languages under the operation
of
concretion and the star right so
if we want to do concatenation we copy
the
string sorry the machine for a and
the machine for b then
the original accept states of n1
we make it we make them not accepting
state anymore
but we also add
additional abstrom
transition to 2
star state then
n1's original star states is the star
states of our whole machine so
our machine looks like this right
so by using this machine we can
recognize
the language
of combination of a and b
so combination
regular languages are closed that are
closed
under the class of regular languages is
under the operation of concatenation
and then finally for star operation it's
an
mixture actually it's a mixture of union
and the conconnation so let's say there
is uh
if a is a regular language now
if a is a regular language now we know
that uh
there is there exists nfa recognizing a
so let's say the nfa is n1
there is a star state of n1 and some
acceptance right and other states so
what we need to do is add one more
states
see that part is like concatenation
right and
epson and this is our new star state and
this state also plays a role of accept
state
by doing this we add we artificially add
epsilon into the language of the
newly construct
nfa can recognize right and then
we have absorbed back to here
the original star state so see that's
also concatenation stuff and
the app strong here here and here
is more union stuff
so the proof the construction of star
operations
is basically composed of
something from concentration and
something from union
so uh we constructed we we construct a
and dfa recognizing
the stock the result of the star
operation on
a regular language so the class of
regular languages
is closed under the star operation
okay so that's the three operation
we already proved previously
theorem 1.25 and
1.45 and
theorem 1.47
and the 1.4
okay so
they are called regular
operations
then we have one more operation
which is intersection here so if a
and b are regular languages we want to
prove that
the intersection of a and b is also a
regular language
that's yes cultural probability uh
closure property
and how do we do that actually we
already know how to do that
in theorem 1.25
we actually proved this result
right so let's go back
to there we just need to
change the construction process
by changing the or here
to end
then we got ourself
and a dfa that recognized the
intersection
of the two given regular languages
or you can use this form
they are equivalent okay so if you d
you feel this this form that will be
also
dfa recognizing the intersection
okay so
this is the proof of the crucial
property of
intersection
then the next one is complement okay for
complement
uh you need to pay attention to the
uh definition of the
word here complement
you know because uh in computer science
there are many
complements for example for logic design
you have
one's complement two's complements
stuff like that right so for for example
once complement just changed to zero to
one
one to zero so if you have string a
string zero
zero one let's say so the com
once complement of this string will be
one one zero right just 0
becomes 1 1 becomes 0. but
for complement here it's a complement on
set
okay because languages are
sets of strings so the complement
here
is a set complement instead of any
string complement
it usually is very confusing because
we many times we use
alphabets like 0 and 1.
so you might think 0 and 1 integer
0 and 1 or bit 0 and 1.
that's why i repeat many times
if we are talking about an alphabet 0
and 1
is not integers or value 0 numerical
values
0 and 1 they are just symbols so for
example we have a
language zero and one and
let's say and
grade equal to or greater than
zero the 0 here is
value 0 integer 0 but 0
here is not individual values so
0 and 1n what is the complement
in one's complement sense you've got a
language
1 and 0 and
n greater than 0 right but it's wrong
it's not where it's not what we are
talking about here
what we are talking about here is that
all possible strings
okay given an alphabet for example this
one
you have all given
all possible strings by
the given alphabet then
you remove all the given
strings in the language all the other
language
sorry all the strings in the given
so what is the complement of this
language
well it's pretty messy right
for example o0
is in the complement or once in a
complement
zero one zero one one zero stuff like
that
in the complement and as etc okay
so complement here is the set complement
then how do we prove that the class of
regular languages is um is closed
under the operation of complement
well if you think about how we define
regular languages then it will be pretty
straightforward
the definition our definition of regular
languages
is that if there is
a finite automata recognized in that
language
that language is regular language right
and for any regular languages
by that definition there is
at least one dfa recognizing that
language
so we just take
that dfa for example the m1 here
okay so let's assume that
the language of m1 is what we are
talking about so given a language a
regular language
you just need to take the dfa
recognizing that
regular language and then
you
re copy everything okay that say
we copy the states of the dfa
of course alphabet and the transition
function and the star state
then we
make the new
accept states the
states of the dfa
minus the original star states
okay so we change the accept states as
this one so for this example that would
be
q2 becomes no more state
not accept states anymore and
q1 becomes one of
the accept states and the q3
is also one of the accept states of this
machine
so it's pretty easy to see that any
string
in
the all possible string constructed by
the given
alphabet if a string
accepted by m1 it will not
accept it by let's say m1 prime
right
otherwise
it will not in this language
on the contrary if it's not
in here it will
be in here right
because after processing any stream
the machine has to stop
on one of its states originally
for m1 if it stops
on q2 then that
string is considered accepted otherwise
it's not now we have a new machine here
and the accept state is exactly
the complement of the original accept
states
then of course the answer is exactly
opposite to the original answers right
so we can easily construct a new
dfa recognizing the
complement of the given regular language
so the class of
regular languages is closed
under the operation of complement
okay
then let's talk about our difference
so what is different we actually already
talked about it
if you have a set let's say a
and if you have a set that's a let's say
b
what is a minus b here by definition it
would be
a remove all the elements
within b something like this
so by removing these parts
we got something like this
right this part will be a
minus b so that's
a minus b and
a minus b is also you see
if you have a universal set here and a
and b are both subset
of the universal set in our case
they'll be sigma star and
what is a minus b here
that would be let's say
sigma star here right and you have b
here
and what is b's complement b's
complement
is this part right
and a is here
and you see a intersect
with b's complement
is a minus b
okay so that that actually can be
derived
from the definition of these operations
so we draw diagrams for
you know you know easier explanation
so if you have no problem with the
difference between a and b
is equivalent to the intersection
of a and the complement of b
then the proof is almost
finished right why because
if a and b are regular languages then
you will have a machine
m for a recognizing a
and you also have a machine
m or sorry m1 and also have a machine m2
for recognizing b
then by doing a construction we just
described for the crucial property of
the complement
operation you can do an
m2 prime which recognizing
b prime right
and then you take m1 and
m2 prime doing the construction
of the intersection
[Music]
process right we just do
something like you know union then
change the final
part of the definition of the accepts
states to this one then you've got
intersection
then finally you construct
some machine
which recognized a
b complement the intersection of a and
the b's complement
and this one will be a minus
b the difference between a and b
okay so
we can construct and a dfa recognizing
the difference of a
and b so uh
the languages of sorry the class of
regular languages is closed under the
operation of difference okay
then the reversal okay
okay uh for the reversal operation it's
uh slightly complicated complicated
because uh
you know a string let's say a string
zero zero one we say
reversal of a string will be what
one zero zero you reverse the order of
the symbol
in that string that's the reversal on
string
okay that's a string operation but
the operation reversal on a set
of string that means
for all the string
in that set we do
the string reversal and then
collect all the string here we call we
do the reversal of that string
sorry on all the string in that
language
okay so
let's say you have a language a regular
language how do you prove that
uh the every string
in that given regular language
you do a reversal operation string
reversal operation
and collect all the results and
the set the newly formed
set of the strings is also a regular
language how do we prove that
and we still can start from our
definition
since uh regular language uh
since the given for any given regular
language
we have dfa for recognizing that
right so let's go back to
m1 here that say
the given language a
here
is recognized by m1
okay then how do we prove that
the reversal of a
is still a regular language
now we want to construct a new dfa
to recognize the reversal of a
and we can start from oh sorry we
actually want to construct
an nfa
the reversal of a and we start from the
dfa
of a so we basically copy everything
here
everything of m1 then
we make a new
state which is our the star state of our
new
nfa then we use
abs long transition to the
from the start state to every accept
state
of the original dfa okay
then we add another new state
which is our only accept state
and we also have apps wrong here
from the start state original star state
of the dfa
to our uh
to the safe states of our new nfa and
that state it will be s and will be a
and the q2 here or all original accept
states
no longer accept states okay
so let's say we copy all the states
of the original dfa and at s
and a at two states uh
yes two states and we actually
have seen the similar operations on
gnfa right so now there
are let's say in this case five states
and of course alphabet is still zero and
one
and then we reverse
all the transition on the original dfa
and make them an fa okay
uh make them the uh
transition in nfa way so let's say
uh it goes back to here
zero same thing right and
it goes back to here one then
no distance something like this
and then one no need to change
still one right and the zero here
here and the zero and one here
and i think that'll be
everything yeah
so
in this way you will see that um
if you want to uh list everything here
so the newly a new transition function
will be
let's say q1
if zero then goes back to
q1 right and if one
goes to nowhere and
if epsilon
goes to nowhere something like that and
you can list everything here i've
transitioned here to
our controller nfa and the
s is the start state
and the accept states only contains
one state of a
then it goes our
constructed nfa for
the reversal why it works
okay why it works because you can
you can do that according according to
the definition
of acceptance of a string of dfa and
an fa right for example
if a string can be recognized
by the original
dfa that means there is a
sequence of the state right
corresponding to w 1 w
2 to w n and
satisfying the three conditions first
one
r 0 is the start state and n is one of
the accept states right
and you can see how we constructed
an fa here when we process a string
the same string the reversal of the same
string
it will firstly go through an epsilon
transition to the accept states
right to the accept state
of one of the original dfa
right for the exam in this example rn
sorry i shouldn't write r n there i
should write
r n here and it will be s here
right then since the
arrows are all reversed
so for the nfa
when you process wn
that's a symbol there is a path
trust trace bay trade sorry
trace back to
this way so w and minus 1
are m minus 1 stuff like this and
finally you reach
w 1.
that will be r0 that's the star state
right and we have an epsilon
transition here
you append epsilon here
to a right
so every string accepted by the original
dfa
will be accepted by our
newly constructed that's saying
another n we use n
here right
because the definition of acceptance
so uh these way works then
for another direction every string
accepted by the constructed
nfa
you can find that way
here and remove
this part and this part and the reverse
the whole thing here
then becomes the requirement
of the different in the definition
for a dfa to accept that string so every
string
every string oh sorry
every string accepted by the original
dfa the reversal will be accepted by our
nfa
and every string accepted by
the nfa the reversal will be accepted by
the dfa okay so
that's one way to uh
prove the closure property of the
uh operation of reversal and the other
will be
well in a way much easier you can use
a regular expression since every
regular language can be described by
regular expressions so let's say if you
have a language a
which is described by let's say
a star and the c
b a
cup b b
okay something like this i just
arbitrarily do that
you just need to reverse the whole thing
then you get the reversal of the
language
right for example for this example
you reverse the there's no reverse for
star operation because it's a unary
operation okay so you reverse the circle
here
okay so a star and
this part and you reverse um
there's no need to do reverse on this
but we
can still do that okay so let's try this
dba okay so that will be
a b b cup
we do that a b c
okay so that will be the reverse of
reversal of
a so a is that
a r is this one you just need to reverse
the regular expression
and after reverse the regular expression
describing the reversal of the language
since the reversal of the language can
be described
by a regular expression we already
proved that
the equivalence of verbal expressions
and
final automata right so the reversal of
a language a is also
a regular language okay so that's
another
way to prove the closure property of the
operation
of reversal then
next well we have an operation called
homomorphism
well some of you may not
be familiar with the operation here so
let's
introduce it a little bit
so what is a homomorphism homovision is
a string substitution
okay it's a operation of string
substitution
and each
symbol it is important here each symbol
is replaced by a single string
one symbol replaced by
a string and then they uh
they they don't
need to be from the same alphabet
they can be from different alphabets
without
loss of generality of course sometimes
you can do the same alphabet but
here we say we say that they are from
different
alphabet okay so for
homomorphism is actually a function
mapping symbols of one
alphabet two strings of
probably another alphabet or
identical alphabet it still works okay
so as long as you define a you know in a
way
a table for each
for each symbol of the
source alphabet for example if we have a
source alphabet
a b and c and our target alphabet
is zero and one so
this is one example
okay just one example so
in this example we map a the symbol a
here 2 1 1 the string in
pi star and the symbol b to 1 0
sorry 0 1 0 and a c to empty string
okay so that would be one possible
homomorphism
so as long again as long as you define
a table mapping each symbol
from sigma to a string
any string just one string in pi star
that would be a homomorphism so you can
define
many many many many possible
homomorphisms
okay so in our example here
we have a homomorphism defined
as this one so any a b
string string in sigma star
can be mapped to
[Music]
the target alphabet
okay so let's say abba
after making this string since
a is what 1 1 right
b is 0 1 0
b 0 1 0 8 1 1
then becomes
0 1 string here and the same thing
we map a b b c a
c c so a b
b okay so c what is c
in this mapping of the empty string so
you have empty string here
and a and empty string empty string
then since empty string is nothing so
the same zero one string mapping
by the homomorphism from different
a b string okay
so homomobian is a mapping you can over
string substitution if you will
so how do we prove that
if you have a language on sigma star
that's uh use something like this
so given sigma star here given sigma
here
it is all possible strings right we call
sigma star
and you define a homomorphism
this way sigma
between two pi star
so there is a pi star here right
so a mapping is defined
outside any string sorry any languages
yes any
string too then what we want to prove is
that
if you have a language ang
sigma in sigma star on sigma star
you can imagine that every string
in l can
be mapped to some string
in pi star right like we have this
here something like this so every string
in
arrow can be mapped to pi star every
string arrow can be mapped to pi
star right and all
strings may be in
in l map to
those strings on pi star
we call the image here
h of l
the homomorphism of the language
on sigma star
okay
then what we want to prove is that
if the language l here you know
is a regular language we want to prove
h h l here is
also a regular language
okay that's what we want to prove
and how do we prove that
it's also quite straightforward here
if l is a regular language
then it must be described
by a regular expression right for
example
we have a regular expression let's say a
star
the same c b a cop
b b okay so if we have a
regular language described as
regular expression this way we just need
to
change the symbol according to
for this example okay let's the hormone
movement here
one one the same star here
then c
right concatenates with
b contain it with
a and still cup then
b b
so we will get 1 1
star then you don't need to write this
because
empty string won't
affect the result under the operation of
concatenation right
so 1 0 1
yeah we actually can write one one
cup one zero one zero
zero one zero okay so
this will be
homomorphism on the pi star
of the original language
so
the homomorphism has the closure
property for regular languages
because h over l here
can be described by
the i and regular expression okay
so that's the uh proof
for the crucial property of homomorphism
okay finally we want
we want to prove the inverse
homomorphism
okay inverse homomorphism
and don't think
don't be confused by the term inverse
here
because it is not it is not
an inverse operation what is an inverse
operation
it's like if you have operation map
something
then inverse operation map the things
back
right that's called inverse operation
but inverse homomorphism
is not inverse operation
what is uh
let's say if if you have a language a
and you do an homomorphism and
generally inverse homomorphism
may not be a okay it might be a but may
not be a so it's not
it's not an inverse operation okay but
what
it is
and what what is the uh inverse
homomorphism
is that homomorphism
mapping strings maybe in symbols
from sigma to pi right given at
homomorphism
given an homomorphism
from sigma 2 pi so
the direction of the mapping
is the same but you
look it you look at the direction
inversely okay so
you have a language on pi
you have a language l on pi not sigma
on pi okay
then imagine that you try
all possible strings on sigma star
you try all possible string on single
master
may pain via the homomorphism
to pi okay for example this string
may be mapped to here and this string
may be mapped to here
and this string may be mapped to here
and the least string may be mapped map2
here
okay so you try
all possible strings
in sigma star and you see
which one which one falls
into the language you
[Music]
have on pi star
okay which one you
have on pasta and
you collect those
strings
on pi star via the hormone vision
to the language on pi star
you call this part
inverse of a
okay you collect all strings on pi star
which will be mapped
into l over a here
on pi star via the given homomorphism
we call all the the collection of all
these kind of string
the inverse of l over a here
okay okay so let's change it to a
inverse of a here
inverse of inverse homomorphism
of a here
we just look at the in the direction
of homomorphism inversely so we call it
inverse homomorphism so in general
if you have a language b
here then you do the homomorphism
you will get h of b here right
but in general all possible
strings in sigma star mapping into
h of b may be just maybe
a superset of b so usually
b will not be not sure
sometimes will sometimes will not be h
minus 1 h of b
okay so
how do we prove that the cause of
regular languages is closed
under the operation of inverse
homomorphism
given that
we know
we know the definition of regular
languages
is that we have a dfa recognized in the
language right so again
let's say if we have a language on pi
star
then
how do we prove
the inverse
which is on sigma star actually
oh sorry this one we want to
construct a dfa or an f
anyway a finite automata for that so
what we want to do here is that
for the language a here
we already know that by definition we
have a
dfam
then for every string
m will give us accept or
not accept answer right
and we want to
build a dfa
based on the m here
and merge the homomorphism
into a such that
it will work on sigma
okay we already know that on pi star
the m on pi star
work like language recognizing the given
language
then we try to merge
the homomorphism here then make this
machine
on sigma star and the processing the
string
mapping into pi star
and accept by this machine and all the
strings on sigma star accepted by this
machine
will be the inverse homomorphism
of the language a okay so that's the
idea
so let's do an example here
go back to our m1 here
let's assume that remember the direction
okay so we have a sigma star
sigma is abc here we use the same
hormone vision
in that slide okay and the pi
will be 0 1 here right
so in here
the language is
arrow of m1 okay
so we want to prove that
h minus 1 of l of m1
which is the l of m1
inverse homomorphism
is still regular we want to construct a
dfa for that
so we copy everything basically of
everything
from m1 we have three states
and now
we want to have this
dfa on abc right
then q1 is still star state and q2
is still the only accepted
now we want to rewrite the transition
here
and how do we rewrite that remember that
in our
example here h of a is
1 1 h of b is
1 0 1 0 and h of c
is epsilon okay so
we want to write a new
transition function so
for this transition function we will
need to write
okay q1 a b c
q 2 q 3 abc
right so when
the state of the machine is at q 1
what will where where it goes when
processing
a and remember that a is
1 1 so we just need to check
1 1
right so q1 encounters a
goes to q 2. that's it
so 0 1
0 right so
q 3 and nothing
and stays at the same stage right q1
so you will get something like
a b
c okay so
use the same construction q 2
1 1 still q 2 right and
0 0 1
0 1 0 q 3
and the q 2 because nothing okay
so that will be a
b and c
okay so for q three
one one goes to q two
0 1
0 go back to itself and nothing
so a
b c
okay so we have a
machine here works on
abc and then
if you have an a it will interpret as
in a way interpret as one one
and let's say for any a b c
string well
for example let's say a
b b a c
so we can go this way a
b b
a so accept right
y is accept because the rho 0
0 sorry one one zero one
zero zero one zero one one
will be accepted by the original machine
let's say
uh okay it's kind of messy here but
let's say 1 1
1 0
0 1 0 1 1
c accepted so
for any dfa on pi star
given a hormone vision we can construct
a dfa to recognize
the inverse homomorphism
on sigma star so the inverse
homomorphism
is recognized by a dfa
constructed based on that dfa on
pi star so we proved that
the cost of regular languages
is closed under the
operation of inverse homomorphism
okay so we have proved the
closure properties of
operations that we have here