okay uh we have established the
relationship among classes of languages
like
figure
and firstly in chapter one
we defined
a computational model called
uh final temper
and later deterministic final automata
and we define that the
language recognized by dfa
is regular it's a class of regular
languages
and then in chapter 2
okay after defining regular languages we
uh
discussed some properties and the
characteristics of regular languages and
the closure properties
and we also
found that there are languages outside
of regular languages
and
our first example is
uh
like this one 0 and 1n
and then we are in chapter 2 defined
context free grammar and the say that
said that
the class of languages that can be
generated by context-free grammars
is context is the context free language
and we know that uh
this language
the first example outside of regular
language
regular languages is definitely
context free language because you can
easily
write down the grammar for less language
so we know that
context three languages
include regular languages and contain
more
non-regular languages
other non-regular
and then we
we are defined two machines in chapter
three right
and according to two
uh according to the difference
of the operations of tuning machines and
uh pdas and the dfas for two machines we
defined two class
two classes of languages one is
decidable and the one is recognizable
right uh two recognizable
and for decidable that means for every
possible strings
of a given
alphabet
a decidable languages
a decidable language means that
you
at least you have a turing machine
for all possible strings
the turing machine either
accept that string
that means the string is in the language
or
reject
that string that means the string is not
in the language that's decidable
and for recognizable we have only you
know accept part that means
if you have a language
and you find a turing machine
recognizing that language that means all
the strings in that language will be
accepted by the turing machine and all
the strings
not in a language
will not
be accepted by two machine
however
as we
know that
not except
not not accepted by the turing machine
uh
for the phone the
not accept accepted part there are two
possibilities one is that the machine
still tell you reject and
it is also possible that
the machine will never give you an
answer okay
anyway so uh
we also proved uh
we also proved
a theorem that
every contextry language
every context free language is decidable
so we know that context free language
is
the class of tongue context languages
is definitely within decidable right
and we also we
have an example that
languages like this one
we can prove that it is not in context
with languages
but we can also easily
design a turing machine to accept to
recognize to actually to decide this
language
so we have examples that
uh
languages outside of contextual language
but inside of decidable so we know
for the relationship here is uh
appropriate drone in figure figure 410
here
and according to the definition
decidable
the class of decidable languages must be
within recognizable right according to
the definition
and the problem now here is that is
there any
language here
if there is no language here that means
decidable and recognizable
are identical
if there is something here then that
means they are
not identical they are different right
and
uh
since we will be using turing machine as
our
computational model
you know
similar to the computers we have right
now like your tablet notebook or desktop
computers
let's uh think about
the
meaning of decidable languages or and
nutrient recognizable languages okay
since we
consider problems as languages and
strings in a language as problem
instances of that problem although
the problem we consider
are yes or no type right
the machine either tells you yes or no
like a graph connect connectivity we use
as an example in previous chapters
we can easily
conceptualize that
decidable
the class of decidable languages
is more
what we want
as
uh problems that are a
practical solvable
practical soluble
algorithmically practically solvable
why
why because
think about it
uh if you have a problem instance
then if you have an algorithm
then
you give that algorithm the problem
instance
of course you expect that the algorithm
tells you
yes
the answer is yes or the algorithm tell
you the answer is no
right
and for the recognizable case for the
case of recognizable languages
if you have a problem that is
recognizable during recognizable and you
have the recognizer
you give an instance
to that algorithm
then
if yes
you will get the answer of yes that's no
problem right but
if the problem instance is actually not
in the language
then
when you
input that corresponding string into the
recognizer the turing machine
recognizing the language
you got lucky you will have a no as the
answer then your case is closed that's
okay
but it is probable that
the recognizer will never give you an
answer and you don't
know
if the string
is in the language or not
so
in a way of thinking recognizable
languages
are not
you know are really
eco rhetorically
solvable in practice
right in some way of thinking
recognize recognizable is not really
what we want we want decidable
okay so that's
we that's the uh
you know informal conclusion
when we
uh discuss computability
in practice what we want is really
decidable because you always want
you always expect
the algorithm you are running give you
an answer either yes or no
okay
or you think about the situation that um
you ask someone a question
and
the pers the person never gives you an
answer and you don't know yes or no
and
all you can do is keep waiting but you
don't know whether or not you will be
waiting forever
so that's the case of recognizable right
so we we really want to know if uh
are the classes of decidable languages
and the
pretty much uh turin recognizable
languages identical or not
okay or not
and
that's
what we want to talk about uh
in
[Music]
this lecture
so is there any problem algorithmically
unsolvable
what we want to
talk about the link the problem we want
to talk about right now is atm
okay so it's not the auto tailor machine
it's not the machine you get money from
you know of the bank
so it's acceptance
of
turing machine so
the naming convention here is that we
have a turing machine
okay and the input stream w is for the
machine
and
if
this machine can really accept the input
for it
which is w here
then the whole string
is in atm okay that's the definition
or you can think about that you are a
teaching assistant or you are a teacher
an instructor for some programming
course
and you ask
you ask
students to
write to
finish the homework assignment
and
and here
you can think you can consider it as
the program
returned by the student
okay so to machine basically is a
program
and
w here is the
test input or test cases
then
atm here
is that
all the program and test cases pair
in which the program accepts
the input
okay
then
what is atm
atm mean uh
the decidability of atm means that can
you write a turing machine
can you design a tier machine which is
also a program right
and
all the string sorry i shouldn't use w
here all the string in
sigma star
if
x in
atm your machine says yes
if x not in atm your machine says no
and it is it possible to
design such a turing machine that's the
problem of the decidability of atm
okay
now you have seen that
we want to prove
theorem 4.11
atm is undecidable
okay
before that as we just
discussed
we actually want to have
the example here right
we want to
have the example here
to
differentiate
to recognizable and decidable right
so
firstly we want to show that firstly we
want to show that
atm is recognizable
atm is recognizable right and to
prove atm recon is recognizable we just
need to you know design a recognizer
so
we say that atm is too recognizable
and we design recognizer so we just
write down a turing machine like this
says that on input mw
and don't forget that there is a step 0
as i describe step 0
to do format checking right
any invalid
format for the input
our machine will do a reject
okay
so
we only consider
inputs of valid formats
okay
so an input mw
where m is a turing machine and a w
research string
that's after checking format checking
and we know that there is a program here
there is a valid c program here or java
program here and there are inputs there
is a input string for that
program
then we just need to simulate the
machine on
the w
on the input string
and how to do that
well
details depend on all your you know
computational models machines or
whatever you want to use
but you can think of it that you use
your
notebook
to run virtual machines
okay so virtual machines is a simulation
from your host machine
and simulate guest machine
okay or you can think of that we have
underlying hardware and
your computer running a program
in a way
that's also simulation
okay
so we just need to simulate
n
and the
feed
feed w input w into the m
okay
so when you simulate another machine
then you know each step of that machine
but you have no con uh you have no
control right
the control i mean
you don't know uh okay i shouldn't use
the word control i should know that
you cannot uh foresee what will happen
you can simulate one step by one step
and know what is happening right now
okay
so
if you observed if our
algorithm yeah sorry our turn machine
observe that m enters its accept state
if
if it enters
accepted
then you know right then we just do and
accept
don't forget that the accept here
accepts what
accepts
this whole string
and
the accept here is
you
our turing machine universal turing
machine actually
accepts
its own input
right
although this accept is caused by
and
accept
w
right
because
u
simulated m on input w and observe that
observes that m enters its accept states
that means m accepts w then
you accept its input
the pair of mw
okay
and if n
enters reject then we know that m reject
w then we reject our
reject our input sorry use rejects use
on input
and
you know that the behavior of you here
is already
status
satisfying the definition
of a recognizer
right
you may be asking that why
and maybe it enters a loop
or
i or we should we can consider it at it
as a loop but
for the word loop you may think that you
can see repeating things
but no
and
let's say m may enters a situation or a
condition that it runs forever
maybe without
repeating anything
how's that possible of course it is
possible because you have a
infinite tape right
that say
if it enters some state
or some situation condition that
it just keep going right
okay in the right hand direction
not goes wrong or goes right right
so
just go
in uh
talk towards the right direction keep
going
it is not a loop
but it enters
some kind of loop for uh sorry some kind
of runs forever situation right
so in a way you don't you you don't have
a chance to
in general
detecting a repeat
or loop situation so sometimes we say
loop just you know um means that there
is a situation in which the machine runs
forever runs forever
okay
if n enters such
situation
as a simulator you
it also enters that simula uh situation
right so it so you will never give you
an answer regarding
its own input
in atm or
not right
so in short you can consider that
the answer of m exactly
is the answer of sorry the answer of u
here is it is exactly the answer of
wronging and
w
just by doing so
we already proved that
atn
is a tuning recognizable language
because the behavior of you satisfies
the definition of
recognizer
so the recognizer for atn exists
so atm is a recognizable to recognizable
language so that's
we know that
atm is somewhere in the circle here atm
is somewhere in the circle here okay
now we want to
prove that
atm is exactly outside of decidable
okay so we want to prove atm is here
it's not in decidable that's what we
want to do now
so
what we want to do
is to use the contradiction in logics to
prove that atm is undecidable
firstly what means by being undecidable
what does that mean
same as
language is non-regular or the language
is not context-free
that means
you
no one can ever
design a turing machine
that is able to decide atm
right being undecidable means that
and the same argument comes again that
well
perhaps we can
not design a tuned machine to be the
decider for atm
that doesn't mean that some very smart
people cannot do it
right
so we must
prove
the undecidability of atm in some
absolute way
you see
for recognizable we just need to
construct recognizer and since we
already construct recognize that there's
no
problem here
atm is recognizable
but to prove atm is undecidable we need
to have some
way to absolutely
shows that it is not possible
to design a decider for atm
so the skill we want to use in this
proof
is you know proof by contradiction
okay
so proof by contradiction firstly we
assume that
we assume that atm is desirable right we
assume atm is desirable we have used
this uh
technique
previously with
pumping lemma for either regular
language or country free language right
we firstly
assume that they are regular or they are
context-free languages then
we derive some
contradiction
so our assumption is wrong so
the theorem proved
so now
assume that atm is decidable
okay assume that atn is decidable
then
the decider for atn
exists
right
so
let's say h here
is the decider for atm
why it's called edge because
the first undecidable problem is called
holding problem
and
you know the author of the textbook of
aligns the acceptance definition for
tuning machines pdas and the regular
uh dfas
so
uh they it
the other changes the holding problem to
be atm here
but the whole proof structure
we can borrow that from the original
proof something like like it so we call
it h
means the decider for holding problem
okay
so
let's say h
is the decider
of atm
then since h is the decider of atn
that means
for its input
there is a
theory machine m and the two machine w
you set up the input
for h2 process
then h will
definitely
tell you the answer
the answer is probably probably accept
or
reject
right it will
definitely
within
some time to tell you that accept or
reject
if h tells you
if h tells you accept
that means
the given n
accepts w
if the answer is reject that means
m
does not accept w
okay so here you
you have to know that
there is no other possibilities
h always
as a decider
as a decider h always gives you an
answer
and the answer is either accept or
reject
and
for accept
that means
m accept w
for reject
that means m does not reject w
and don't forget that does not reject
actually con
contains
two possibilities one
you know runs forever
right
one runs forever the other is of course
reject
okay
so
m's behavior may have three
possibilities but
edge tells you accept when m accept w
and
reject when m does not accept w
okay so
we assume that such a decider exists
okay
or you can imagine
that there is some api existing
somewhere
someone provides you this api
you know on amazon ec2 or
other you know github
website and you don't need to know the
detail of edge you just need to know
when you give when you give a h
m and w h will return you an answer and
the answer
is either accept or reject and if accept
that means
the m and w you give
m will accept w
otherwise and does not accept w okay so
we assume that such an api such a time
machine exists somewhere in the world
then we can write down a program like
here d
let's write a program
okay
what
does our program d do
our program on a turing machine which is
a program okay which is a program
our program
calls h
okay
we call the api edge here
and what
on the input m
and m as a input
okay
it is possible you you need to do a you
know uh re-encoding for the n but
you can
you just need to reformat m according to
m's alphabet something like that so
anyway
m here
it's in the same it
essentially we just
repeat m itself as its own input that's
what we are doing right now
so
our program d here
is given
a program
then we call
h on
the program as a program and the program
itself as the input
so that's what we the the program d do
here
then
since we know that edge will
either return accept or reject it must
return
and there is only two possibility there
is no other possibilities okay
so if h accepts
okay
our d report reject
if edge rejects
our d report
accept
okay
so we just re uh reverse the answer of
h that's what
d do oh sorry that's what d does
okay
so
first question here is that
does the program d
exist
of course it it exists right because you
can write in any language
because all you all d
all d does
is
get an input
and duplicate
or possibly
re-encode the input
and then it
calls an api h and
that edge to c
to process the
input here
and since edge will return an answer we
just you know
uh make the answer false to true or true
to false reverse the answer and then
return
so there is nothing
in question
that
d
cannot do
so the existence of d
is no problem
d
always exists
okay so that's the first question here
then there if there is no problem
regarding the existence of d
then
what
suppose
supposedly
d will do is
here
that
this is the behavior of d
right
we
input
a program into d and that's wrong d
and d will definitely give us accept or
reject
why because there's no there's no
particular
you know uh there's nothing particularly
difficult
or possibly impossible for d to do
so d just
duplicate or possibly re-encode the
input and close edge and return
the reverse answer of edge right
so d either accept or reject
when d accepts
that means
and
the machine the
program you give d as input
m does not accept itself as the input
string
right
m does not accept itself as input string
well uh according to my previous
experience
many
many of you may
may think of
how is that possible program read itself
as input
well
in a way how
is it not possible
every program you write is a text file
right
then you just
input your the the source code the
source code of that program into that
program then it's as simple as simple as
that
don't think
too complicated
okay
the situation here is
pretty much
very simple
you just
fit in your own program the source code
of it that's it okay so we are talking
about
a program running and
on the input of its own source program
that's all we are talking about
nothing else okay
so if d here accept that means
the given n does not accept
its own source code as input string
if d reject
that means the given program m here
accepts
its own source code as input string
right so
this is the behavior of d
which is you know
which is uh
determined by the behavior of an h
then let's talk about
if
we
input
these own source code
to d
what will happen
okay
if we input
the source code of d
as the input string
for b
to process
then what will happen
we think we can think of it this way
if
the
answers accept
if the
that means d
does not
accept
its own source code right
if let me repeat that again
if d x uh the answer if if the answer is
accept
that's
well
indicates
d does not accept
okay d does not accept its own input
but it's wrong
right it's contradiction
why
because
it says the
does not accept
does not accept its own source code but
what really happens
is the
accept its own input
right
so the
so
this
one
is
wrong
because what really happened is that
the accept d
you need to think of the what mean uh
what does the answer of accept and
region mean and what really happened
okay
so if it really happens
uh okay that's a
if d really accepts d
that's the situation we're talking about
if d
really accepts
d such a situation
will happen under
the condition that d
does not accept d
so that's the
contradiction here
okay
that's a contradiction here
so
on the other hand there is another
possibility that
d
rejects
right
that's the other possibilities because
there will be only two
possible possible answers returned from
d
the other one is reject
so
if d
really rejects d
that will happen
[Music]
under the situation
that
d
accepts
so
that's also
a contradiction it's wrong
so also a contradiction
because what really happened
is
d
rejects d
and such a
such an event only happens in the
condition that
d
accepts d
okay
so that means
as long as
the decider of two sorry the decider of
atn which is the edge here
exists
as long as
h exists
we can surely construct d
and
d causes the contradiction here
then we know that
h
should not exist
okay
because the contradiction raised
by the existence
of
the designer of atn
so
the designer of atn should not exist
so atn is undecidable because there is
impossible to decide to
design a an
atm decider
okay so that's how we prove
theorem four point
eleven
okay
so that's uh
repeat the whole
proof
again okay so uh
very quickly
so the flow goes this way
firstly
we assume that
the decider of atn
exists
let's call it h
so the behavior of h is that
whatever input
into h
h will give you two only two possible
end answers
as will always stops and gives you
the answer
regarding the
string okay
so if h tells you
accept
or that say h accept
its own input
that means
m
accepts w
otherwise if h tells you reject that
means edge reject its input
that means m
does not accept w
and don't
forget that does not accept
contains two possibilities rejects or
runs forever okay
anyway we assume that h exists
okay h exists
so we can write
we can design a turing machine as
here kinda call it d
what does these two machine do
these two machine
will
process an input which is also a turing
machine
and then we the d here just duplicate
the source code of the uh sorry the
source code of the two machine and
possibly
re-encode the source code of that two
machine into the alphabet
of the turing machine
see because the alphabet
for d
may be different
from the alphabet for n right
so
d
may be able to uh to process m here and
may not be able to process its own
source code as encoded in these
alphabets so we probably need to
re-encode
m
for amazon alphabet okay that's two
that's uh
you know details but
uh you can think of why would we
want to
possibly need to re-encode it
okay anyway
so this job is essentially
duplicate m and
fit
the pair here
into h
and h is a decider so edge will always
stops and gives you an answer
if h accepts d
rejects if h rejects d
accepts
that's what we constructed to do
so this behavior is that
if d
accepts m that means
m
does not accept its own source code
if d rejects
m that means
m accepts its own source code right
that's the behavior of d
and these ex
these existence is no problem
because there is
no particular
impossible things
we ask did to do okay
however
contradictions
are obtained here
because
since d
also always stops
and let's check to the two possible
answer from d
if d
accepts
its own source code
that must mean
d
does not accept its own source code so
that's an inter that's a
contradiction
if d rejects
its own source code
it have to mean that d
accepts its own source code that's also
a contradiction
and see there's no other possibilities
so
the existence of d
is
impossible but the program of d can be
written down so
the impossible
the impossibility
is raised by the existence of h
so we can conclude that
h
cannot exist
okay h cannot exist
since h is the decider of atm
so our conclusion
is that oh sorry
our conclusion is that
atm is undecidable because the decider
of atm cannot exist
as long as
the decider of adm exists we can
construct d
to show to indicate
the contradiction
okay
so we know that
atn
is undecidable
and we also know that atn is too
recognizable
so
we complete the proof that finding a
language here
which is outside of decidable
but inside of recognizable
so we have
existence
in our instance here
so
basically we complete the
diagram in figure
410 the relationship among classes of
languages
and we exactly know the relationship
among classes of languages
is like what we have here
as in figure 14
okay
so regular languages is a proper subset
of context free languages and there are
languages here
and countif language is a proper subset
of decidable and they are languages here
and decidable
is a proper subset of recognizable
because
there is language here
okay