okay so let's continue to discuss
what kind of languages do
non-deterministic finite automata
recognize
okay i guess many of you have already
guessed that
non-dimitri final automata also
recognize
regular languages right you are correct
so we want to prove that nfa
and dfas are equivalent
and let me remind you that whenever
you see the word equivalence or
equivalent you must ask
what kind of criteria what criteria
we use to do the judgment okay
because if you use different criteria
you will get different results
and for this course most of the time
we use languages as the judging criteria
for equivalence for example
when we say
a machine a is equivalent
to machine b actually we are saying that
the language recognized
by this machine is the language
recognized
by that machine okay
so if machine
recognizing the same language we say
that
they are equivalent that's usually with
same
equivalence of one machine
but now
we say equivalence of
the set of a net phase
and the set of dfas
we are not talking about a single
machine we are talking about
a set so
what do we mean by
nfaas and the dfas are equivalent
actually we want to prove that
nfa
has an equivalent dfa
and also every dfa
has an equivalent nfa we actually need
to do
both direction why because we want to
prove that
the language can be recognized
by nfa or nfas
collectively is the language
can be recognized by all the dnase
collectively then we want to prove
in order to prove this we want we need
to say that
okay when you get one dfa
you can you can find an
nfa recognizing the same language as the
dfa
and vice versa but you see
why do we have only
every nfa has an equivalent equivalent
dfa to prove because
every dfa has an equivalent
anaphase is trivial
why because you can easily know that
dfa is a special case
of nfa if you don't
believe it you can go back
to the dfa session
and you see we just need to rewrite
we just need to rewrite
uh the definition of m1
so q is q1q2q3
sigma is one and zero and the q1 is the
star state
f is q2 right then we change
the transition function we add
epsilon column here and goes to
empty set
then we change the
current entry to be
set
and of course this nfl doesn't have
epsilon arrows epsilon transitions right
and every step it has only
one destination one path
but by definition it is still an nfa
so you can see that every dfa
can be transformed
to a to an nfa
and it is obvious that they
recognize exactly the same language
because nfa can go multiple
paths if you let nfl to go
exactly one path and there and
no absolute transitions then
that's df nfa behave
exactly like a dfa so dfa
is actually a special case of nfa
so there's uh there's no point to prove
that direction but you must know that
that the
direction also need to be true
to establish the equivalence of
nfa and dfas then if you have no problem
we have theorem
1.39 to prove
okay so how do we prove that
the proof idea is actually very similar
to the closure property
of the union operations on the class of
regular languages we want to
trace we want to trace
the operation of an effect
let's go back to
the union what did we what did we do
we say that okay you have two
dfa and
when process the same string you have
computational path like this
right then we construct a new dfa
the state
of this new dfa traces
the two states so it's
like this way
and any states here is like
this one so that's the idea
and look at how
nfa process
if we can do something like this
this this
this and this
this and this then
the machine will behave exactly
like a dfa right
and you might say uh well but
for two machine it it can
easily be seen that you have only the
combination
of their states right but
now is it possible to contain all the
possibility
actually it is why because
we don't care about multiple paths
to accept the string right as long as
one path accept a string
then the whole machine accept the string
in this case you can see that
we don't need duplicate
states for example
when it comes to this part
we only need to leave one
path because
start from q4 reading the same symbol
they will go to the same places
so we don't need multiple copies we only
need
one for each time step
so in this case all possibility
within any step
is the power set
of the state right
and it it it can easily be seen that
for every state for every state
you either have a process you either
have process on the state
or not so for this example
every time every every
time step you have so many
possibilities which is power of
the states so
we can use the same idea to prove
the union the closure property of the
union operation
and construct an equivalent dfa for nfa
so how do we construct that
so given an nfa
this one is given we want to
construct a dfa
and the 5 tuple is q prime sigma delta
prime
q 1 q 0 and f prime
and in this case the sigma is exactly
the same so we don't need to
discuss it right because we want to
construct an equivalent dfa
so what should be that what should be
the
state of the
dfa apparently
we can directly use power set like we
use cartesian products for the
previous case we can use power set
and when we use power set we can
directly use the
powers the members of the power set
as the label of that state
when you see the example we will we will
give
you will understand what i'm talking
about
so we use power set firstly we have
two children cardinality
of q states and then
we can use
the subset directly as the label of the
set to
represent what state the original nfa
has process on okay
so in this case in this case
what is the star state of our nfa
sorry dfa that would be
this state
it's kind of tricky that don't consider
it as a set
you should consider it's a label
attached to some state
and we use the label to indicate
to specify that set
sorry that state
okay here we say that the star states q
0 prime is this one
this thing but
that that is not a set
that is a state only the name the label
of the state okay
and what is the accept states
of our dfa
since every state
of the dfa is
or not is represents
a set of the states of the original nfa
as long as it contains an
accept state of the original nfa
we consider that state
our accept state
okay
then
what is the transition function
so right uh writing a transition
function is
exactly like what we did
for proving the closure property
of the union operations on the class of
regular languages that
our transition function
when the dfa on this state
and sees this symbol
and don't forget that this
state actually represents
a set of the original states of the
original nfa
example if the original nfa
has states q1
q2 q3
to q something qn and
one of our one
states of our dfa states may be
like q two and q
three right it is a set
but it is a state of dfa
so delta this state sees
this symbol is what
you just need to look up
the original delta
q2 and give the same symbol
it will return some set
of states right and the union
q3 the same symbol
if you have one more here then
union the original transition function
q4 this symbol that's why
we write transition entry
this way for every
original every state of
the original nfa within
the state of our dfa which is
which is a set of the nfs states
we look up the original interface
transition function
with the state and the same symbol here
and it will be some
set of the original and every state then
we union
lay o
after we do the union it will
become
a set of the original nf states right
then it is exactly one
of the dfa
state
so that's the construction of the
equivalent dfa
from a given enlightened
but here we haven't considered epster
because when you when nfa sees epsilon
it can go
to the
specified states right
so we just need to
introduce a notation regarding
epsilon we call it epsilon closure
so epsilon closure means
start from the states within
a dfa state by traveling along
zero or more epsilon arrows
so let's
see the example here see
so for empty set
the absence closure of empty set
is empty set right
for the sets containing only q1
the epsilon closure of this set
is what is still q1
right because traveling zero
epsilon arrows
then for q2
the epsilon closure will be first
q2 itself then
traveling from q2 to q3 so that will be
q3
okay so for q3
it's it is q3
because
can go no more places and for q4 is q4
then interesting part is goes on
q1 q2 for the set of q1
q2 the epsilon closure of q1 q2 will be
[Music]
q1 itself q2 itself
union with q1
goes to any state no q2
can traveling by one epsilon closure
ah sorry epsilon arrow to q3
right so this one will be
this union with this
so the same thing goes to q2 q3
will become q2 q3
and q2 q4 will be q2 q3 q4
and q3 q4 will be q3 q4
and goes on so by doing that
epsilon closure we just need to
change the transition function
to add
this part
and to change this part augmented
with epsom closure
and also change the star state
by absent closure
of the star state
okay because it might have
because an nfa might have something like
you start from
these states but there is
absolute epsilon epsilon arrow to
another state
so effectively start from this state
and folk twice one is the original state
and the other is the state from the
epsom closure
and it's like goes this way epson
so start from two separate states
in the beginning so we need to have
here and here then we can
construct the equivalent dfa
okay so uh firstly let's
see an example okay so
let's say we
have a nfa here
so the states q is
one two three right
remember that one here two here three
here
are not integers they are just
you know symbols or label of states okay
so do the power set
of q that will be
[Music]
these eight subsets
all possible subset right
okay so then we can uh
draw the whole thing here
so first firstly we draw
empty set
one two three
[Music]
one two one three
two three one two three
okay
then
we construct the oh sorry
then we select the not select sorry
we uh
define the star state
the star stage should be this one
but actually should be epsilon closure
of one
right and you can see that
epsilon closure would be
one itself and the traveling by epsilon
variable that would be
three so
that's why the star states of this
machine
is this one
then we start to
do the transition function
so start from empty set
i shouldn't call it empty set but start
from this state okay
so we know that it goes
to nowhere so either a or b
goes to nowhere so like this
then for one
we look up where
if you are on one
and sees a there is no
outs there is no out arc for a
right so that would be go out
that will make the transition goes to
empty set
so that's this one and the b
only uh goes two and we need to see
epsilon of two something like this
that will be still two so it goes to
2 okay so 6a and 6b
then let's considered two
okay so
when the original nfa is on two and the
c is
a that will be two and three
so two and three
and we do epsilon still two and three
so two and three here
then b that'll be three
and epsilon closure still
three so b three
okay then
three here okay
so when you are when the original nfa
is on three and this is a it will be
gold
b1 but don't forget that
epsilon closure of one is one three
so a goes to one three
and b that will be empty so
empty okay so
we have one two three
finished then let's say
one two one two we see
a one c's a
and a two c say and do union then
epsilon closure okay so once this a go
empty two c's a go two three
so m t two three epsilon closure
two three
and the b 1 6 b
goes to 2 6 b goes 3
still 2 3 but you know different
uh path so still
2 3. then
we see one three
one sees a
empty three six a
one three so empty union with one
three and the two epsilon closure
still one three right
then b once this b goes to
two and three
[Music]
c b goes to empty set so two
and uh empty set and the absolute
closure
sorry
once this b goes to two
three c b goes to zero uh not zero
empty set so empty state union with two
and two epsilon culture is still two so
b one three
six b goes to two okay then
two three so two
six a goes to two three
three six a goes to one three
so two three union with one three and
consider epsilon closure that would be
actually one two three
so two three six a
goes to one two three and two
three c 6 b 2 6 b
3 3 6 b
empty so 3 empty
epsom closure
3. okay then
finally we have one two three
so
one this a actually we can
do that like one two
and two three right
one two 6 8 go to 2 3
2 3 6 8 go to 1 2 3. so that would be 1
2 3.
so 1 2 3 cc goes back to itself
and 1 2 6 b go to 2 3
2 3 6 b goes to 3 3
and the 2 3 doing union and epsilon
closure
that will be 2 3 so this b
goes to 2 3.
okay so
we now processed the whole thing here
so you can construct these
dfa
given an fa here
okay
for this dfa we can easily see that
this one is the start state so
it is not possible
to goes to this state so it's useless
and also this state
so the two states are useless
so it can be written
as a sixth state dfa and
as a note here that such a
simplification of
dfa is not general
in in general
we will have a minimization of dfa
process
so it's it is not necessary that
you will find some useless state as
in this case okay so that would be the
example to construct the dfa
but the question remains um
unlike unlike the proof
in unlike the proof
in the cultural property of union
operation
i said that that proof that construction
is
is quite intuitive so we don't provide
a correct a correctness proof to prove
that the construct by the procedure the
constructed dfa
is really equivalent of
in that case really recognize the union
of that two languages
but in this case apparently the dfa
constructed
is kind of complicated right
i think most of can most of us
cannot readily
accept that the dfa here
is really equivalent to nfa here
the language of the dfa is really
the language of this nfa
it's kind of difficult to accept so we
need to prove that
but
in order to do the proof we need some
uh mathematical trans construction to
help
to help us and the proof here
we consider no epsilon errors for
simplicity
okay you need to do the epsilon closure
puts back to the proof then it will be
okay but
for simplicity we don't consider that
you can
try to do it in your uh by yourself
we define its extended transition
function
given one transition function okay
so the extended transition function here
is not
some new things it is a
it is merely a syntax
sugar we use a shorter
notation to express more complicated
construction
but we don't introduce new things
into the framework
so when you have a dfa that dfa
will have a transition function
right and based on this transition
function
we define extended transit function
recursively based on
this transition function how do we
define that
we define the extended charging function
for all the states of the dfa
and if nothing here which is an empty
string
then the extent transition function will
be that state
okay it is the base case
if this is not
an empty string then
we separate
the final symbol here
and the calls back the extended
transition function
and this extended transformation finally
will have
well return a state then
you just look up the original transition
function
with this state and the symbol here
and why do we want to do it because we
just
want a notation to easily express
uh
the state transition after some dfa
read a string
so for example if a dfa
has a transition function delta and
you want to know that the dfa starts
from
q0
after it reads 0 1 1
0 1 where it goes
how to express that so we use the
transition from extended transition
function here we say that
okay we use this notation
to express that okay
so according to the definition here what
will
what will it be it will become
delta delta head
right q0
q 0 0 1 1 0
and 1 right
the final one x and
a in here
then again
delta delta hat
q 0 0 1 1
the last one previous string
zero one right
then delta
delta delta delta hat
q 0 0 1
okay 1 sorry
0 1.
do that again you get
q 0
zero one
one zero one
okay so you can see that we do that
once more we get
q0 absolute
right then 0 1
1 0
1.
and what do we have here
it will be the
state right so that will be q0
so you see we use this notation to
represent
what will this dfa start from q0
read 0 1 1
0 1 goes 2.
so that's only a syntax trigger to
express this
okay so
we also define the same
extended transition function for a net
phase
transition function in the same way
so
if nothing here we have
the set of this state only
if there is something here then we
separate
the last symbol
and this part
goes to extend the transition function
and since extended transition function
will be a set
of states so for every state
in the set we do the original transition
function
so that means if you have
if you start from some set the extra
extended transition function
will represent after processing a string
what states will have process on
the same concept as the dfa extension
extended transition function
so if you have no problem with this then
we can prove that firstly
from the original nfa
start from the start state
for every string
the result will
be the same as our constructed dfa
and how do we process every possible
strings we do a induction
on the length of string
so the basis will be empty string
of which the length is zero okay
so according to our construction
according to our construction
the extended transition function of
the dfa will be this
right because it's epsom and this one by
our code
our construction it is
exactly q0 and
a set contains only q0 and the list
exactly is the nfs
extended transition function so
we have a basis then we make a
make an assumption on the for the
induction step
we assume that for
string for string of length n
they are identical
it's enough it's an assumption okay
then we look at one more
symbol the string with one more symbol
that will be
one string attach a symbol right
we want to prove they are the same
okay so this one is assumption
we want to prove this one based on that
assumption
and how do we prove that kind of
easy so left hand side we
copy it here then
we look up how dfa
how dfs extended transition function
defined so
sorry
you can go back to
copy this part back to that part
so we separate this one x a
so a here x here right
so that will be the delta
uh dfs extension transition function
this one copy here and the x
here goes back to extended transitioning
function
and the last symbol we look up
look up the original
transition function then
this part is our
hypothesis right so we can
simply replace this one
[Music]
with this one so that makes
this one okay
so we have this one
then according to
according to how we construct
m's delta where is this
this is here
according to the way we construct
the dfa transition function we can
expand to remember that the delta here
is delta n there and the delta prime
here
is delta m
sorry
delta m there okay
so
delta m is the delta prime there
and we just need to copy this part
here
and then
look up this part
there so for every p within
this part we look up
the original anaphase delta function
transition function with the same symbol
then if you have no problem with this
step
this one is exactly
an ffs extended transition function
like we defined on this page so we
write from this direction back to this
direction
okay so
we now prove that by the
by induction we prove that for every
length
of the string we know that
the result of our constructed
dfa will be exactly the same as the
result
of the original nfa
based on the result we can further prove
that
the language of the original nfa
is exactly the language of
our constructed dfa
okay so the definition
of the language of the
original nfa is that
every string start from
the start state and
after processing the string right
there will be some state
has the process will go stop
and will stop on some state
as long as one of the states
is the member of
the defined accept state
that's why we use intersection with
acceptance
non-empty then that will be
the string will be in the language right
so that's the definition of the origin
uh
language of the original nfa we already
proved that
this thing
is this right
that's what we proved in the last slide
then we rewrite
this part to this part
why can we do that because because
the definition of f1 prime
is exactly
our dfa state
has intersection with the accept states
well in f prime right so
that will be
this step
because any every one state
of the dfa represents a set
of nfa as long as it contains
an accept state of n that means
r as
a set of the anaphase state
intersection with f
noun empty
right then this one
will be in the f prime
so
the this is one dfa
state and represents
a set of nfa state
intersection with accept state
non-zero sorry now empty
if it happens then
these states must be in our
final state for the dfa and
we know that this
is exactly
the language of the dfa so
we know it's the language of
m so we prove that l of
n is l of
n okay
so that means that means
after
go through the procedure here
to construct and do a dfa
according to the given nfa
the language recognized by the
constructed nf dfa
is equal to
that of the nfa okay
so we prove that of course we consider
no
epsilon errors first here and
you can have that later so
we proved that
every nfa has an equivalent dfa
we also know that every dfa
has an equivalent nfa right
that means they are equivalent
that means the definition or
of our regular language the definition
of the term
regular language is defined on dfa
now we know nfa and the dfa are
equivalent
so we can extend the definition to
a language is regular
if and only if noun determines the
finite automaton
recognize it why can we do that
because any nfa
recognizes some language right you can
find
a dfa recognize that language
so that language is regular
okay so that's it for equivalence
of another and dfas and now we know that
you can use nfa or dfa
to handle regular language a language
can
be recognized by a dfa it must be
recognized by nfa and vice versa
so now we can use us from now on
we can use nfa for the proof
of properties of regular languages
okay