[Music]
hello everyone
let's get started with
the course
the goal of the course is to discuss
what are the fundamental capabilities
and the limitations of computers
that is we want to know the limitations
of computation
in a mathematical way firstly we need to
define what computation is
but it is a very difficult and
complicated problem
i guess many scholars and the
researchers
have tried to do that but
it seems that no one
has successfully done the job
then someone figured out another way to
do it
they defined computational models
which are
abstracts
computational machines
and of course those machines are not
physical machines are not like
something you can touch in the physical
real world
it's a it's in your
thinking but it's an abstract machine
then we discuss what this kind machine
can do to discuss
what
is the
capability and the limitation of
computation and computers
and also as i said last time
i believe many of you are not familiar
with
doing axioms definitions
and then
discuss
some theory in mathematical way
so we start from the simplest
computational models
which is
finite stem machine or final time term
if you have taken course like a
logical design or
something like that you may
have known the
finite state machine
it's very similar actually
in a way it's identical
but
here
we usually call it final content and use
slightly different notations
so what is
a finite state machine or final
temperature let's see an example
so
let's see the example on the textbook
of automatic door
if we want to
describe
the operations of an automatic door we
may
use this
we may use we may describe
automatic door this way the operations
of
an automatic door this way
so
first we simplify the whole situation
that
an
automatic door has only two
states
one is that is closed the other
is open
okay
when the door
is
closed
when the door is closed
something
happened
to trigger the transfer
the transition
of the state
so we just need to
uh
describe how the state
transit
so for this example if the door is
closed
let's say
someone
stand in front of the door
stands in front of the door
the door becomes open
right
so you have a transition here
from closed to open
then if no one
stands in front of the door or
behind the door
the door
closed
if the door is open no one
is in front of the door or behind the
door
then
it is closed
we can use this kind of
this kind of
abstract abstract computational
models to describe
the operations
of automatic doors
and of course
for this example the situation
is highly simplified for example
everyone everybody knows that
an automatic door or a common door
doesn't have only two states
it may be closed it may be opened
but
it may be you know
in between
see every door is
not either open or closed
it may open a little bit or open not
fully open
right
so it is
only
a description
to the extent you want to describe
something
some
operations
and it is a
it is an example attached to
something in the real world
then we try to abstract abstract the
whole
model the concept
into something
more
yeah abstract
so
we can see
here
is an abstract
model of the whole thing
so it's a we call it a finite automata
okay
so
how do we
describe
this kind of abstract
computational
machines
in the mathematical language
that's the problem here
and
we try to define
finite automata
this way
we say that
a finite automaton
a finite a finite automaton
is a five topple
is a five tuple
where
q
is a finite set called
the state
okay
and the sigma is also a finite set
and
it is called the alphabet
the alphabet
then we go to the fourth
item first
within
the states
within the states there is a spatial
state
we call
it star state
by star state it means when the machine
is booting up
it will start from this state
okay
and then we think
we see in the states
within the states
there are a subset
they are a subset we call
the state of accept state
okay accept state
in all times it is called
final state
okay final state that is why we usually
use use f
for accepted because
this set
was
called
final states
okay so
we have that means
a finite automaton
a finite time tone
has five components
as long as you define the five
components
you will define a finite element
and what are the five components
first you need to have a finite set of
states
and you need to have a finite set of
symbols we call the symbol set alphabets
then within the states there is a
spatial state
called star state and a subset of the
states we call
accept states
okay
and then
the third component
is a function
what function
it will map
state
with
symbol
to
some states
we call it
transition function
we call it transition function
and uh
well i personally think
transition function is
more
more similar to you know
the operations
of a program
okay
so you also can think about the whole
final tom turn is a computation machine
doing something and the behavior
is mostly described
by transition functions
and other things like states and
alphabets
they are kind of support
uh they are kind of supporting material
to transition functions
something like that but it's my personal
opinion you don't need to
believe it okay
so
let's see
the example
using the
formal description
okay
so m1 here
figure 1.6 and one here
is an example of final automaton
if we want of course we can use the
figure easily visualize the
conceptual machine abstract machine
but
in mathematics we need to describe it
formally and how to do it
how to do the description
we say that m1
is a finite automaton
then we need to describe the five
components
first one
we say that n1 states is q
okay what is q
in this case
q
has three
members q1
q2 q3
all right so we need to
clearly precisely describe
what are in the set
then alphabet
sigma
what is sigma in this case
the sigma in this case has two
symbols
zero and one
okay
but don't be confused
by using 0 and 1 here the 0 here is not
it's not the zero in integers or values
or numbers or whatever you think it is
zero here is just a symbol
there is no spatial meaning of it
we just use two different symbol and we
say that okay sigma process two kinds of
symbols one we use zero
to know
to denote it and the other one we use
one to denote it so the one
and zero here
are not integer one
and integer zero okay
then
we say that
we within
our states
q1
is the star state
okay
so
when you put up the machine the machine
operates from q1
so q1 is the start state
and we need to also need to specify
accept states
so we say that
the set
okay accept states are a set a subset
of q it's not only one state of course
in this in this example
we have only q2
as
an accepted but
you can have more or you can have zero
state okay so it's a subset anyway so in
this case
our accept state
has one main one member only which is q2
okay so we have described
four
components of m1
and then
delta the transition function
we need to describe the transition
function which actually the operates of
the whole machine
so transition function
in
final automata we described here
must be
fully defined that means you we must
describe that
when the machine is
on the state q1
and
zero happened
where it goes
so in this case we design the machine to
go q1
okay
so that's
this transition
when zero happens
q the machine if the machine is on q1
goes back to q1
and if one happens
then it goes to q2
so if 1 happen
it goes to
q2
okay
and when the machine is on
q2
when 0 happens goes to q3 so when zero
happens goes to q3
and when one happens goes back to q2 so
when one happens goes back to q2
when the machine is on q3
no matter
0 or 1 it goes to q2
so we have 2 transition 1
0 and 1
okay
so you can see that
m1 the machine m1 here the machine m1
here
must be
formally described
by
the formal description
and of course
we can use
the visualization here
more easily into into it
intuitively
describe the machine
but let me remind you that
the visualization here is not formal
it's informal
so when you are in
let's say examination
you cannot
use a figure
or a diagram
as your answer
you can use it as
assist
us
you can use it to assist
to
describe
your answer but
formal description
is the only thing we accept as the
answer
okay
so you cannot just draw some diagram and
say that okay i i have already answered
the question no we don't accept that you
have to describe it formally because
that's the mathematical way
okay
or that's what
we want you to
practice
that's very important because
if you
you can actually draw a pretty good
diagram
but
drawing diagram itself
might not be so
accurate or precise
we need to
form do
description
to make the whole thing
more precise
more accurate
so that's practice okay
so that's the
definition of finite automata
now we have
uh finite automata defined
this way so that means
whenever
you define some
five tuple
with these let's say
specification
as long as you define something
followed this kind
following this kind of description we
can say that
that thing you defined is a finite time
term
okay
then we have a finite time time like
this
the problem is the problem is
we say that it is a computational
machine and
how
and we also know that the transition
function is like this when the machine
is on q2 and c1 goes to q2
fine
then
how
does it compute and
what
does it do
okay
so let me also use a
informal example first
to describe
how the machine operates
and what
are this kind of machine
do
so
we have
two symbols for this example m1 we have
two symbols
in the alphabet one is
zero and the other is one
and let me remind you again the 1 here
and the 0 here are not integers 1 and 0.
okay so imagine that you have a
zero one strings
uh sorry you have some zero one strings
uh that has example
here
one
uh
zero one one zero zero one
okay
suppose you have one
string like this one
zero one one
zero zero one
so how m1 operates
imagine that
you turn on the power so the machine is
at
is on q1
right because q1 is the start state
then imagine that you are i don't know
playing video games or
some gambling games
you have two kinds of
tokens one kind of token is zero and the
other the other is one
then imagine that
you put the token
into the string sorry into the machine
okay
so
when you
put in one
sorry zero
then
the machine will go
well goes from q1
okay 0 right back to q1
so
q1
the start state and you put 0 here
and goes to q1
right
then you put one
so follow this transition the machine
goes to q2
so you put in one machine goes to q2
then you put one machine
stays
on q2
okay
then you put in zero
the machine goes to q3
right
then you put 0 again so machine goes to
q2 right this one
and then
you put one
into the machine
again so one
q
okay
so i guess it's pretty easy pretty
straightforward
to trace
one step uh step by step
of the operations of the machine right
any question on that i think it should
be pretty straightforward
okay
so after
okay the most important point one of the
most important point here is after
after you put in all your token
that means
if we treat
this as a string
after
each
character or symbols of the string
has been consumed by the machine now you
don't have a string right it's
all gone
then you see we check
what state
the
machine
stop
starving so in this case
after the machine
consumes
0 1 1
0 0 1 so
zero
one
the machine the machine finally
stops on q2
then we check
if q2
is a member of the accept state
if
yes in this example
yes
right
since the
since q2
is a machine of the accept states
defined
in the machine
we say that
the machine
accepts the string
0 1 1 zero zero one
okay
so
for this example if
our input string is not
1 1 0 0 1
if our input machine is
1 1 0
then
the machine will stop
on
q3
right
so if does
machine stop on q3
and in this case
q3
is not a member of
accept state
we say that
this
machine
does not accept
0 0 1 1 0
okay
so you can
think of the machine as a
as
some string processing pro string
processor
so you input a string and
it either accept the string or not
accept a string
okay
so let's say
when you
when the five components are different
they are different machines
okay
so we can see that we have m1 this way
and imagine that
we have some other machine m1 prime
and
everything
is
identical
as m1
but
the accept states of m1 prime is
let's say q2
and q3
okay
so is m1 prime
a legal finite automaton
yes it is
but uh
sorry and apparently m1 prime is
different from m1 why because you can
check that
m1 prime of course also accept
0 1 1 0 0 1
and it also accepts 0 1 1 0 right
because
q 3
is a member of m1 primes
accept states
so i used to be asked by uh
students when we talk about this
they they usually ask that uh can i have
q1 also in
uh the accept states can i have more
states
the answer are oh yes because
as long as you have uh you clearly
formally defined
a machine's five components it becomes
uh
it's
it is considered
a legal final terminal
and the different
uh difference in any
five uh in any of the five components
they are different machines so of course
you can have one more two more
states in the finite states
in the final stage in the accept states
that you own only that you are getting
different machines
okay
like you have a computer and you change
you change the cpu then it becomes
another computer they are all computers
something like this
okay
so if you
uh if if you want you can check more
strings
something like if uh
we can also have
like one one zero zero sorry
one one zero zero one zero one one one
okay
so it's pretty straightforward that's
putting the machine
one
zero
one okay so the machine accepted
something like that
okay
now
what we want to know is
how do we formally
define what i just described
right
how do we formally do that
and
it's also pretty easy
although
as
uh
regular common people like me we don't
usually talk
we don't usually speak or talk about
things in this way but
formally we define what i just described
in this way that
finite automaton m
sorry
final automaton m
since we said that a final terminal has
five tuple
right so final time term m is like this
one
we say that it accepts string w
and a string is a
sequence of the symbol from
alphabet
okay so in this case
w
is w1 w2
to w n and
each w i is
in
the alphabet
okay
oh sorry
we say m accept string w
if a sequence of states
r 0 r 1 to r n see
you have a
string length
and
to process the whole string
there will be
plus one
states
right because when the machine is booted
up
it
is on the start state and the start from
the start from the start state
you process one symbol goes to the next
one so two states
process another symbol
goes to next states then three states
so when you process n symbols
always
and plus one states
so
in this
we say that the machine
and accept string w
if
a sequence of states are 0 r 1 2 r n
in q
because q is the states of the machine
right
exists
with satisfying the three conditions
first one
r0 is the star state of the machine
and that's it let's look at the third
one first
the final
the last state
is a member of accept states of the
machine
okay
then
previous states
receive
the symbol
goes to
the next state
in the list
okay
so that means
we say n
accepts w
means
there is a sequence of
states
the machine will start from r1
and
process w1
goes to r2
r1 so it starts from r0 process w1
goes to r1 and the process w2
goes to r2
process w3
goes to r3 and so on
process wn
goes to rn
and you can see here
delta of r0 w1
exactly is r1
and the delta of r1 w2
is
r2 and the delta of r2
w3
is exactly r3 and so on
and r1
is the star state
and
go through the transition function
we get r0 r1 r2 r3
and rn
finally
rn
is a member of
accept states
so
if you can find a sequence r0 to rn
satisfying the three conditions here we
say that
and
accept
w
okay
seems complicated but actually it's
pretty straightforward
and as long as you understand why we
define this way
then
it's pretty
straightforward as i said
then we go back to our
example
okay
we say that
1 1 0
0 1 right we say that m1 accepts the
string 0 1 1 0 0 1.
i use the informal way to describe it so
the machine starts from q 1 q1 c0 goes
to q1 then
c1 goes to q2 this one stays q2 c0 goes
to
q3 and so on
finally it
ends on q2 so we say that the machine
accepts string right
according to
the definition
we say m1
accept
input string
is because we can find we actually can
find a sequence
of states
which is q1
q1
q2
q 2
q 3
and q 2.
we actually can find the sequence of
states as this one which is our r0 r1 r2
r3 r4 r5 r6
okay
we say m1 accept string w because we can
find
this
sequence of states satisfying the three
conditions
which
is
first one
r0 is q1 which is the star state
right
for second condition
q1
reads
and check delta function
q1
reads
0 then you go to q1 right
so delta of q1 0
is q1
then also q1 reads 1
delta of q1 reads 1 is q2
so is q2
and then q2
reads 1
delta of q2 with 1 is q2
q2
right
then
[Music]
goes to q3
goes to q2
stay
at q1 and q2
and the third condition
r6
which is q2
is a member of
accept states
see
so
we say that machine m1
accepts string w
not because
i do the informal
description says that okay q1 q2 q3 q1
q2 q3 stuff like that
it is because
there exists
q1 q1 q2 q2 q3 q2 q2 such a sequence of
states
satisfying
the three conditions
first one is the star state last one is
the is a member of the acceptance
and
every
state
check the machine's delta function
with the input
really goes to next state
so
really goes to next states
then we set the machine
accept the string
okay
then
let's imagine that
that's imagine that
as long as
you
have
the alphabet
of the machine
then
it is in this example the alphabet is 0
1 so let's say
imagine that you arbitrarily
uh pick a
zero one string like
one one zero zero one one one one one
zero something like that then
you
let the machine process a string you
either get accept
or
not accept right
any 0 1 string
we don't want to really try that right
now but you can imagine that any zero
one string in this case
we can put into the machine and get
an answer of accept
or get an answer of another except
right
then
then we imagine that
all strings
some machine accept
we say that
let's say if a
is the set of almost string
all strings that machine n accept
we say that
the state
the set here
is
the language of machine m
we use the notation
l of n
is a
okay
okay so
firstly
in our code in this course
in the course of formal languages this
course
language the term language has no
spatial meanings
language
is a set of strings
okay as long as it is a set of strings
we call it language
so don't
think uh don't don't don't uh think that
the language here has any special
meanings no it's just a set of strings
all right
then we define that
let's say
you
define a finite automaton this way then
you get a finite parameter and then you
imagine that for a machine m for a
finite automaton n
it will accept some some strings
okay maybe an empty set that means no
strings but doesn't matter let's say
as long as one
machine
here
then it will accept
a set of strings
don't forget that it may be empty empty
set okay but it will accept some strings
we say that all the strings accepted by
the particular machine we say the
set here
is
the language of the machine
and we write
this way
that's it so language of machine m is
the set a that's it
in this way we say that
m
recognize
a
or
previously
in all times
mathematicians say that m
accepts a
and why we change accept in this case
to recognize
because
it's easier to know
it is a
language or a string
okay
see when we say that the machine accepts
a string and if the verb accepts here
can also be
described to be used to indicate that
a language to be accepted by a machine
it will be
confusing you have to check the context
to see the a
the big a here capital a here is a
string or
a language
so in order to you know it eliminates
and
potential troubles
we try we change the verb
here to
recognize
so when you see x recognized
sorry
x recognize
y
you know that m is a machine and y is a
language
and
you see x
accepts
y
you know y is a string x is a machine
so that's
better for
descriptions and also by the
definition
this way
we know that a machine only recognize
one language
why because it's pretty straightforward
that because the language of some
machine
is
the set
of all strings accepted by that machine
right
so machine must recognize only one
language which is exactly
all the string
it accepts
okay so that's the definition
and
finally for today we said that
a language is called
a regular language
if
some finite automaton recognize it
okay
let's back to go back to the
definition here
see
we say that a final automaton is a five
tuple like this
then
you can use
within the specs
you can define a lot of finite
automatons
each finite automaton can recognize
one language
right some language
then
we say that
a language
can be recognized
by a finite element
we call
it's
a regular language
so
we use
finite automaton as computational models
and what is a
string and what is language
in the analogy here
in our way of thinking
a language
is an abstract
entity of a problem
by the problem is not
one problem instance
it's a kind of problem
for example like a traveling salesman
problem or a
scheduling problem or a
flexible manufacturing problem things
like that
and a string
is a problem instance of that problem
so we define finite hunter and we say
that
the problem can be handled by this kind
of machine
we call them
regular languages
okay so i guess that's enough for today
so
we will continue the
course
in next lecture