let's continue to
prove the equivalence of final taunta
and regular expression
last time we have proven that
if a language is described by a regular
expression
then it is regular
to prove this lemma we used
the definition of regular expression and
according to regular expression we can
construct
corresponding finite automata to any
possible
valid regular expression
that's why if a language is described
by a regular expression it is regular
because
that language can be recognized by an
nfa
and we already proved that any
nfa has a
equivalent dfa so by definition that
language
is regular okay so let's do
another direction that we want to prove
if a if a language is regular that means
if a language can be recognized
by some deterministic or
non-deterministic final automata
it can be described
by a regular expression
that means see if you have a machine
finite automata
deterministic or non-deterministic and
you can directly
use regular expression to specify
the language of that machine that we
want to
prove here
so how do we do that well basically
what we want we want to do is
to convert a dfa
into regular expression okay
since a language represented by a dfa
it is regular because that's our
deformation
so given a dfa we convert directly
converts that dfa into regular
expression
we by this way we can prove that
any regular language can be described
by regular expression okay
so before doing that
we need another
kind of machine as helper okay
so here we introduce a new machine yet
another new machine
it is called generalized
non-deterministic
finite automaton well long name but
let's call it gnfa okay
and what is a gnfa
a geometry is also a five table but uh
slightly different from what we have
previously
first one is also a finite set of states
okay a finite set of states
and the second one is also alphabet
that means the language of the machine
is composed of a sigma here
then let's say the fourth the fourth
uh component is a star state
of course q start is in
the states right and the
fifth uh fifth component is q
accept so uh gnfa has only
one accept state it's
it is uh slightly different from what we
previously have
right so the
accept states is also in
queue okay and since
the component
are different so the delta function the
definition of the transition function
delta
is also different so
for transition function
you can start from any state
to you can start from any state except
for
accept state to any state except
for start state and map to
a regular expression okay well if you
cannot
catch the definition here we have an
example
so see in the figure
it is an example for g n f a
there are four states here let's say one
two three four so
uh we write a tuple like
one two three four
that's the state right and the alphabets
will be
a b and transition function
and the state one is the star state and
the state
uh four is the final
accept state okay so that's the formal
description of the machine of course we
didn't write the delta yet
so for delta you can start you can
start from
any other state except for q accept
so that's a delta 1
2 actually we should have delta 1 1
oh no because the
you cannot go into star state so there
is no one one
and one two would be what in this case
a b star that's a regular expression
right
and one three is
uh nothing which is empty set
and actually that's a regular expression
of course the
language of the regular expression means
empty set
right and 1 4 be
b right so you can do that
from the figure and complete the formal
description
and that's our gnfa okay
so for a g and g and a glfa
you have several uh finite finite uh
states and then one of them is the q
start and the other of them
uh another of them would be q accept and
there are only one
accept states for gnfa and transition
are mapping from state to state
and the mapping would be regular
excavation
okay so how
does this machine work let's say
the formal description is like this and
pretty similar
to what we previously had and you can
compare them and check it check it but
in short
we said that a gnfa accepts a string w
in sigma star which is all possible
strings composed
by sigma right if
the string can be separate into several
parts
let's say k parts and usually k
is nothing to do with the length of the
language
the string and each of the parts
is also a string and it is possible
epson okay
but it each part of the
separated string is also in
sigma star and you can find the sequence
of states q1
q0 q1 to qk such that
three conditions are satisfied first one
is that the first stage in the sequence
is the start state of the machine and
the final one
would be the accept states of the
machine
and each for each
step
from q i minus 1
to q 1.
the corresponding string
corresponding string is
in the mapped
the language of the mapped
regular expression okay
so q w 2 is in
r 2 what is r 2
that would be
q one q
two like this
okay so that means
start from start state and when you
want to go to q1
you can use some strings
in the specified
the specified language by the
oh sorry by the
regular expression
of the transition function
okay so that's cn
uh exactly see an example then you can
get that better
let's say
if the input string is
simply b
okay so
we say that the machine can accept the
string b
why because you can let's say the state
will be 1
two three four
okay so
we can say that uh the sequence
will be the state a sequence of states
is
1 4 and
satisfy the three conditions first
the first state the first state is start
state and the final state is accept
states right
and the string b
is in the language of
delta what 1 4
which is the regular expression b
right and what is the regular
uh the language that is
b so
this g n f a accept
b let's say if you check
abstrom the empty string as input
i think the machine doesn't accept
epsilon because there are only
three uh h
out of start and you have no
empty string in it right
actually when we have a regular version
as
empty set here that means it's there's
no way from q star to three
and anything here and
here are not uh
uh does uh do and do the
the two languages do not contain empty
string so you have no way
from q star and go somewhere with empty
string
okay so no
let's say another example as
a a a
b e a okay
so we might think that uh you can go
since it's a
so it will be in this
language right because the language
would be
a a b
a b b a b
b b etc
right so a is in here
so you can go from 1 to 2
with a
then that if we go a
we go back to two right but
you will find that there is no way for
bba
here see you cannot go
this way although you think you can
think you have
a b or no va sorry so you have no way to
go
this way or you go this way
because there are empty string so you
can you know
not consuming anything and the goal here
after going here
there's no a b so you cannot go this way
you might be able to go this way with
spending 1b or 2 over
2b but this one
still there and after you arrive q
accept
not nowhere to go so it won't be able to
process the
whole string this way so
it looks like this machine cannot accept
this
this stream but yes it can
because don't forget that gnfa is
generalized non-deterministic finite
automata so
it's it has the
uh non-deterministic computation
capability
so any possible way
uh as long as one of them accept the
string
we have to consider the machine accept
the string
so which way let's see if
um if we go to
from 1 state 1 we go to
state 2 by using a right like this
then
we go another we use another a
go through this transition
to three stage three
we can do that right because what is a
star
a star means empty string a
a a a a a et cetera
right and then we
use this transition
go back to three okay
then we go through this transition
with empty string right because a a star
what is a star again it is empty string
a a a a a a
etc even numbers of a's
right so have an
abstract here
then go back to
two finally we use ba
go through release arc what is the
language here
the language will be a b and b
a two strings so
finally four so you see this string
in one computational branch can be
separate
as a a
a b epsilon
b a and the corresponding
sequence of states would be 1
2 3 3
2 4. and the satisfying the three
condition that
one is the start state four is the
accept state
and each separated string is in
is in the language specified
by the regular expression of the output
of the transition function of the two
states
right so you can you see that for
example for
2 3 the delta function
2 3 what is it
specified specify a star
right and the string a here
is really in
the language of a star
right which is empty string
a two a's three a's
etc right
so that's the that's how
gnfa's operate
so finally we can see that uh if you
want this string to process
b b b b let's say this string
you will find that it cannot go this way
not this way
only this way but this way in
for this language there is only one b
right b so after going through this
transition then you still have something
cannot process because there's no way
out of
q accept so no and yes
so that's the example of the operation
of gnf8
okay so if you have no
problem here then you can think about
the machines we have learned
for now and we have
dfa we have nfa and now we have gnfa
and of course like uh we when we
introduced
an fa we are talk we were talking about
uh
since we have a new machine and we
actually
don't know what kind of languages this
this new new machine can handle or
recognize
and now we have yet another new machine
gnfa
we don't know that either
but it is easy to see that
a dfa a dfa is really
a special case of gnfa okay
although uh they seem pretty different
but actually it's very easy to see that
by doing a conversion let's say
if you have a dfa like the
m1 we have here okay
so uh what
should we do for the conversion it's
pretty easy
you add one more state
as the new start state of the gnfa we
want to construct
and then and other new stars
sorry another state which will be the
accept state
and since gnfa is
uh non-deterministic okay and it has
regular expression on the transition we
add
absolute to the original
start state of the dfa and from
the accept states we add epsilon to our
new
accept state okay if you have multiple
accept states of the
dfa you for example if q3
is also us and accept states in the
original dfa
we also do this
okay for example and the original
accept state is no longer
accept states in our geon effect it's a
common state only that
it has only that it will has
will have a abstract as regular
expression
to the new accept states
okay and then the
interesting part is that we can treat
we can consider all the
symbol see that would be symbols
for the original dfa here we
directly make them
regular expressions okay
so for regular expression of 0
what language it specifies that will be
only one string zero right
and for example in here that would be
one something like this so here
will be
zero and one
right then we just need to
change that like uh change data type
and interpret the transition at
differently than we finished
we actually finished the construction
so formally described our new gene fa
converted from m1 will be
at two more states right
so five states and sigma is
also still 0 1 and q
not q1 anymore that would be
s right and accept state is a
there's no set here it's a
s accept states and for transition
function
it's not the of this type
anymore it will be pre uh slightly
complicated that would be abs are sorry
not episode
s 2
q 1 map to f zone
and what is s 2 q 2
and the q 3
that will be empty and mt so you see
that
uh in the g in gnfa
all the edges we don't draw on the
diagram that means
we you can consider there
are ages between all the possible pairs
of
pairs of states but many of them
there's no way to go on many of them
like
q3 to here it actually
is empty set and for example
there is an edge here but empty set
because
you cannot consume some part of the
input string to go that
uh state so in general phase like this
okay so we can
easily complete the transition
function for the constructed gnfa
so the new gnfa
constructed from m1 okay
the next question is why
can we say that okay m1 here
is the new gnf is is equivalent
as recognizing the identical language
to our newly constructed unifa
because it's pretty easy from the
definition
okay see from the definition
of the acceptance of a
dfa let's say if you have a dfa here
the this dfa accepts string
if a sequence of state
exists with the satisfying three
condition right
okay then by using our construction you
can easily
see that if there is a string satisfying
the condition
here then for the separate
for a separation for how the uh string
is divided
we add f song in the front of it
and f zone
append an epson to the end and
for the sequence we have our new star
state
and new accept state
okay then it's pretty easy to see that
this one let's say r minus 1
is our star state and r
n plus 1 is our accept state
and the definition
the condition for accept
the string here can convert
to the definition of acceptance of a
string of gnfa here
because everything is the same only that
you have a step from
s to the original
start state and when you accept the
string
it goes to our new accept
accept state with nothing right
so everything can be accepted by
this dfa will be accepted
by our newly construct
dnfa gnfa sorry and
vice versa because
when you when the newly constructed gnfa
accepts some string
the same thing happened you just need to
remove the start state
and the access state and the middle part
satisfying the definition of acceptance
of
the dfa right so as if
any for any input string
see for any input string
you add epsilon epsom here then
it goes from s to q one which is the
star state of the original dfa
and one of the accept states
of the dfa and two
our gnfa okay
so that's why it's easy to see that
the constructed gnfa is equivalent to
the original
dnfa because they recognize
exactly the same language
that's why i said we can consider that
dfa is a special case of gnfa
because every dfa
you can convert to a an equivalent
gnft so that also means
the language recognized
by gnfa
is a is possibly a superset
of regular language right
it cannot it can be more but not less
at least regular language so we know
that
legal language would be equal to
or a subset of the languages
recognized by gnfa
okay
now here comes the interesting part
when we check gnfa you can
see something interesting that see
from qstart
to queue accept as this example
you can go through
this way directly
to kill accept by
spending strings within
the language here right you can also do
this and repeat here
and then go here
of course you can also do another
possible way
like here here and here
but let's think about
this state okay
if you want if you want to get rid of
this state
it is possible why because
you just need to consider
the effect of the existence
of this of this state
what do i mean for example
for this gnfa
we have this
path and this page and this path right
except for this one we have the three
page
and as long as
all possible strings
leading some state to another
can be preserved this state
no longer need to be
here so full
example of this path only for this path
okay they can we can do
this one and go in through this
state and go to
kill accept if we want to
get rid of it we just need to
make what
can be consumed
on the path
we keep everything here
so we union with you can do
a b start right and
several times a a infinite uh indefinite
times of a a and then
a b b a
concatenate with this right
so if we add this one which is
a b and repeat on a a
and contain it with a b or b a
all possible strings are preserved
by this part right just for this path
okay just for this path so for this path
you we just need to add
this part and this part
repeat and this part
and the same goes to this one
then after considering all
effects we can get a get rid of these
states
okay so simply put
if we want to get rid of some state
we consider remember that all
possible pairs all possible pairs
of states okay
and how do we preserve the
path so the original one here
and the union with from this
state goes to this state
repeat on the read
state here and then r3
so r1 contain it with r2
star because you can you don't need to
stay here but you can
also do indeed definite numbers of loop
and then q and r3
so considering all pairs then you can
get rid of that state
okay so the procedure will be
here
changing the transition function
and then get rid of that state
so that's uh practice this whole thing
then you can know that firstly start
from dfa
okay let's say we have a two-state dfa
and like we already introduced that
we add one more
state as a new star state of our gnfa
and then uh one more new stage for
accept states
and we add epsilon and
epsilon and we treat
all the original symbols as
regular expressions okay then the gnfa
is constructed right then
we want to get rid of the state
so let's follow the example on the
textbook
first so if we want to get rid of two
right we need what uh
what path is we need to consider we need
to consider
as a as
one 1 a
why this because that's all possible
passes
all possible okay because there's
nothing out of a
and there's nothing 2s
okay so we don't have one s we don't
have a s
and we don't have a1 so all possible
paths are s1 1a and sa
so consider if we consider as
1 okay this path
consider this path what should we
write on s1 remember that
you need to get rid of r2 sorry 2
right state 2. so
r4 for s1 is epsilon that will be
epsilon
that's r4 in the previous
slide right and
union with
what is r1 here
r1 r2
r3 okay
so there's no uh arc from
s22 that means it's
empty set as regular expression and also
this one empty set as
regular expression so that will be
empty set and
r2 star then continue with
empty stat okay
so empty set container with anything
cancel out that will be empty set and
the union with empty set
only alpha which is epsilon so that's
why
epsom here the epsilon here is not
a copy of epsilon here
it is after operated all the
possibilities
still epsilon okay
then we consider
s a okay that's step by step s1 as
a so sa initially
is mt set because there's nothing there
right so r4 here
is empty set that'll be r4
then what is r1 still empty set
and then r2
a cup b and r3 epsilon here
so r1
r2 r4
okay but you can see that still empty
so nothing draws here
okay that would be empty
then we consider what
one a
okay so for one a
directly r4 nothing here so it's empty
so alpha is empty then
r1 what is r1 r1 here is the
b here okay b here
then r2 is still
a cup b star and
r3 empty empty string
so
union with empty sets you don't need to
write that
content is concatenate with empty string
you don't need that
so that's the regular expression here
okay see we can see the old possibility
here
so we got this one
here then
we want to get rid of one there's only
one path
to consider s2a so that would be
empty set which is r4 right r4 here
and then r1
r2
r 3
okay so we don't need to write this
and continue it with f song don't need
to write this
so that's the answer
okay so the interesting part is
see from s to a
all possible strings
apparently indicated
and specified by the regular expression
and what is the all possible string here
we know that this gnfa
is equivalent to this dfa
because their language
is identical
and after the process
here we make the whole gnfa
two states and
for the transition function mapping
star state to accept states
to this regular expression that
means
this regular expression specify
describes the language of
the gnfa so describe the language
of the dfa
so all possible regular languages
can be described by
regular expression and we know that all
languages
describing by regular expression
are regular right our previous
uh lesson so
we know that gnfa
and the language
recognized by gnfa is exactly regular
language
as a note here that uh
when we have gnfa
the order of the states
that we get rid of
may change the final result of the
regular expression but they
will describe the stand the same
language
only that their experience their
appearance may be different okay
so if in the examination
a gnfa need to be simplified
to only a star state and
and accept accept states to extract the
regular expression
at least in my examination we will give
the order
for you to get rid of the states
otherwise the result
may be different although they described
the same language
and for this
simple example in a textbook you
actually
have the same result if you do like
one first and then get rid of two
and you will give you will get the same
result
but generally may you may not
give that have the same result if the
the order is different okay
so what we have now
what we have firstly
uh in this chapter firstly
we define the effect
right after defining dfa we define
regular languages based on dfa
we said that any language
can be recognized by dfa
are regular that's our definition
then we introduce
final time top with the capability of
non-deterministic computation
and we prove that
any dfa is a special case of
nfa right it's pretty simple you just
need to rewrite the
transition function basically and we
also have a
theorem that every nfa
has an equivalent dfa so
the two kinds of computational model is
equivalent right then
we introduce our e regular expression
and firstly we
prove that any language
described by regular expression
we can simply construct a corresponding
nfa that's that means
every language described by regular
expression
are regular languages right
then we define
gnfa
and any dfa
is a special case of gnfa right you add
two more states
and treat all the symbols of the
original dfa
as regular expression and add
epsilon transition from new start state
to the original start state
and the ad transition epsilon transition
to all original accept states to the
new accept state of gnfa then you get
an equivalent one finally
we just proved that we can
simplify or we can delete some states of
gnfa
and finally gets the regular
expression describing
all possible strings in the language
of that gnfa right
so that means all the four
of the four computational models here
dfa nfa gnfa and regular expression
recognize regular
languages right
dfa is our
base for definition and
you have a dfa you can convert to
convert it to
nfa you have a dfa you can convert it
beer gnfa to regular expression
and you can convert between the four
any uh between the four computational
models
so the four models here i couldn't
and oh they can do
regular languages
okay